[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The main objective of transportation is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Economical transport of goods",
            "b) Economical transport of passengers",
            "c) To generate revenue",
            "d) Safe economical and efficient transport of goods and passengers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The main objective of a good transportation system is to provide safe economical, efficient transportation for the facility of passengers and the transport of goods."
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The factors influencing the cost of transportation are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Supply",
            "b) Demand",
            "c) Both supply and demand",
            "d) Cost of land"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Increased productivity of various items such as agricultural and their distribution can lower the cost of products. The cost of transportation substantially reduces prices."
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "Which is the most flexible type of transportation available?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roadway",
            "b) Railway",
            "c) Waterway",
            "d) Airway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The other 3 types of transport systems have to depend upon the roads to reach their destination point from the terminals that is railway station, harbours and airports."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "The transportation system that requires a low initial investment among the following is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roadway",
            "b) Railway",
            "c) Harbour",
            "d) Airport"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Roadway requires a cheaper initial investment when compared to the other 3 networks and it is the only system that provides equal facility for everyone in the society."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "The PMGSY aims to connect all villages under a population of 500 by which year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2003",
            "b) 2004",
            "c) 2005",
            "d) 2007"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The PMGSY aims to connect all the villages of the population above 1000 by 2003 and population below 500 by 2007 it later became a part of bharat nirman programme."
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "The road density in India in km per 100 sq. km land area in 2008 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 110",
            "c) 129",
            "d) 150"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The road density is the mean length of state roads per 100km2 so it is highly uneven in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "The PMGSY was launched in the year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2000",
            "b) 2002",
            "c) 2003",
            "d) 2004"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The PMGSY was launched in the year 2000. The main aim of this program was to connect the rural roads by the year 2007."
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "The current road length in India is in which position in the world?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st",
            "b) 2nd",
            "c) 3rd",
            "d) 4th"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total roadway length in India is around5, 532,482km in march 2015 which is the 2nd largest network in the world."
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "The current highway development works in India are undertaken by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) NHAI",
            "b) Govt. of India",
            "c) State governments",
            "d) NHDP"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The highway works all across the country are undertaken by NHAI, It was formed in 1988 and it has mandate to follow all the NHDP (national highway development program) which is implemented in phases."
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "The scope of highway engineering is divided into how many parts.",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The scope of highway engineering is divided into 2 parts called phases and details. In these phases overall review is given and in the details it is planned in detail."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The main features of the roman road do not include the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) They were built straight",
            "b) They were strong",
            "c) They excavated soft soil till hard strata was obtained",
            "d) The total thickness was 0.75m to 1.2m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The romans built roads by excavating till the hard strata they were much stronger than required for animal drawn carts that time."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "The tresaguet method of laying roads was developed in the year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1764",
            "b) 1774",
            "c) 1800",
            "d) 1796"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The tresaguet method was developed in 1764 AD in France after the fall of Roman Empire, in later years better methods were developed."
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "The method of providing a definite cross slope by varying thickness of foundations under roads was proposed by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tresauguet",
            "b) Metcalf",
            "c) Telford",
            "d) Macadam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Telford insisted to provide a definitely varying cross slope by varying the thickness under the foundation of stones."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "The cross slopes provided for drainage water under Macadam’s construction road is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 10",
            "b) 1 in 20",
            "c) 1 in 36",
            "d) 1 in 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slope provided is 1 in 36, it was proposed by Macadam. He also completely changed the construction methods that were used earlier."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The broken stones that were used in the construction of roads in macadam’s construction were?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10mm and 20mm",
            "b) 20mm and 40mm",
            "c) 30mm and 50mm",
            "d) 50mm and 100mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bigger stones that were passing through 100mm sieve were used at the bottom and compacted and the smaller stones that were passing through 50mm were used at the top of the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "The Indian Roads Congress was formed in the year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1928",
            "b) 1934",
            "c) 1929",
            "d) 1930"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Indian Roads Congress was formed in the year 1934 after a recommendation from the jayakar committee after a meeting in year 1928 and CRF was formed in 1929."
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "A research organisation that was formed for the research and development organisation works related to roads was?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indian Roads Congress",
            "b) Central Research Institute",
            "c) Central road found",
            "d) NHAI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The jayakar committee recommended that a research board should be formed for all research and development works related to roads and it was formed in 1950."
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "The first 20 year development plan is also called as?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nagpur road plan",
            "b) Lucknow road plan",
            "c) Bombay road plan",
            "d) Delhi road plan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The First 20 year development plan conference was held in Nagpur, hence it is also called a Nagpur road plan, second was held in Mumbai and third in Lucknow."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "The east west corridor of National highway connects which of the following cities?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delhi-Bombay",
            "b) Bombay-Madras",
            "c) Kolkata-Vadodara",
            "d) Porbandar- Silichar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Phase II of NHDP consists of linking the east west corridor from Porbandar in Gujarat to Silichar in Assam."
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Primary system of roads consists of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) Expressway",
            "c) National highway and Expressway",
            "d) State highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Primary system consists of National Highway and expressway. The secondary system consists of State highway and other Major District Roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "The 4th 20 year road development plan aims for vision in which year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2021",
            "b) 2022",
            "c) 2024",
            "d) 2025"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The 4th 20 year development plans aims for vision 2021. But however it was well before 2000."
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "The National Highway network should be expanded so that no part of a country is more than 50km away from NH is policy of which twenty year road development plan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1st 20 year road development plan",
            "b) 2nd 20 year road development plan",
            "c) 3rd 20 year road development plan",
            "d) 4th 20 year road development plan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In the 3rd year road development plan it was proposed that the national highway should be expanded such that no part of the nation should be 50km away from a national highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "The phases of highway planning do not include the following?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Assessment of road length requirement",
            "b) Preparation of master plan",
            "c) Showing the phasing of a plan in five year plan",
            "d) Financing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Financing of the highway is done after the planning of the highway after getting approval from the government, before the assessment, preparation and DPR are prepared."
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "Which type of roads can be utilized during monsoon?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unpaved roads",
            "b) Gravel roads",
            "c) Fair weather roads",
            "d) Bituminous roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bituminous roads are convenient to use compared to the other roads because they can easily drain off the water and are comfortable to use during rainy season. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "The Nagpur plan classified the roads based on ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Location",
            "b) Function",
            "c) Location and function",
            "d) Annual daily traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Nagpur plan classified the roads based on location and function into 5 categories namely National Highway, State Highway, Major District Road, Other District Road, Village Road."
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "The roads that connect the district headquarters to important city of other state is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) National Highway",
            "b) State Highway",
            "c) Major district road",
            "d) Other district road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A State Highway is a highway that connects the district headquarters to other important cities in another state."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "The arterial roads are a classification of which type of roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rural roads",
            "b) Urban Rods",
            "c) National highway",
            "d) State highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Urban roads are classified into Arterial roads, Sub arterial roads, Collector streets and Local streets."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "The rectangular pattern of roads has been adopted in which Indian city?",
        "Options": [
            "a) New Delhi",
            "b) Chandigarh",
            "c) Hyderabad",
            "d) Mumbai"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Chandigarh city was planned by assuming the rectangular pattern. But by this pattern operation of traffic has been a problem."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "The Nagpur plan formulae assumed which type of pattern?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Star and grid",
            "b) Star and circular",
            "c) Hexagonal",
            "d) Circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Nagpur plan assumed star and grid pattern in which it assumed to connect all the nearby important cities and villages to the National capital."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The Nagpur plan conference was held in which year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1941",
            "b) 1942",
            "c) 1943",
            "d) 1947"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Nagpur plan conference was held in 1943 which was the first 20 year development plan. The main target of the plan was to achieve 16km road density per 100sq.km."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "The highway research Board was set up in which year?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1947",
            "b) 1953",
            "c) 1963",
            "d) 1973"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The highway research board was set up in the year 1973 by IRC to give good guidance for road development in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "The second 20 year development plan conference was held in which city?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Nagpur",
            "b) Bombay",
            "c) Madras",
            "d) Lucknow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The second 20 year development plan conference was held in Bombay, their target was to achieve road length of 32km but they achieved 34.8km."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "Planning is based on _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Factual data",
            "b) Analysis",
            "c) Scientific data",
            "d) Factual data and analysis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Planning based on factual data and analysis may be considered scientific and sound."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "The planning survey consists of how many numbers of studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The planning survey consists of the four studies namely\nEconomic studies\nFinancial studies\nTraffic studies\nEngineering studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "The estimates are studied in which type of studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Economic studies",
            "b) Financial studies",
            "c) Traffic studies",
            "d) Engineering studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The details to be collected during economic studies are useful in estimating the requirements, cost involved in the project and economic justification."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "The revenue from road transport sector is studied in which type of studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Economic",
            "b) Financial",
            "c) Traffic",
            "d) Engineering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sources of income, excise duty, registration charges and tax all are studied in financial studies only."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "The accident cost analysis is estimated by conducting ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Origin and destination",
            "b) Traffic survey",
            "c) Transportation facilities",
            "d) Geometric design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The accident cost analysis, trends in road accidents and facilities all are estimated by conducting traffic survey, origin and destination studies are for trips and geometry for the facility."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "The topographic survey is conducted to estimate which of the following characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Engineering",
            "b) Traffic",
            "c) Financial",
            "d) Soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The engineering studies are conducted to assess topography, soil, location and classification of existing roads and other developments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "The master plan may not be prepared for ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Village",
            "b) City",
            "c) State",
            "d) Country"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The master plan is prepared after interpretation of small plans in different phases. It may be prepared for a city, district, state or even country."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The determination of optimum length is based on ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Saturation system",
            "b) Geometric design",
            "c) Type of highway",
            "d) Length of highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The determination of optimum length is based on the saturation system based on U.S system of highway planning."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "The final step after fixing the optimum length of the road is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Financing",
            "b) Construction",
            "c) Phasing",
            "d) Preparation of master plan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The final step after fixing the optimum length is phasing of the road program before the construction, after financing and master plan the construction is under taken."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "The utility unit as per saturation system for a population of less 1001 to 2000 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25",
            "b) 0.50",
            "c) 1.00",
            "d) 2.00"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The utility unit is a factor that is used to decide the priority given to the users for optimum utilization of road and it is 1.00 for a population of 1001-2000, it increases based on the population."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "As per the Nagpur plan, the un-surfaced roads were meant for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) State highway",
            "c) Major district road",
            "d) Other district road and village road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Nagpur plan classified the roads into two categories, category one was meant for the national highway, state highway and major district road. The un-surfaced roads were meant for other district roads and village roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "The total length of the first category roads was calculated by adding up the sum of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) NH+SH+MDR",
            "b) NH+SH",
            "c) SH*2",
            "d) NH+2SH+MDR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The category one type of roads consisted of national highway, state highway and major district roads. The length was calculated by adding all the three types of roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "What was the development allowance assumed in the Nagpur plan?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 15%",
            "d) 25%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The development allowance was assumed as 15% and in this plan the length of the railway track also was deducted, this was not like the previous 20 year plan."
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "During the development of the roads maximum priority is given to which type of road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) State highway",
            "c) Major district road",
            "d) Village road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum priority during construction of any road is given to national highway as they connect across length and breadth of the entire country."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "The total length of highways in 2001 in km was __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 56000",
            "b) 56756",
            "c) 56750",
            "d) 57000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The total length of NH achieved in 2001 was 5700km against a planned length of 66000km."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "The total area of a state is 2500km. Calculate the length of MDR.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 km",
            "b) 200 km",
            "c) 300 km",
            "d) 400 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Length of MDR=Area of the state/12.5=2500/12.5=200km."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "The tertiary road system consists of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) State highway",
            "c) Major district road",
            "d) Other district road and village road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As per the 2nd 20 year road development plan the primary system consists of national highway and state highway. The secondary system consists of state highway. The tertiary system consists of other district road and village road."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "The ‘rural road development plan: Vision 2025’ aims to provide basic access to villages in how many phases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Vision: 2025 aims at providing accessible facilities to villages in 3 phases by giving priority to the population in the village."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "Expressways should be constructed along __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Congested cities",
            "b) Major traffic corridors",
            "c) Along with highways",
            "d) Small cities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Expressways should be constructed along major traffic corridors for the convenience of passengers to travel safely and comfortably."
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "The maximum number of cities and towns are connected by which type of highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) State highway",
            "c) Major district road",
            "d) Village road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The national highway connects most of the cities and towns in the country. State highway connects in the state, village road in villages and other roads connect the remote areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "The changes in gradient and vertical curve are covered under which type of alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal alignment",
            "b) Vertical alignment",
            "c) Geometric design",
            "d) Highway specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The changes in gradient and vertical curves are covered under the vertical alignment, whereas the remaining three are covered under horizontal alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "The improper alignment of road will not result in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in construction cost",
            "b) Increase in maintenance cost",
            "c) Increase of population",
            "d) Increase in accidents"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The increase of population does not depend on the alignment of the road, whereas improper construction and maintenance lead to accidents."
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "The basic requirement of alignment should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Short",
            "b) Easy",
            "c) Safe",
            "d) Short, easy, safe and economical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The alignment of the road should be short, safe, easy and economical for users and engineers."
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The economical option during the construction of a road around a hill is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cut the hill",
            "b) Provide a tunnel",
            "c) Provide a road around the hill",
            "d) Look for other alternative approaches"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most economical option is to provide a road around the hill. In this alternative approach is not advisable as it has to pass either through the hill or nearby the hill."
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "Obligatory points through which the alignment should not pass are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Religious structure and costly structures",
            "b) Intermediate towns",
            "c) Important cities",
            "d) Important places of worship"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The obligatory points through which alignment should not pas include religious structures and costly structures because destroying them would require a lot of compensation."
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "The desire lines are prepared for the study of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic flow",
            "b) Origin and destination",
            "c) Growth of traffic in the future",
            "d) Anticipated traffic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The desire lines are lines which study the traffic flow from origin and destination."
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "Which of the following types of roads are most preferred for highways?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cement concrete roads",
            "b) Gravel roads",
            "c) Bituminous roads",
            "d) Unpaved surfaces"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most preferred type of road is bituminous roads. They are cheap for initial construction when compared to other types of surfaced roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "The stability of slopes is considered while designing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) State highway",
            "c) Hill roads",
            "d) District roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slope stability is important during the design of hill roads, because it may have a danger of landslides."
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "The coefficient of lateral friction as recommended by IRC is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.15",
            "b) 0.40",
            "c) 0.35",
            "d) 0.30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The coefficient of lateral friction recommended by IRC is 0.15 and it lies between 0.3-0.4 for longitudinal friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "The resisting length should be kept __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) minimum",
            "b) Maximum",
            "c) Depends on gradient",
            "d) Depends on rise and fall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The resisting length should be kept as low as possible for gradient purposes, if it is maximum then there will be a problem with the gradient."
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "The surveys of highway alignment are completed in how many stages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The surveys are completed in 4 stages namely map study, reconnaissance, preliminary survey and detailed survey."
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "The maps in India related to topography are prepared by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Geological survey of India",
            "b) Survey of India",
            "c) NHAI",
            "d) GOI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the maps related to topography in India are prepared by survey of India, NHAI is for highway alignment and geological survey of India for any rocks exploration, government of India is the finance aid for all."
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "The survey in which details are covered roughly but not accurately is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reconnaissance",
            "b) Rough survey",
            "c) Map study",
            "d) Detailed study"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The reconnaissance survey consists of studying the details in the field roughly which are not covered in the map study."
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "The soil survey is conducted in which of the following survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preliminary survey",
            "b) Reconnaissance survey",
            "c) Map study",
            "d) Topography study"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The preliminary survey consists of collecting topographical data, soil survey and other data, in reconnaissance survey rough survey is done, map study is for a plan."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "A closed loop used for survey purpose is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open traverse",
            "b) Closed traverse",
            "c) Primary traverse",
            "d) Secondary traverse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A traverse is a closed loop used for survey purpose, if it is open then it is called as open traverse."
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "Expand GPS?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Global position satellite",
            "b) Global perception satellite",
            "c) Global position system",
            "d) Geographical position system"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: GPS –Global position system is a modern technique used for survey. GIS is also used for weather report and other applications."
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "The intervals for levelling work in rolling terrain are taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50m",
            "b) 30 m",
            "c) 45 m",
            "d) 40 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the rolling terrain the interval is considered as 50m and in hilly terrain is taken as 30m."
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "What is the first step in a preliminary survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Primary traverse",
            "b) Map study",
            "c) Detailed survey",
            "d) Detailed project report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step in preliminary survey is to establish primary traverse followed by a survey and detailed project report."
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "The surface thickness of the pavement is decided based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HFL",
            "b) MFL",
            "c) MSL",
            "d) HFL and MSL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The HFL is the height till which water raised during recent floods, to avoid the flooding of roads they are always kept above HFL. "
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "The key map size should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20*22 cm",
            "b) 32*20 cm",
            "c) 32*32 cm",
            "d) 20*32 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The key map shows the proposed site and important places, the key map should not exceed 22*20cm in size."
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "The index map shows __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Topography",
            "b) Soil",
            "c) Area of the site",
            "d) Plan"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Index map is used for general topography. They are usually prepared in 32*20 cm map."
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "Detailed size drawings are prepared in which sheet?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A1",
            "b) A2",
            "c) A3",
            "d) A4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The detailed plans of drawings are prepared in A2 sheets. They are usually 60*42cm in size."
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "The cross sections should be drawn for every __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10m",
            "b) 20m",
            "c) 50m",
            "d) 100m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cross section should be drawn for every 100m or wherever there is an abrupt change in the level."
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "The approximate cost of construction evaluated for the project is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Project report",
            "b) Project feasibility",
            "c) Estimate",
            "d) Detailed project report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The approximate cost of a project before the construction is called an estimate."
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "The report that includes all the works including soil, bridges, topography, material studies and drainage studies is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Feasibility report",
            "b) Detailed project report",
            "c) Survey report",
            "d) Primary report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Detailed project report or DPR is the report that is created after all the surveys and estimates have been prepared for a final review."
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "The planning, design and construction of either a network of new roads or road link is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway project",
            "b) Highway estimate",
            "c) Highway interlinking",
            "d) Highway design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The highway project includes planning, designing and execution of new roads or providing links between existing roads, the design is for geometry and interlinking word is not so appropriate and estimate is prepared for every highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "Highway should be planned for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present requirements",
            "b) Traffic developments",
            "c) Traffic studies",
            "d) Present requirements and future requirements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A highway should be planned such that the present and future requirements of the highway are satisfied."
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "The New highway project is divided into how many stages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The new highway project is divided into (i) Selection of route, alignment and geometric design. (ii) Collection of materials (iii) Construction stages including quality control."
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "A part of land that is acquired during the initial stages of construction for future expansion is called ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerb",
            "b) Footpath",
            "c) Right of way",
            "d) Camber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Right of way is a part occupied either by the highway or railway by paying some compensation to the owners for future expansion which may have kerb, footpath and camber."
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "Which method is recommended by IRC for flexible pavements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CBR",
            "b) IRC 6",
            "c) IRC 21",
            "d) IRC 58"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The CBR method is recommended by IRC because it gives very reliable accuracy as the test depends on soil characteristics, IRC 6,21 and 58 are the code books for various pavement design."
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "Inspection of the site is done in which survey?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preliminary",
            "b) Secondary",
            "c) Reconnaissance",
            "d) Final report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reconnaissance survey includes the inspection of the site, soil, material and construction materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Road roughness is tested by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bump integrator",
            "b) RTRRMS",
            "c) GIS",
            "d) UI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The road roughness is tested by bump integrator which is measured in mm/km and is classified into various types based on unevenness index value."
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "To minimize the cost of the project the most suitable method is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CPM",
            "b) PERT",
            "c) CPM and PERT",
            "d) Normal distribution curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: CPM is mostly used in major projects, CPM is cost oriented whereas PERT is useful only for research purposes, normal distribution curve is followed by CPM."
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "The highly flooded areas should be re aligned by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing additional thickness of the pavement",
            "b) Providing suitable layers of pavement",
            "c) Providing appropriate camber",
            "d) Providing higher geometric specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The existing road can be re aligned only by providing a thickness of pavement because the camber cannot be changed, so the additional thickness is the only option available."
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "Embankments are provided on a highway near ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Important cities",
            "b) Religious structure",
            "c) Railway tracks and highly flooded area",
            "d) Costly structures"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The embankments are provided mostly near the highly flooded area, embankments near the railway tracks may be provided or may not be required it depends on the railway track."
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "The drawing for re alignment shows the existing road, proposed re alignment, contours and all other features it is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plan",
            "b) Elevation",
            "c) Cross section",
            "d) Longitudinal section"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The plan shows all the above features, whereas the sections show existing roads, ground elevation, beginning and end of transition curves."
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "The DPR consists of how many components?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DPR consists of report, estimate and drawing making it three components."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "The first step in the detail checklist of DPR is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Executive summary",
            "b) Background",
            "c) Roadway features",
            "d) General details of the project"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The executive summary is the details that are prepared after the field work in the site has been completed."
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "The name of the work and project details is managed under which category of DPR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Executive summary",
            "b) Background",
            "c) Roadway details",
            "d) General details"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the background of the project name, scope of service, data source, importance and economics of the project are managed."
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The roadway features include the study of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accidental analysis",
            "b) Geometric design",
            "c) Route alignment",
            "d) Safety"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The roadway features are studied for route selection, route alignment, environmental factors, cross section elements, traffic studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "The final step in the specifications and design of roadway elements is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specifications",
            "b) Design elements",
            "c) Geometric design",
            "d) Safety and audit of the design elements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: After all the design requirements are calculated and if they are finalized the last step is to check the safety of the design elements."
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a structure constructed for drainage purposes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aqueduct",
            "b) Syphon aqueduct",
            "c) Level crossing",
            "d) Pitot tube"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A pitot tube is an instrument which is used to measure the velocity of water in rivers and streams."
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "The strength of the materials can be checked by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Visual inspection",
            "b) Quality control",
            "c) By asking the manufacturer",
            "d) By referring to various codes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The materials should always be tested in a laboratory for accurate and exact results quality check should always be conducted."
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "For small projects which type of method is used for the calculation of project time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Milestone chart",
            "b) Bar chart",
            "c) PERT",
            "d) CPM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: For small projects, the completion time may be evaluated by bar chart, milestone chart may be used when all the critical activities are required."
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Which of the following is prepared first during estimate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Schedule of rates",
            "b) Rate analysis",
            "c) Detailed cost estimate",
            "d) Detailed project"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step in the preparation of estimates is a schedule of rates followed by rate analysis and detailed cost estimate."
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "The site amenities are covered under which of the items of DPR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Background",
            "b) Abstract",
            "c) Miscellaneous",
            "d) Estimate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The site amenities, diversion of roads, road side plantation and other facilities are covered under miscellaneous items, background and abstract are the important aspects, estimate are also very important."
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "The design of horizontal and vertical alignments, super elevation, gradient is worst affected by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of vehicle",
            "b) Width of vehicle",
            "c) Speed of vehicle",
            "d) Height of vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: All the geometric design features are worst affected by velocity of the vehicle only."
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "The most raised portion of the pavement is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Super elevation",
            "b) Camber",
            "c) Crown",
            "d) Kerb"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most elevated or the highest portion of a pavement is called as a crown, whereas camber is the portion that is raised for drainage purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "The extra width of pavement is provided on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal curve",
            "b) Width of pavement",
            "c) Length of pavement",
            "d) Super elevation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Extra width of the pavement is provided on horizontal curve to avoid the skidding, if the vehicle negotiates the curve then the centrifugal force will act towards outside and there is a chance of skidding, to avoid this extra width is provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "Transition curve is introduced in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal curve",
            "b) Circular curve",
            "c) Between horizontal curve and circular curve",
            "d) Vertical curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A transition curve is introduced between horizontal curve and circular curve, the transition curve slowly introduces the centrifugal acceleration to avoid the danger of skidding."
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "The most important factor that is required for road geometrics is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SSD",
            "b) OSD",
            "c) ISD",
            "d) Speed of vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The road user characteristics, traffic and vehicular characteristics mostly influence the road geometric design but the most important factor is the speed of vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "The design speed of NH on a cross slope of up to 10% is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100kmph",
            "b) 80kmph",
            "c) 60kmph",
            "d) 50kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  a\nExplanation: The ruling speed up to a cross slope of 10% is 100kmph; it decreases with an increase in increase of cross slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "A part of pavement raised with respect to one side keeping the other side constant is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Footpath",
            "b) Kerb",
            "c) Super elevation",
            "d) Camber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The super elevation is a portion of pavement raised on outer edge with respect to inner edge or both edges raised with respect to centre."
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "The main purpose of providing camber is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To collect storm water",
            "b) To maintain equilibrium",
            "c) To follow IRC specifications",
            "d) To follow geometric specifications"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: During the rainy season the roads are usually flooded with water so to keep the pavement dry they have to be drained off so the road is provided with a camber."
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "The legal axle load of the design vehicle used in India is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.6 tonne",
            "b) 8.2 tonne",
            "c) 16.2 tonne",
            "d) 32.4 tonne"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The legal axle load used for the design of pavements is 8.2 tonnes; usually they are expressed in MSA (million standard axles)."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "In India, the type of traffic assumed to design pavements is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low traffic",
            "b) Heavy traffic",
            "c) Mixed traffic flow",
            "d) Very low traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India generally there is always a mixed traffic flow except during midnight hours and early morning hours, so the designer has to assume mixed traffic flow only. "
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "The braking efficiency mainly depends on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sight distance",
            "b) PIEV theory",
            "c) Friction",
            "d) Length of the curve"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The braking efficiency mainly depends on friction and speed of the vehicle, if the speed of vehicle is more, then braking efficiency will be less."
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "The braking efficiency for a vehicle moving with a speed of 18kmph, having a lag distance of 14m and coefficient of longitudinal friction is 0.36.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25.28%",
            "b) 25.4%",
            "c) 25.6%",
            "d) 25.8%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Braking efficiency=100*f’/f\nf’=v2/2gL\nf’=5*5/2*9.81*14\nf’=0.09\n=100*0.09/0.36\n=25.28%."
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "If the longitude coefficient of friction is 0.4, then the resultant retardation in m/sec2 as per IRC will be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.93",
            "b) 4.00",
            "c) 4.01",
            "d) 4.02"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deceleration of the vehicle mainly depends on the speed of the vehicle and coefficient of friction; however IRC has calculated the average value is 3.93 m/sec2 from equations of motion."
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "The unevenness index for a good pavement surface of high speed should be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1500mm/km",
            "b) 2500mm/km",
            "c) 3500mm/km",
            "d) 4500mm/km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The unevenness index for a good pavement surface should be kept as low as possible, because they may cause discomfort to passengers and increase the rate of accidents."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "If the camber is x%, then cross slope is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100X",
            "b) 200/X",
            "c) X/100",
            "d) 100+X"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: The cross slope is generally expressed in n in 100 terms, so the cross slope is X/100."
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "The camber required depends on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of pavement",
            "b) Rainfall",
            "c) Type of pavement and rainfall",
            "d) Rainfall characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The camber to be provided changes depending on the type of rainfall and the type of pavement surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "The minimum camber required in heavy rainfall area for bituminous roads as per IRC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2.5%",
            "c) 2.7%",
            "d) 3%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum camber to be provided in heavy rainfall areas is 2.5%. If there is heavy flood then provision of this camber will be sufficient to drain of flood water."
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "The camber is not provided in which of the following shape?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Straight",
            "b) Parabolic",
            "c) Combination of straight and parabolic",
            "d) Circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The camber is a raised portion, it has to be either straight or parabolic no other shape of camber is possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "The rise of crown for pavement of 7m wide having 1 in 50 slopes with respect to edges is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.14",
            "b) 0.07",
            "c) 0.09",
            "d) 0.11"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Width of pavement=7m\nRise of crown=7/2*1/50=7/100=0.07."
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "The equation of parabolic camber is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y=x/a",
            "b) Y=x2/a",
            "c) Y=x3/a",
            "d) Y=ax2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The general equation is expressed as y=x2/a, where a=nw/2 for a pavement width of w and cross slope of 1 in n."
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "The minimum width of carriage way in urban roads is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5m",
            "b) 3.0m",
            "c) 3.5m",
            "d) 3.75m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum width of carriage way is 3.75m in urban roads; this value may be less in towns and villages depending on the requirement like 3.5 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "A median is also called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic separator",
            "b) Traffic junction",
            "c) Traffic check post",
            "d) Traffic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The median may be a physical marking, divided area or protected by physical structure to avoid head on collisions."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "The desirable width as per IRC for median on rural roads is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3m",
            "b) 5m",
            "c) 8m",
            "d) 14m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The desirable width is 5m on rural roads which can be reduced to 3m if there is a restriction of land."
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "The height of low kerb is kept about ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50mm",
            "b) 75mm",
            "c) 100mm",
            "d) 200mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A kerb is a structure used to separate pavement and median, pavement and shoulder, pavement and footpath. In low kerb height is restricted to 100mm only."
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "The minimum shoulder width recommended by IRC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0m",
            "b) 1.5m",
            "c) 2.0m",
            "d) 2.5m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum shoulder width is 2.5m recommended by IRC, the shoulder provides lateral stability and act as emergency lanes for vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "The width of drive way should be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Minimum",
            "b) Maximum",
            "c) Intermediate",
            "d) Maximum or minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The width of drive way should be kept as minimum as possible to reduce the crossing distance of pedestrians."
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "A road running parallel to highway for some selected areas with grade separator are called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Footage road",
            "b) Urban road",
            "c) Frontage road",
            "d) Parallel highway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: A frontage road is a road that is mainly laid in urban areas to connect some parts of the city without disturbing the highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "The width of formation is calculated by adding?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sum of the width of pavements",
            "b) Width of pavement+ separators",
            "c) Width of pavement + separators + shoulders",
            "d) Width of pavement + separator + shoulders + side drains"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The width of formation or roadway is the sum of pavements, shoulders and separator excluding side drains."
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "The boundary till which building activities are prohibited is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Right of way",
            "b) Boundary line",
            "c) Building line",
            "d) Control line"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The space left over for future expansion of roads without allowing any building activities is called as building line."
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "The normal width recommended in rural areas by IRC for a national highway is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45m",
            "b) 29 m",
            "c) 60 m",
            "d) 25 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average width required for a national highway is 45m, it may be between 30m-60m for plain and rolling terrains."
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The length visible to driver at any instance of time is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sight distance",
            "b) Visibility limit",
            "c) Head light distance",
            "d) Overtaking sight distance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The length of the road that is visible to the driver at any time is called sight distance, in night visibility it is headlight sight distance and in zone which it can be overtaken is called overtaking sight distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "The stopping sight distance of a vehicle moving with 45kmph and having a coefficient of friction as 0.4 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 48m",
            "b) 49m",
            "c) 50m",
            "d) 51m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: SSD=0.278vt+v2/254f\nSSD=0.278*45*2.5+452/(254*0.4)\nSSD=51m."
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "The stopping sight distance does not depend on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a)  Break reaction time",
            "b) Speed of vehicle",
            "c) Length of vehicle",
            "d) Friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: SSD=0.278vt+v2/ (254f)\nIn this equation t is the reaction time taken by driver for stopping the vehicle, v is the speed of the vehicle and f is the coefficient of friction, so the SSD is independent of the length of the vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "The SSD is based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed of vehicle",
            "b) PIEV theory",
            "c) Voluntary action of brain",
            "d) Reflex action of brain"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The SSD is based on PIEV theory, it is the theory that estimates the time taken to perceive and react."
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "The reaction time considered in SSD is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5 sec",
            "b) 2 sec",
            "c) 2.5 sec",
            "d) 3 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The reaction time considered in SSD unless and until specified is 2.5 sec; it is based on PIEV theory."
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "The desirable relationship between OSD and length of overtaking zone is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of overtaking zone = OSD",
            "b) Length of overtaking zone = 2 OSD",
            "c) Length of overtaking zone = 3 OSD",
            "d) Length of overtaking zone = 5 OSD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum length of the overtaking zone is 3 times of OSD, but desirable is 5 times of OSD."
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "If the speed of overtaken vehicle is 80Kmph, then the design speed is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80kmph",
            "b) 96kmph",
            "c) 100kmph",
            "d) 106kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Vb=V-16\nV=Vb+16\nV=80+16=96Kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "If the speed of overtaken vehicle is 50kmph then spacing of vehicles is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10m",
            "b) 12m",
            "c) 14m",
            "d) 16m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The spacing of vehicles is given by S=0.2Vb+6\nS=0.2*50+6\nS=16m."
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The reaction time of a driver assumed in OSD is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 sec",
            "b) 2 sec",
            "c) 2.5sec",
            "d) 3 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The reaction time assumed is 2 sec which is less than time taken in SSD because here the driver does not need to perceive and react so this time is less than the time taken in SSD."
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The height of the driver above the road level is assumed as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.1m",
            "b) 1.2 m",
            "c) 1.5 m",
            "d) 1.6m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The height of the driver assumed is 1.2m which is till the eye level; this is assumed for clear vision in night."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "The relationship between SSD and ISD is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) SSD = ISD",
            "b) SSD = 1.5 SSD",
            "c) SSD = ISD + OSD",
            "d) SSD = 2 ISD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ISD is the intermediate sight distance which is provided when there is no possibility of providing OSD as far as possible the roads are provided with SSD = 2 ISD relationship."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "The sight distance recommended by IRC for 50kmph speed is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100m",
            "b) 110m",
            "c) 120m",
            "d) 200m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IRC recommends a sight distance of 110m for a speed of 50kmph, 180m for a speed of 80kmph and 220m for a speed of 100kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "The degree if curve is central angle subtended by an arc of length is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20m",
            "b) 25m",
            "c) 30m",
            "d) 35m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The relation between degree and radius of circular curve is RDπ/180=30."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "The ratio between centrifugal force and weight of the vehicle is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact factor",
            "b) Impact ratio",
            "c) Centrifugal factor",
            "d) Centrifugal impulse"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The relationship between centrifugal force and weight of the vehicle is called impact factor or centrifugal ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "Which of the following is equal to super elevation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sinθ",
            "b) Cosθ",
            "c) Tanθ",
            "d) Secθ"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The transverse inclination to the pavement surface is called as super elevation or cant banking which is equal to tanθ."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "If the radius of a horizontal curve is 120m, then calculate the safe allowable speed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50kmph",
            "b) 60kmph",
            "c) 70kmph",
            "d) 80kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The safe allowable speed is Va = √(27.94R)\nVa = √(27.94*120)\nVa = 60kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "If the super elevation of the highway provided is zero, then the design speed of highway having a curve of 200m and coefficient of friction 0.10 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40kmph",
            "b) 50kmph",
            "c) 55kmph",
            "d) 60kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design velocity is given by V=√127Rf\nV=√127×200×0.1\nV=50Kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "The design speed on a highway is 60kmph; calculate the super elevation if radius of curve is 150m and coefficient of friction is 0.15.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.07",
            "b) 0.038",
            "c) 0.04",
            "d) 0.15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: e+f=v2/127R\ne+f=3600/(127*150)\ne+f=0.188\ne=0.188-0.15\ne=0.038."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "The super elevation is calculated for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75% of design speed including friction",
            "b) 80% of design speed neglecting friction",
            "c) 75% of design speed neglecting friction",
            "d) 80% of design speed including friction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The super elevation is calculated for 75% of design speed neglecting the friction on the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "If the super elevation is 0.07 and width of pavement is 7m then the raise of outer edge with respect to inner edge is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.47m",
            "b) 0.48m",
            "c) 0.49m",
            "d) 0.50m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The raise of outer edge is given by\nE=Be,\nE=7*0.07=0.49m "
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The ruling minimum radius in the curve is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R=V2/127(e+f)",
            "b) R=V’2/127 (e+f)",
            "c) R=127(e+f)",
            "d) R=127/(e+f)"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ruling minimum radius is calculated by using the minimum design speed provided by IRC."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "The extra widening is the sum of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mechanical widening and psychological widening",
            "b) Two times of mechanical widening",
            "c) Two times of psychological widening",
            "d) Mechanical widening – physical widening"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The extra widening is the sum of mechanical widening and physiological widening, the mechanical widening is done for the safety of vehicles and psychological widening is done for the comfort of passengers."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The mechanical widening of a track is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) l2/2R",
            "b) nl2/2R",
            "c) nl3/2R",
            "d) nl/2R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mechanical widening of track is given by nl2/2R where n is the number of tracks, l is the length of wheel base and R is the radius of track."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "The length of wheel base usually considered in India is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.1m",
            "b) 5.9m",
            "c) 5.8m",
            "d) 5.5m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The length of the wheel base may be assumed as 6.0m or 6.1m for vehicles if data is unknown, this value is considered for commercial vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "The total off tracking of a vehicle having wheel base length as 6.1m and radius of curve 120m is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.150",
            "b) 0.151",
            "c) 0.153",
            "d) 0.155"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The total off tracking of a vehicle = l2/2R\n=6.1*6.1/(2*120)\n=0.155."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "The extra width required on two lane pavement for a radius of curve 100m as recommended by IRC is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6m",
            "b) 0.7m",
            "c) 0.8m",
            "d) 0.9m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IRC recommends a value of 0.9m for two lane pavement for radius of curve 100m, this value decreases with increase in the length of curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The mechanical widening of a curve is 1.5m, the curve is having a radius of 120m and design speed as 80kmph find the total widening on the curve.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.20m",
            "b) 2.26m",
            "c) 2.25m",
            "d) 2.24m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total widening is the sum of mechanical widening and psychological widening,\nExtra width required=1.5m + V/9.5√R\n=1.5 + 80/9.5 √120\n=2.26m."
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "The most preferred type of transition curve by IRC for highway is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spiral",
            "b) Cubic parabola",
            "c) Parabola",
            "d) Lemniscate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most preferred type of transition curve by IRC for highway is parabola, for its ease of construction and other field work."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "The minimum value of change of centrifugal acceleration is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4m/sec3",
            "b) 0.5m/sec3",
            "c) 0.6m/sec3",
            "d) 0.7m/sec3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum value of change of centrifugal acceleration is 0.5 m/sec3 and the maximum value is 0.8m/sec3."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "The rate of change of acceleration in m/sec3 for a design speed of 85kmph is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.6",
            "c) 0.7",
            "d) 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rate of change of acceleration for a design speed of 85kmph is given by\nC=80/(75+V)\nC=80/(75+85)\nC=0.5m/sec3."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "In a steep terrain the radius of curve is 100m and the design speed is 80kmph then the length of transition curve will be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 44m",
            "b) 54m",
            "c) 64m",
            "d) 74m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The length of the transition curve will be V2/R\nLs=80*80/100\nLs=64m."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The total shift of a transition curve is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) L2/12R",
            "b) L2/24R",
            "c) L2/48R",
            "d) L2/96R"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total shift of a transition curve is L2/24R, where L is the length of the transition curve and R is the radius of the curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "The vertical alignment of a highway includes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sight distance and traffic intersection",
            "b) Widening of pavements",
            "c) Design of valley curves and gradients",
            "d) Highway lighting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The design of valley curves, summit curves and gradient are included in the vertical alignment of highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "The ruling gradient required for plain or rolling terrain is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 15",
            "b) 1 in 20",
            "c) 1 in 30",
            "d) 1 in 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ruling gradient value required for plain and rolling terrain type of road is 1 in 30 or 3.3%."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "The maximum grade compensation for a curve of radius 75m is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 1.4%",
            "c) 1.5%",
            "d) 1.6%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum grade compensation is 75/R = 75/75 = 1%."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "The vertical alignment does not influence?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sight distance",
            "b) Vehicle operation cost",
            "c) Accidents",
            "d) Vehicle speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The vertical alignment influences sight distance, vehicle operation cost, vehicle speed and comfort while travelling at high speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "The angle which is measured at the change of direction of two gradients is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard angle",
            "b) Subtended angle",
            "c) Deviation angle",
            "d) Setback angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The angle which denotes the direction of change of two gradients angle is called as deviation angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "The length of the summit curve is based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Comfort",
            "b) Sight distance",
            "c) Convexity",
            "d) Deviation angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The length of summit curve is based on stopping sight distance, it is further divided into two cases when L>SSD and L<SSD."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "The value of “a” in the equation y=ax2 used in the summit curve is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) N/2L",
            "b) N/3L",
            "c) N/4L",
            "d) N/5L"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The value of the constant “a” is N/2L where N is the deviation angle and L is the length of the curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "If the length of the summit curve having SSD as 150m and deviation angle is 1 in 30 is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50m",
            "b) 100m",
            "c) 150m",
            "d) 170m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The length of the summit curve is given by\nL=NS2/4.4\nL=1*150*150/ (4.4*30)\nL=170m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "If the deviation angle of the curve is 1/200 and the design speed is 80kmph then calculate the total length of the valley curve for comfort condition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.22",
            "b) 18.52",
            "c) 19.22m",
            "d) 19.52m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The total length of the curve for comfort condition is 0.38(NV3)1/2\n=0.38(1/200*803)0.5\n=19.22m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "The equation for L<OSD for summit curve is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) NS/8H",
            "b) NS2/8H",
            "c) NS2/10H",
            "d) NS2/12H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equation of summit curve for L< OSD or L<ISD is given by NS2/8H and the height of the eye of driver is generally assumed as 1.2m."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "The minimum length of vertical curve recommended by IRC for a design speed of 100kmph is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30m",
            "b) 40m",
            "c) 50m",
            "d) 60m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: IRC recommends a value of 60m for curve having a design speed of 100kmph this value decreases with a decrease in speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "The branch of engineering that deals with improvement of traffic performance, traffic studies and traffic network is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway engineering",
            "b) Railway engineering",
            "c) Traffic engineering",
            "d) Traffic management"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The branch of engineering that deals with improvement of traffic performance, traffic studies and traffic network are called as traffic engineering, it also includes geometric design and other specifications."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "In India for design of roads pedestrian is considered as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Element of traffic",
            "b) Intruder in traffic",
            "c) Essential part of traffic",
            "d) Controller of traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In India unfortunately pedestrian is considered as an intruder in traffic and not given much importance as a result most of the victims are pedestrians only."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "The basic objective of traffic engineering is to achieve ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficient, free and rapid flow of traffic with least priority given to accidents",
            "b) Efficient, free and rapid flow of traffic with fewer accidents",
            "c) Efficient and rapid flow of traffic",
            "d) Rapid flow of traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The basic objective of traffic engineering is to achieve efficient, free and rapid flow of traffic with fewer accidents and pedestrians are also given importance."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The study of traffic engineering is divided into how many major categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Five",
            "b) Six",
            "c) Seven",
            "d) Eight"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The study of traffic engineering is divided into 7 major categories they are traffic characteristics, traffic studies and analysis, planning and analysis, geometric design, traffic operation, road safety and administration."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "The “3-Es” of traffic engineering stand for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enforcement, empowerment and eradication",
            "b) Engineering, education and expulsion",
            "c) Engineering, education and enforcement",
            "d) Engineering, education and enthusiasm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The “3-Es” in traffic engineering represent Engineering, education and enforcement."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "In traffic engineering, the elements are classified into how many categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In traffic engineering, the elements are classified into two categories they are human and machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "Which of the following roads are congested during peak hours?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rural roads",
            "b) Urban roads",
            "c) Highways",
            "d) Express ways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The urban roads mostly in cities and towns are congested during morning and evening times due to the school, college and office timings."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "The traffic survey is conducted during ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Harvest season",
            "b) Harvest and lean season",
            "c) Rainy season",
            "d) Summer season"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Traffic surveys are conducted during harvest and lean season because they are more accurate and easy to conduct."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "Design of road intersections is a part of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway engineering",
            "b) Railway engineering",
            "c) Traffic engineering",
            "d) Harbour engineering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Design of road intersections is a part of highway engineering in which types of intersections, the advantages and disadvantages are studied."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "What is the most important objective of traffic engineering?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To consider pedestrians as obstruction",
            "b) To reduce the accidents",
            "c) To increase the traffic",
            "d) To provide a high speed road without any other priority"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most important objective is to reduce accidents with considerable speed and the pedestrian should be considered as an element not obstruction."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The difference in between the set of front axle and rear axle while negotiating a horizontal curve is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Psychological widening",
            "b) Off tracking",
            "c) Skidding",
            "d) Slipping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Whenever a four wheeled vehicle such as bus or truck negotiates the horizontal curve then there is a centrifugal force induced and a difference is formed between front and rear axle which is called as off tracking."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "A wheel base of 6.5m negotiates a 35m curve find the off tracking?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5m",
            "b) 0.6m",
            "c) 0.62m",
            "d) 0.7m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Off tracking=l2/2R\n=6.5*6.5/70\n=0.6m."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "In a braking test, a vehicle was moving with a speed of 45kmph and was stopped by applying brakes, the skid marks were 10.0m in length. Determine the skid resistance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.78m",
            "b) 0.69m",
            "c) 0.71m",
            "d) 0.72m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: speed=45/3.6\n=12.5m/sec\nBraking distance = u2/2gf\n10=12.5*12.5/ (2*9.81*f)\nF=0.78m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "The brake efficiency in the braking test is assumed as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 95%",
            "b) 96%",
            "c) 99%",
            "d) 100%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the braking test the wheels are assumed to be fully locked and the efficiency is assumed as 100%."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "Gross weight, axle and wheel loads of vehicle govern the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Width of pavement",
            "b) Thickness of pavement",
            "c) Structural design of pavement and cross drainage structures",
            "d) Traffic junctions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The weight of the vehicle and wheel loads usually recommended by IRC is used for the design of pavements and cross drainage structures."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "How many types of factors affect traffic characteristics?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors affecting traffic characteristics are physical, mental, environmental and psychological."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The hearing, visibility and reaction time are covered in which type of factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical",
            "b) Mental",
            "c) Psychological",
            "d) Environmental"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The visibility, hearing and reaction time are related to the physical conditions of the road, they are covered under physical type."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "An intelligent driver who consumed alcohol will have a chance of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increased alertness",
            "b) Increase in reaction time",
            "c) Increase in speed",
            "d) Increase in judgment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A person who is extremely intelligent if he consumes alcohol, then there is a chance of losing his control over mind temporarily and will have an increase in reaction time."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The pollutant mostly released by automobiles is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CO",
            "b) CO2",
            "c) O3",
            "d) CH4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pollutant mostly released by automobiles is CO, when it is mixed with haemoglobin it forms carboxyhaemoglobin which is very dangerous for health."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The most likely cause of accidents is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impatience in driving",
            "b) Slow speed of vehicle",
            "c) Pedestrians crossing the road",
            "d) Cattle crossing the road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most likely cause in this case is impatience in driving as it may lead to anxiety and fear; this mostly affects the user psychologically."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "The width recommended by IRC for all type of vehicles is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5m",
            "b) 2.0m",
            "c) 2.5m",
            "d) 3.0m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IRC recommends a width of 2.5m for any type of vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "The stability of a vehicle is influenced by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Width of wheel base only",
            "b) Width of wheel base and height of gravity",
            "c) Height of gravity only",
            "d) Length of vehicle only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: The stability of a vehicle is influenced greatly by width of wheel base and height of center of gravity is useful near horizontal curves."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "The height of the vehicle mainly influences?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Width of pavement",
            "b) Length of curve",
            "c) Clearance under structures",
            "d) Design velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The clearance of structures like over bridges and under bridges mainly depends on the height of the vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "The minimum number of parameters needed to measure brake efficiency is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The parameters required for measuring brake efficiency are initial speed; braking distance and actual duration of braking application in these three parameters any two of them are needed."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "If the acceleration of the vehicle is 6.17m/sec2 then the average skid resistance is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.61",
            "b) 0.62",
            "c) 0.63",
            "d) 0.64"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average skid resistance f=a/g\nf=6.17/9.81\n=0.63. "
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "What is the first stage in traffic engineering studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic volume studies",
            "b) Spot speed studies",
            "c) Speed and delay studies",
            "d) Origin and destination studies"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step in traffic engineering studies is traffic volume studies, which are carried out to understand the traffic characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "The traffic volume is usually expressed in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LMV",
            "b) PCU",
            "c) LCV",
            "d) HCV"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In India the traffic is heterogeneous so there are many types of vehicles, so every vehicle is expressed with the same unit PCU which means passenger car unit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The number of vehicles that pass through a transverse line of road at a given time in a specified direction is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic studies",
            "b) Traffic flow",
            "c) Traffic origin",
            "d) Traffic destination"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of vehicles that pass through a transverse line of road at a given time in a specified direction is called as traffic flow or traffic volume expressed in PCU."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "HCV stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy commercial vehicle",
            "b) Heavy cash vehicle",
            "c) Heavy consolidated vehicle",
            "d) Hard commercial vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: HCV stands for heavy commercial vehicle which includes trucks and buses."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "The traffic flow is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Static",
            "b) Dynamic",
            "c) Static and dynamic",
            "d) May be static or dynamic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The traffic flow on the roads is dynamic it changes with year, month and season. It also depends on time daily."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "What is the first objective of traffic volume studies?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To decide priority for improvement of roads",
            "b) For geometric design",
            "c) For computing roadway capacity",
            "d) To plan traffic operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first objective of the traffic volume studies is to decide priority for improvement of roads like relaying of roads, widening of roads and other works."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Pedestrian data is used for planning __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway",
            "b) Sidewalks and cross-walks",
            "c) Kerb",
            "d) Camber"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The pedestrian data is used for planning of sidewalks, cross walks, subways and foot-over bridges."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "Which of the following method is more accurate for traffic analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Manual count",
            "b) Automatic count",
            "c) Average of manual and automatic",
            "d) Past records"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The automatic count is more accurate as it is done for 24 hours by machine; it is more reliable than manual counting."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "The outgoing and incoming traffic are counted at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic intersections",
            "b) Highway",
            "c) Urban roads",
            "d) Traffic symbols"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The outgoing and incoming traffic are usually counted at traffic intersections as they are convenient to count."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "The traffic that is prepared based on 365 days of the year is called?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yearly traffic",
            "b) Annual average daily traffic",
            "c) Average daily traffic",
            "d) Average yearly traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The traffic that is prepared based on 365 days of the year is called as AADT or annual average daily traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "The charts showing the variation of the traffic is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic chart",
            "b) Trend chart",
            "c) Variation chart",
            "d) Traffic flow maps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The charts showing the variation of the traffic are called as variation charts which show the variation in day, time, year and season."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "The traffic design in India is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10th hourly volume",
            "b) 20th hourly volume",
            "c) 30th hourly volume",
            "d) 45th hourly volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India the traffic design is based on 30th hourly volume which is considered as peak factor for traffic design."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "The 5 minute count at a traffic junction is 15 find the hourly count?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 100",
            "c) 120",
            "d) 180"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The hourly count = 15*12\n=180."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "If the traffic volume count on a road is 150 and daily factor is 1.1 and seasonal factor is 1.2 then ADT is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 196",
            "b) 197",
            "c) 198",
            "d) 199"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: ADT= Traffic volume*D.F*S.F\n=150*1.1*1.2\n=198. "
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "The ratio of seven day average for 24 hours and 24 hours count on any particular day is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Daily factor",
            "b) Seasonal factor",
            "c) Annual factor",
            "d) Weekly factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of seven day average for 24 hours and 24 hours count on any particular day is called a daily factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "The annual average daily traffic is calculated by which of the formula?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ADT*DF*WF",
            "b) ADT*DF*WF*SF",
            "c) ADT*WF",
            "d) ADT*SF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The AADT is given by AAADT=ADT*DF*WF*SF, it depends on traffic, day, season and week."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "Running speed of a vehicle is equal to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Travel speed+ delay",
            "b) Travel speed",
            "c) Travel speed-delay",
            "d) Average of travel speed and delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The running speed of a vehicle is obtained by dividing the distance with a time of travel and subtracting the delays."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "The speed at any instant of time is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Running speed",
            "b) Travel speed",
            "c) Spot speed",
            "d) Space speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The speed at any instant of time is called as spot speed or instantaneous speed, running speed is during travel and the average speed of travel is travel speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Options": [
            "4. Which of the following relationship is correct?",
            "a) Travel speed= running speed",
            "b) Travel speed< running speed",
            "c) Travel speed>running speed",
            "d) Travel speed=1.5 times of running speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Running speed is always greater than travel speed as the travel speed always includes the stopped delays."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "Peak hour factor is expressed in percentage of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ADT",
            "b) AADT",
            "c) PCU",
            "d) DF"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Peak hour factor is expressed in the percentage of AADT; it is used in the design of transportation facilities and major projects."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "How many types of traffic speed studies are conducted?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two types of studies conducted for speed, they are (i) spot studies (ii) speed and delay studies. "
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "If the distance of a vehicle moved is 25m and the observed travel time is 15 sec then space mean speed is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4m/s",
            "b) 5m/s",
            "c) 6m/s",
            "d) 7m/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Space mean speed=3.6*25/15\n=6m/sec. "
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "If space mean speed of a vehicle is 50kmph, then the time mean speed will be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 50kmph",
            "b) Greater than 50kmph",
            "c) Equal to 50kmph",
            "d) Depends on the vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The Time mean speed will always be greater than space mean speed and it will be greater than 50kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "If the instantaneous speed of 4 vehicles are 35, 40, 45 and 50 then the time mean speed will be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40kmph",
            "b) 41 kmph",
            "c) 41.5kmph",
            "d) 42.5kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The space mean speed is given by\nVt=V1+V2+V3+V4/(4)\n=35+40+45+50/ (4)\n=42.5kmph. "
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "The geometric design in India are designed for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 85th percentile speed",
            "b) 15th percentile speed",
            "c) 98th percentile speed",
            "d) 100 percentile speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India mostly the road geometrics are designed for 98th percentile speed, the upper limit for speed is 85th percentile and lower limit is 15th percentile."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "The weaving manoeuvres is a type of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Merging",
            "b) Diverging",
            "c) Intersection",
            "d) Crossing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The weaving manoeuvre is a type of crossing manoeuvre as it involves crossing of traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "Which of the following does not affect traffic flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vehicles travelling at speed",
            "b) Length of the vehicle",
            "c) Weather conditions",
            "d) Geometric design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Traffic flow does not depend on the length of the vehicle, as it is not related to the flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "The speed at which the value of time headway is lowest represents the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optimum speed",
            "b) Maximum speed",
            "c) Maximum headway",
            "d) Minimum headway"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The speed at which the value of time headway is lowest represents the optimum speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "In countries like USA and UAE, which of the regulation is followed?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Keep to left",
            "b) Keep to right",
            "c) Keep to middle",
            "d) Follow intersection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In countries like US and UAE, keep to right regulation is followed as they follow the left hand drive."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "When the gap of the vehicle changes to a smaller lane then it is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lane change",
            "b) Forced lane change",
            "c) Simultaneous lane change",
            "d) Voluntary lane change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The gap of the vehicle changes to a smaller lane then it is called as forced lane change, as it forces a driver to shift to the smaller lane."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "The vehicles per unit length at any instant of time is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Density",
            "b) Jam density",
            "c) Maximum density",
            "d) Traffic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: At any instant of time, the vehicles per unit length are called as density, if traffic speed is zero then it is called jam density."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "The distance between the two consecutive vehicles is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Space headway",
            "b) Time headway",
            "c) Jam density",
            "d) Traffic flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The distance between the two consecutive vehicles is called as space headway, and it is measured from head to head of the vehicle."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "The maximum jam density occurs at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Zero speed",
            "b) 15th percentile speed",
            "c) 30th percentile speed",
            "d) 98th percentile speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum jam density occurs at zero speed, which indicates that there is no movement of vehicles and the density is maximum."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "If the space headway is 7m, then the jam density in vehicle/km is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 142",
            "b) 144",
            "c) 145",
            "d) 146"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ki=1000/7\nKi=142 vehicles/km. "
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "The minimum space headway increases with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in length of vehicle",
            "b) Increase in width of vehicle",
            "c) Increase in weight of vehicle",
            "d) Increase in width of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum space headway increases with the length of the vehicle, if the length is more then the headway will be more."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "Which of the following equation is correct?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q=KV",
            "b) K=qv",
            "c) K=qv2",
            "d) V=kq"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: K is the density of vehicles/km and V is the velocity in kmph Q is the number of vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "The maximum jam density occurs at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ki",
            "b) Ki/2",
            "c) Ki/3",
            "d) Ki/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum jam density occurs at Ki=Ki/2 and Vs = Vsf/2."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "If the jam density is 145vehicles/km, and velocity is 60kph then the capacity flow is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2175",
            "b) 2200",
            "c) 2375",
            "d) 2500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Capacity flow=145*60/4\n=2175 vehicles per lane. "
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "The equivalency factor for the car recommended by IRC is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1.0",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 2.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The equivalency factor for a car is 1.0, and it increases with the difficulty for the driving of vehicle for hand cart it is 2.0."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "The maximum theoretical capacity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000V/S",
            "b) 1000S/V",
            "c) 1000S",
            "d) 1000V"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum theoretical capacity is 1000V/S, where V is the velocity in kmph and S is the SSD."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What is the first phase of traffic regulation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Driver controls",
            "b) Vehicle controls",
            "c) Traffic flow regulations",
            "d) General controls"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first phase of traffic regulation is driver controls followed by vehicle control, traffic flow regulation and general control."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "The various regulations imposed through the traffic control devices do not include __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clear visibility",
            "b) Easy recognition",
            "c) Sufficient time for driver",
            "d) Traffic population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The various regulations imposed through the traffic control devices do not include as they are not related to control of traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "The minimum age for attaining a license for a geared vehicle is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 years",
            "b) 18 years",
            "c) 20 years",
            "d) 21 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Then minimum age for driving a non-geared vehicle is 16 years, for geared vehicle it is 18 years and for transport vehicle it is 21 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "The motor vehicle act was revised in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1939",
            "b) 1988",
            "c) 1989",
            "d) 1987"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The motor vehicle act was passed in 1939, and it was revised in 1988."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "Traffic symbols are classified into how many categories?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The traffic symbols are classified into three types they are informatory, cautionary and mandatory."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The symbol when violated which may lead to offense is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cautionary",
            "b) Mandatory",
            "c) Informatary",
            "d) Both informatory and cautionary"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mandatory symbol is a symbol which has to be followed at all times, if violated except for special cases, they may attract a penalty."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage in one way traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in average travel speed",
            "b) More effective coordination of signal system",
            "c) More stream lined movement of vehicles",
            "d) More chances of overtaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In one way traffic there are more chances of overtaking as there is traffic only in one direction, there is a chance of overtaking."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "The total conflict points at a junction on both two way roads are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Four",
            "c) five",
            "d) six"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The total number of conflict points is the sum of major and minor conflict points, major conflict points are 4 and minor conflict points are 2, so total conflict points are six."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "The maximum number of conflict points is formed in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One way regulation on one road",
            "b) One way regulation on two roads",
            "c) Two way regulation on one road",
            "d) Two way regulation on both roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum number of conflict points is formed in two ways regulation on both roads is 24."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "The specifications for road signs are specified by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRC 6",
            "b) IRC 21",
            "c) IRC 67",
            "d) IRC 97"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specifications for road signs are specified by IRC 67-2010."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "The diameter of the small size information board is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 600mm",
            "b) 900mm",
            "c) 1200mm",
            "d) 1500mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diameter of the small size information board is 600mm, for medium size is 900mm and the large size diameter is 1200mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "Which type of board should be installed if the speed limit is 100kmph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small",
            "b) Medium",
            "c) Large",
            "d) Not required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Large sizes of boards are required when speed limit exceeds 100kmph, for lesser speeds small and medium sized boards can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "Give way sign is of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Triangular shape",
            "b) Circular shape",
            "c) Octagonal shape",
            "d) Hexagonal shape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Give way sign is of triangular shape and it is coloured with a red border and white background."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "STOP sign is having __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Octagonal shape",
            "b) Circular shape",
            "c) Triangular shape",
            "d) Any shape"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: STOP symbol is of octagonal shape and covered in red background and red border."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "The clearance time is indicated by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Red",
            "b) Amber",
            "c) Green",
            "d) White"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The clearance time is indicated by amber, in some places yellow and blue color also used."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "To reduce the conflict points which method is preferable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Restricting the entry in one side",
            "b) Widening of the roads",
            "c) Use of traffic signals",
            "d) Diverting the traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case, use of traffic signals is advisable as it will be useful to control the traffic up to a certain extent; if it becomes heavy, then diverting may be another option which is not convenient."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "One of the disadvantages of traffic signals is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Provide orderly moment at intersection",
            "b) The quality of the traffic flow improves",
            "c) Traffic handling capacity increases",
            "d) The rear end collision increases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The rear end collisions are common in very highly populated cities, if there is a sudden stoppage of vehicles there is a chance of rear end collision."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "The traffic signals that are installed for pedestrians are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic control signals",
            "b) Pedestrian signals",
            "c) Special traffic signals",
            "d) Automatic signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The signals that are installed for pedestrians are called as pedestrian signals; they are useful when there is no person to control the traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "The clearance time for amber is usually __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5sec",
            "b) 1sec",
            "c) 1.5sec",
            "d) 3sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The clearance time for amber may be assumed as 2sec to 4 sec, in most of the cities it is assumed as 3 seconds."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "In trial cycle method, the average time headway is assumed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2sec",
            "b) 2.5sec",
            "c) 3sec",
            "d) 3.5sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average headway in the trial cycle method is assumed as 2.5sec for 15 minutes of trial cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The number of cycles for a trial period of 45 sec is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 22",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Number of cycles=900/45\n=20."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "If the number of cycles in trial cycle method is 20, for traffic of 170 on one road and 160 on other road, then calculate the total green time in sec.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 38",
            "b) 39",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 41"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Green time on 1st road=170*2.5/20\n=21.25\nGreen time on 2nd road=160*2.5/20\n=20\nTotal green time=41 sec. "
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "In approximate method of signals, the average time taken to cross by the pedestrian is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4sec",
            "b) 5sec",
            "c) 6sec",
            "d) 7sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In approximate method, the time taken is assumed as the crossing time and initial time taken to cross, which should not be less than 7sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "There is a traffic flow of 250 vehicles on road A and 200 vehicles on road B, if the green signal time on road A is 15 sec, then the green signal time of road B is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10sec",
            "b) 11sec",
            "c) 12sec",
            "d) 13sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  From the relationship,\nGa/Gb=na/nb\nGa/Gb=250/200\nGb=12sec. "
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "If the amber time at a signal is 3 sec and the green signal time is 25sec, find the red signal time?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 22sec",
            "b) 21sec",
            "c) 28sec",
            "d) 29sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The total red time is the sum of green time and amber time, so total red time=25+3=28sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "Which of the traffic signal method is based on saturation flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trial cycle method",
            "b) Webster method",
            "c) IRC method",
            "d) Approximate method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The saturation flow is the maximum flow which occurs on the peak hours and it is the maximum flow, in absence of data it is assumed as 1600PCU."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "On a 2 phase road, the saturation flow on road A is 1000 and normal flow is 250,whereas on road B the saturation flow is 1500 and normal flow is 500,the total red time is 10 sec, find optimum cycle length.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 35sec",
            "b) 36sec",
            "c) 37sec",
            "d) 38sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  Ya=250/1000=0.4\nYb=500/1500=0.3\nY=Ya+Yb=0.7\nC0=1.5*L+5/ (1-Y)\nC0=1.5*14+5/ (1-0.7)\nC0=87sec. "
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "Which type of traffic island can be used for reduction of conflict point?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Divisional Island",
            "b) Channelized Island",
            "c) Pedestrian Loading Island",
            "d) Rotary Island"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The major conflicting points can be mostly reduced by rotary islands, which are mostly used near major traffic intersections."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The indicators that may be marked for visible outline of the road is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Roadway indicator",
            "b) Roadway delineator",
            "c) Roadway line",
            "d) Roadway markings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The indicators that are marked for the visible outline are called as roadway indicators, they are of 3 types they are roadway indicator, hazard makers and object markers."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "The guide posts are usually of height?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6m",
            "b) 0.7m",
            "c) 0.8m",
            "d) 2.0m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The guide posts are usually of height 0.8-1.2m and they are placed at 45 degree angle for clear visibility."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not an intersection at grade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Un-channelized",
            "b) Channelized",
            "c) Rotary",
            "d) Different level intersections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The intersection at grade include un channelized, channelized and rotary intersections, the different level intersections are used for over pass and under pass."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "An intersection that is provided for different levels of road is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intersection at grade",
            "b) Grade separated intersections",
            "c) Channelized intersection",
            "d) Rotary intersection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  An intersection that is provided for different levels of road is called grade separated intersection, thus eliminating the crossing manoeuvre."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "If the velocity of a vehicle is 60kmph and the other vehicle velocity is 20kmph, then the relative velocity is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 80kmph",
            "b) 40kmph",
            "c) 20kmph",
            "d) 60kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The relative velocity is the difference of the velocities moving in same direction and sum of the velocities of vehicle moving in opposite direction."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "If the angle of merging is low, then the relative speed will be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low",
            "b) High",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) Depends on width of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the angle of merging is small, then the relative velocity will be low and impact will be low."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "If an additional pavement is provided for lane change, then that intersection is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tee intersection",
            "b) Rotary intersection",
            "c) Flared intersection",
            "d) Skewed intersection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If an additional pavement is provided for lane change, then that intersection is called as flared intersection, it is provided in very crowded areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a requirement for the intersection at grade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Area of conflict should be large",
            "b) Adequate visibility",
            "c) Avoiding sudden change of path",
            "d) Sufficient radius should be provided"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intersection at grade requirements do not include large conflict area, it says the area of conflict should be as less as possible."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "The most complex type of intersections for traffic operation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Un-channelized",
            "b) Channelized",
            "c) Rotary",
            "d) Grade separated"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The channelized intersections are the most complex type of intersections for traffic operation, but they are very easy to construct."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "The procedure of adopting medians and traffic island in an un-channelized intersection is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dividing",
            "b) Crossing",
            "c) Channelizing",
            "d) Designing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The procedure of adopting medians and traffic island in an un-channelized intersection is called as channelizing of the intersection."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "In India the design velocity at rotary is considered as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30kmph",
            "b) 40kmph",
            "c) 50kmph",
            "d) 60kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In India, usually there is no limit to approach the rotary but for safety it is considered as 40kmph for design purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "If the coefficient of friction is 0.43, and the design velocity is 40kmph then the radius of curve is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20m",
            "b) 25m",
            "c) 28m",
            "d) 30m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The radius of curve is given by\nR=V2/127f\nR=40*40/ (127*0.43)\nR=30m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "The minimum radius for rotary recommended by IRC is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.3 times of entry radius",
            "b) 1.33 times of entry radius",
            "c) 1.5 times of entry radius",
            "d) 1.7 times of entry radius"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IRC recommends an average radius of 1.33 times the entry radius for rotary design."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "If the average width of the entry section is 3m and the exit is 6m then the average width is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4m",
            "b) 4.5m",
            "c) 5.0m",
            "d) 5.5m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The average width is average of entry and exit width\n=3+6/2\n=4.5m. "
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "The PCU value near rotary is highest for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cars",
            "b) Bus",
            "c) Cycle",
            "d) Animal drawn vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The highest value for PCU near rotary is for animal drawn vehicle which is 4 to 6 PCU units."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "In a traffic lane the traffic moving extreme left is 250 PCU and in extreme right it is 240 PCU, the sum of the weaving traffic crossing left and right is 500 PCU, find proportion of weaving traffic.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 3.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: b is the proportion of traffic entering into rotary, c is the proportion of traffic leaving the rotary, a is the proportion of traffic moving in the left lane and d is the proportion of traffic moving in the right line\nP=b + c/ (a + b + c+ d)\nP=500/ (250+500+240)\nP=0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "The capacity of rotary in PCU per hour for a proportion of weaving traffic 0.5 and the width of weaving section is 12m, average width of entry is 0.4m and length of the weaving section is 7.2m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1088 PCU",
            "b) 1100PCU",
            "c) 1200 PCU",
            "d) 1300PCU"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Qi = 280W [1+e/W][1-p/3] / (1+W/L)\nQ=280*12*[1+0.4/12][1-0.5/3]/(1+12/7.2)\nQ=1088PCU."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "The best type of interchange can be provided with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rotary",
            "b) Diamond",
            "c) Partial cloverleaf",
            "d) Full cloverleaf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Full clover leaf interchange provides all the required facilities for interchange and it is the most convenient to use."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "A grade intersection may be provided if the PCU exceeds __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5000",
            "b) 6000",
            "c) 7000",
            "d) 10000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the PCU value exceeds 10000 then the grade separators may be used as and when required."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The capacity of an uncontrolled intersection is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000 to 1200 vehicles /hour",
            "b) 1100 to 1200vehilces/hour",
            "c) 1200 to 1400 vehicles/hour",
            "d) 1400 to 1600 vehicles/hour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The capacity of an uncontrolled intersection is 1200-1400 vehicles/hour if there is no traffic signal or police to control it."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "The ramps in the grade separated intersections do not include __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Direct",
            "b) Semi direct",
            "c) Indirect",
            "d) Cloverleaf"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Clover leaf is a type of inter change, it is not an intersection, whereas all the remaining are a type of intersection."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "The product of fast moving vehicles and number of trains should exceed by how much to justify the bypass road construction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25000",
            "b) 5000",
            "c) 50000",
            "d) 250000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  If the product of fast moving vehicles and number of trains should exceed by 25000 then we have to justify the bypass road construction and if it exceeds 50000 it is mandatory."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "Parking facilities may be classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  b\nExplanation: The parking facilities are classified into two types, they are on street and off street parking."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The type of parking in which the vehicles are parked along the kerb is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerb parking",
            "b) Off-street parking",
            "c) Parallel parking",
            "d) Angle parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The type of parking in which the vehicles are parked along the kerb is called kerb parking."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "Which type of parking facility is convenient for all types of users?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerb parking",
            "b) Off-street parking",
            "c) Parallel parking",
            "d) 90 degree parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The 90 degree parking is most convenient for users as it is easy to park and easy to handle even for new users."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The maximum number of cars can be parked in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerb parking",
            "b) Off-street parking",
            "c) Parallel parking",
            "d) 90 degree parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum number of vehicles can be accommodated for same length in parallel parking."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "The number of parking spaces for a kerb of 59m and having the length of car as 5.0m is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 11",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Number of parking spaces = 59/5.9\n=10\nHere, extra width of 0.9m is considered, because the vehicles cannot be parked very close."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "The first stage of the parking lot is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Entrance",
            "b) Acceptance",
            "c) Storage",
            "d) Delivery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first stage of parking lot is entrance followed by acceptance, storage, delivery and exit."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "The parking facility in which elevators are required to change to a different level is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parking lot",
            "b) Multi storeyed building",
            "c) Clover leaf junction",
            "d) Ramp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In multi storeyed buildings, usually in tall buildings there is an elevator provided to change the level of parking."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "In 90 degree parking the length of kerb is 25m, the parking spaces are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 12",
            "d) 13"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Parking spaces in 90 degree parking=25/2.5\n=10 "
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "The place allotted particularly for only parking is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parking lot",
            "b) Parking space",
            "c) Clover space",
            "d) Traffic parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The place allotted particularly for only parking is called as parking lot."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "The most inconvenient method for parking is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 degree parking",
            "b) 45 degree parking",
            "c) 90 degree parking",
            "d) Parallel parking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: 30 degree parking is the most inconvenient as everyone cannot turn in this angle. 90 degree parking is convenient and in parallel most cars can be handled."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "The road traffic consists of how many types of traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vehicle traffic",
            "b) Pedestrian traffic",
            "c) Vehicular and pedestrian traffic",
            "d) No traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The road traffic consists of both vehicular traffic and pedestrian traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "Which of the following is not a consequence of pedestrian using roadway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in effective roadway",
            "b) Reduction in running speed",
            "c) Reduction in capacity of road",
            "d) Increase of zebra crossings"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Zebra crossings are meant only for a crossing of pedestrians, it is not related to roadway."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "In which type of transport, walk mode is mandatory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Personal vehicles",
            "b) Public transport",
            "c) Ships",
            "d) Airways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mostly in public transport like bus and metros, walking is mandatory for a long distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "What is the most vulnerable part of the traffic?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic jam",
            "b) Vehicles",
            "c) Pedestrians",
            "d) Cattle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Pedestrians are the most vulnerable part of traffic and they should be treated with the utmost care."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "What is the main objective of the pedestrian facility?",
        "Options": [
            "a) To minimize the pedestrian conflicts",
            "b) To minimize the traffic conflicts",
            "c) To minimize the traffic on road",
            "d) To maximize the pedestrians on road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main objective of the pedestrian facility is to minimize pedestrian conflicts caused by vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The studies that are conducted for planning the facilities of pedestrians is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrian studies",
            "b) Pedestrian volume studies",
            "c) Geometric studies",
            "d) Statistics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The studies that are conducted for planning the facilities of pedestrians are called pedestrian volume studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The width requirement of side walk depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrian flow",
            "b) Traffic flow",
            "c) Pedestrian and traffic flow",
            "d) Climatic conditions"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The width requirement of side walk depends on the pedestrian flow of that area, traffic doesn’t travel on footpath and climate doesn’t affect the pedestrian but affects the design."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "The pedestrian facilities are planned for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Present requirement",
            "b) Estimated growth of population",
            "c) Past population",
            "d) Both present and past requirements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The facilities like footpath and sidewalks are planned for the future estimated population."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "What is the minimum width of side walk?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0m",
            "b) 1.5m",
            "c) 1.75m",
            "d) 2.0m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum width of side walk is considered as 1.5m it may be more depending on the requirement."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The width requirement of side walk is decided with the help of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pedestrians",
            "b) Vehicles",
            "c) Pedestrian flow",
            "d) Vehicular flow"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The width requirement of side walk is decided with the help of pedestrian flow, its width is decided based on pedestrian flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "The dead width usually considered as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5m",
            "b) 1.0m",
            "c) 1.5m",
            "d) 2.0m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dead width usually is considered as 1.0m and in shopping areas it may be more, it is a width which is not mostly used, usually left for a setback."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "If the side walk is 1.5m, then the capacity of pedestrians in one way is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1200",
            "b) 800",
            "c) 1600",
            "d) 2400"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the side walk is 1.5m, then the capacity of pedestrians in one way is 1200, it increases with increase in the width."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "The cross slope of paved footpath may be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 2%",
            "b) 2 to 3%",
            "c) 3 to 4%",
            "d) 4% only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:  c\nExplanation: The cross slope of footpath may be 3 to 4% and in unpaved it may be 4 to 6%."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a controlled type of pedestrian crossing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pavement marking",
            "b) Studs",
            "c) Warning signs",
            "d) Pedestrian signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Pedestrian signals are a type of traffic signals used to control the pedestrian traffic, warning signals are for traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The approach velocity as per IRC for pedestrian crossing facilities is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60kmph",
            "b) 65kmph",
            "c) 70kmph",
            "d) 75kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The approach velocity as per IRC is considered as 65kmph, for the safety of pedestrians but it may depend varying on the conditions."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "The highway accidents occur mostly at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Day time",
            "b) Night time",
            "c) Both day and night",
            "d) Early morning hours"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The highway accidents occur mostly at night time if adequate lighting is not provided. "
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "Highway lighting is more important at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cities",
            "b) Towns",
            "c) Villages",
            "d) Bridges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  Highway lighting is more important at bridges because its boundaries should be visible even at night time."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "Road lighting is a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Advantage for users",
            "b) Disadvantage for users",
            "c) Economically profitable",
            "d) Obstruction for users"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Road lighting is an added advantage for users, even headlight of vehicles may be sufficient but it would be better if it is provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "During the construction of highway, more highway lighting preference is given to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Village",
            "b) Town",
            "c) City",
            "d) Intersections"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: During the construction of highway, more highway lighting preference is given to intersections, as it is the most critical place."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "If the object appears darker than the road surface it is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Discernment",
            "b) Partial discernment",
            "c) Silhouette",
            "d) Reverse silhouette"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the object appears darker than the road surface it is called as silhouette. If the reverse process occurs it is called reverse silhouette."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "Which of the pavement is better for highway lighting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black top surface",
            "b) Cement concrete",
            "c) WBM",
            "d) Gravel roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Cement concrete roads have a better visibility than other all roads, but they are more expensive."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The objects adjacent to the pavement are seen by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Silhouette",
            "b) Reverse silhouette",
            "c) Lamps",
            "d) Head lights"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The objects adjacent to the pavement are seen by a process called as reverse silhouette."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The intensity of highway lighting is measured in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lux",
            "b) Candela",
            "c) Lumen",
            "d) Dioptres"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The intensity of highway lighting is measured usually in lux, dioptre is unit of focal power, candela and lumen are also units of intensity of light, but not usually used."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "The minimum amount of highway lighting to be provided on urban roads is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Lux",
            "b) 15 Lux",
            "c) 30 lux",
            "d) 40 Lux"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IRC recommends a minimum of 30 lux on urban roads and 15 lux on rural roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "Which of the design factors considered in roadway lighting provide all the necessary features?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lamps",
            "b) Luminaire distribution of light",
            "c) Spacing of lighting",
            "d) Lateral placements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  The design factors considered in roadway lighting provide all the necessary features are luminaire distribution of light."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "Which lamps are preferred at intersections?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium-vapour",
            "b) Mercury",
            "c) Filament",
            "d) Fluorescent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Sodium vapour lights are mostly preferred at intersections, as they provide more lighting and are economical."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The ratio of average illumination recommended by IRC is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3",
            "b) 0.4",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 0.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ratio of average illumination recommended by IRC is 0.4, for national highway it is better if it is more than 0.4 for illumination purpose."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "The clearance recommended by IRC for poles in urban roads is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3m",
            "b) 0.4m",
            "c) 0.5m",
            "d) 0.6m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The clearance recommended by IRC is 0.6m from raise of kerb and in non-availability of space it may be reduced to 0.3m."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The spacing between the highway lamps is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 to 15m",
            "b) 15 to 30m",
            "c) 30 to 45m",
            "d) 30 to 60m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The spacing between the highway lamps is between 30-60m, they are not fixed they may vary but they are recommended between 30-60m distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "The maintenance factor of highway is assumed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.6",
            "c) 0.7",
            "d) 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The average life or maintenance factor can be assumed as 80% or 0.8, this is an assumption only it may also be 100%."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "Land use, transportation and road network plans are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inter linked",
            "b) Intra linked",
            "c) Not linked",
            "d) Depends on the network"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Land use, transportation and road network plans are inter linked to each other and they are inseparable."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "What is the main cause of accidents in urban areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improper planning",
            "b) Extra wide roads",
            "c) Additional thickness of the pavement",
            "d) Traffic congestion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main cause of accidents in urban areas is improper planning, no adequate facilities and increase of traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "The first stage in the function of traffic engineering department is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Planning and design",
            "b) Collection of data",
            "c) Investigations",
            "d) Finance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The first stage in the function of the traffic engineering department is a collection of data followed by analysis and design."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "Traffic forecast is not influenced by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GDP",
            "b) Industrial output",
            "c) Population",
            "d) Weather"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Weather cannot influence the traffic forecast, as it is not related to traffic engineering, the remaining directly or indirectly are related to the traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "Demographic factors do not include __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GDP",
            "b) Population in urban cities",
            "c) Population in rural areas",
            "d) Overall population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Demographic factors include population, the population in urban and rural areas, GDP accounts for economic factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "The NHDP are being undertaken by private companies on the basis of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Profit",
            "b) Revenue",
            "c) BOT",
            "d) Commission basis"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India mostly private and govt. sectors follow BOT which means build operate transfer, it is built by a private firm and later transferred to govt."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "The traffic will increase if the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Price of fuel decreases",
            "b) Price of vehicles decreases",
            "c) Price of fuel decreases",
            "d) Price of vehicles decreases"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The traffic increases if the prices of vehicle decreases, price of fuel may increase and decrease, but if the price of the vehicle decreases then the traffic increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "The traffic population is estimated by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arithmetic method",
            "b) Geometric method",
            "c) Incremental increase method",
            "d) Harmonic method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The population forecast is calculated by\nP=P0 (1+r)n\nWhere, P is the expected population, n is the number of years, P0 is the present population."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "The materials not included in highway construction are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stone",
            "b) Dust",
            "c) Soil",
            "d) Petrol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Petrol is not used directly in highway construction, but by-product like bitumen is used. Stone, dust and soil may be used in subgrade and base."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "For places where there is a passage of flood water then the highway has to be built on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Embankment",
            "b) Subway",
            "c) Overpass",
            "d) Underpass"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the HFL is more than the formation level of the road which is going to be provided, then it has to be built on embankment."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "The layer which is constructed above embankment is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub grade",
            "b) Fill",
            "c) Base",
            "d) Sub base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The embankment is the lowest layer and it is below the sub grade, base is above sub base, sub base is above the sub grade."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "The highest CBR number is required for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pavement",
            "b) Sub grade",
            "c) Sub base",
            "d) Base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CBR number decreases with an increase in height, the soil requires the highest CBR and the pavement requires the lowest CBR."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "What is the most common waste material used in construction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fly ash",
            "b) Slag",
            "c) Pozzolona",
            "d) Rice husk"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Fly ash is an industrial waste obtained from the thermal plants, it has been mandatory to use the fly ash in bricks."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "Bitumen is a by-product of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wood",
            "b) Petroleum",
            "c) Kerosene",
            "d) Coal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bitumen is obtained by burning the petroleum at high temperatures, it is mostly used in the construction of flexible pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "Tar is a by-product of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wood",
            "b) Petroleum",
            "c) Kerosene",
            "d) Coal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tar is a by-product which is obtained from wood, tar and bitumen may look similar, but they are not the same."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "In the initial stage of construction which type of pavement is cheap?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible",
            "b) Rigid",
            "c) Composite",
            "d) WBM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Flexible pavements are easy to construct and have cheaper cost than C. C pavements and also they are easily accessible to the users. "
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "A good soil should have __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ease of compaction",
            "b) Temporary strength",
            "c) High sensitivity",
            "d) High void ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: A good soil should have ease of compaction, permanent strength and less sensitivity."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "The process by which the water voids are removed is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction",
            "b) Consolidation",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) Shear strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water voids are mostly removed by consolidation; it is a long process so mostly compaction is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "If the GWT rises to the ground level, then the bearing capacity reduces by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2",
            "b) 1/3",
            "c) 1/4",
            "d) 3/4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The bearing capacity of the soil reduces by 50% if the ground water rises to the ground level."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "What is the most common method used for the removal of voids in soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction",
            "b) Consolidation",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) Shear strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Compaction is the most commonly used method for removal of voids; it is mostly done by modified proctor or standard proctor test."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "What is the volume of voids in the 3 phase diagram of soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Volume of air",
            "b) Volume of water",
            "c) Volume of air and volume of water",
            "d) Volume of solids"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Both the volume of air and volume of water contribute to the voids in the 3 phase diagram of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "What is the ratio of volume of voids and volume of soil solids?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Void ratio",
            "b) Porosity",
            "c) Saturation",
            "d) Air content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of volume of voids and volume of soil solids is called as void ratio, porosity is the ratio of voids and total volume, saturation is volume of voids in volume of water, air content is air voids in volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": " Montimorrite is a type of mineral which causes expansive behaviour is found in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black cotton soil",
            "b) Laterite soil",
            "c) River soil",
            "d) Glacial soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Montimorolite is a type of mineral which is of expansive nature, it is found in mostly black cotton soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The soil that is formed by the action of wind is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lacustrine soil",
            "b) Alluvial soil",
            "c) Aeolian soil",
            "d) Glacial soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The soil that is formed by the action of wind is called as Aeolian soil, lacustrine by lakes, alluvial by River and glacial by glacier."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "The maximum density which is desirable in highway embankments is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry density",
            "b) Saturated density",
            "c) M.D.D",
            "d) O.M.C"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum density which is desirable in highway embankments is M.D.D, if it is greater than MDD then it’s density decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "The void ratio can never be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 1",
            "b) Greater than 1",
            "c) Less than zero",
            "d) Equal to 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The void ratio can never be less than zero, as it is a positive quantity, but it can be greater than 1 or equal to 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "In Indian system the soil is classified as per __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) USCS",
            "b) ISCS",
            "c) BIS",
            "d) ASTM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In Indian system the soil is classified as per ISCS. In international as per USCS, BIS regards the standard in India and ASTM in USA."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "The theoretical void ratio of sand is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.87",
            "b) 0.91",
            "c) 1.01",
            "d) 1.03"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The theoretical void ratio of sand is taken as 0.91."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "If the water content of a soil sample is 25%, and dry density is 15KN/m3 then its dry density in KN/m3 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.75",
            "b) 19",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 21"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Ὑd=Ὓ/1+w\nὛ=15*1.25\n=18.75KN/m3. "
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "If the permeability is high then its void ratio is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Low",
            "c) Medium",
            "d) Depends on soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  If the void ratio is high then, the permeability of the soil will be very high, for example gravel in which there is a lot of void ratio so the permeability is very high."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "The property of soil by which its state and size changes are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Activity",
            "b) Sensitivity",
            "c) Thixotropy",
            "d) Shear strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Thixotropy means changing in touch; it is used for very sensitive soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "What is the specific gravity of sand?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5",
            "b) 2.6",
            "c) 2.7",
            "d) 2.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specific gravity of sand is usually considered as 2.7-2.8 in non-availability of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "In field, the dry density of soil can be determined by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Oven method",
            "b) Sand bath",
            "c) Burning",
            "d) Sand replacement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If there is no facility of the lab, then the dry density can be instantly tested by burning."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "Which type of roller is most suitable for soil compaction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth roller",
            "b) Sheep foot roller",
            "c) Pneumatic roller",
            "d) Hydraulic roller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sheep foot roller compact the soil both by the action of kneading and pressing, so they are the most suitable for compaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "The unpaved shoulder usually consists of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel",
            "b) Sand",
            "c) Bricks",
            "d) Clay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the case of unpaved shoulders, gravel is most preferred because of its permeability, strength and other advantages."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "The specific gravity of sand is determined by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyconometer",
            "b) Density bottle",
            "c) Hydrometer",
            "d) Oven"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific gravity of sand is determined by density bottle method, as it is a fine grain soil and for coarse aggregate it is tested by pyconometer."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The liquid limit of the soil is determined by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hydrometer",
            "b) Pyconometer",
            "c) Sand bottle",
            "d) Cassagrandes apparatus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The liquid limit of the soil is determined by cassagrandes apparatus, which consists of recording the number of blows for specified water content."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "The shear strength is more for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cohesive soil",
            "b) Non cohesive soil",
            "c) Frictionless soil",
            "d) Dust"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The shear strength is more for cohesive soils, if the soils depend only on friction then it is very dangerous, so cohesive soil are strong and advisable."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "The weight of the hammer in modified proctor test apparatus is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.8kg",
            "b) 4.7kg",
            "c) 5.0kg",
            "d) 6.0kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The weight of the hammer in a modified proctor test apparatus is 4.7kg and in simple proctor it is 2.8 kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "Coefficient of permeability is more for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel",
            "b) Sand",
            "c) Clay",
            "d) Brick"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Coefficient of permeability is more for gravel, as the size increases the permeability increases, sand has higher permeability than clay and brick has the least permeability."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "Which type of soil is suitable for the construction of pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black cotton soil",
            "b) Sand",
            "c) Stone dust",
            "d) Gravel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Gravel is the most suitable type of soil for pavement construction; replaced soils are mostly filled by gravel."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "Coefficient of uniformity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) D60",
            "b) D10",
            "c) D60/D10",
            "d) D30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Coefficient of uniformity is D60/D10, where D60 is the percentage of passing for 60mm sieve and D10 is the percentage of passing for 10mm sieve."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The slope of curve obtained between the number of blows and water content in the cassagrande’s method is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Toughness index",
            "b) Activity",
            "c) Flow index",
            "d) Liquid limit"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The slope of the curve obtained between the number of blows and water content in the cassagrande’s method is called as flow index."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "If the sensitivity of the soil is greater than 16 then it is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Insensitive",
            "b) Little sensitive",
            "c) Highly sensitive",
            "d) Quick"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the sensitivity of the soil is greater than 16 then it is very quick soil, if it is near to zero then it is not so sensitive soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "Gravel having well grading is denoted by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) GW",
            "b) GP",
            "c) SM",
            "d) SW"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Gravel having well grading is denoted by GW, where G denotes the gravel and W defined well grading, P denotes poor grading and S denotes the sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "The fine grain soils are classified according to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Atterbergs limits",
            "b) Atterbergs charts",
            "c) USCS",
            "d) ISCS"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The fine grain soils are classified according to Atterberg charts, which are classified as per A-line, they are represented in Atterberg charts and classified as per USCS and ISCS."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "If the load value at 2.5mm penetration in CBR is 190kg and the load for 5.0mm penetration is 48kg, then the CBR value at 5 mm penetration is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.6",
            "b) 4.4",
            "c) 4.3",
            "d) 4.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  CBR value at 5.0mm penetration=48*190/2055\n=4.4% "
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "The plate bearing test is used to evaluate __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modulus of sub grade reaction",
            "b) Modulus of sub base reaction",
            "c) Modulus of base reaction",
            "d) Modulus of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The plate bearing test is used to evaluate the modulus of subgrade reaction “k” which is used in westergards analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "If the shear strength of the non-cohesive soil is 84KN/m2 and angle of friction is 30 degrees, then the normal strength in KN/m2 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a)  140",
            "b) 141",
            "c) 143",
            "d) 145"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:\nS=c+σtanθ\n84=σtan30\nσ=145 "
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "Stone aggregate do not have to resist __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weathering effect",
            "b) Traffic load",
            "c) Wheel load stress",
            "d) Soil load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stone aggregate do not have to resist the soil load as they are transferred by foundation only, weathering traffic and wheel load are directly experienced by aggregates."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "Sand obtained from river is used as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Course aggregate",
            "b) Fine aggregate",
            "c) Filling materials",
            "d) Substitute"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation:  Sand obtained from river is used as fine aggregate as it can be used to fill the voids in the concrete, coarse aggregate is obtained from the rock, sand is not used as filling material but stone dust can be used if sand is not available."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "Soft aggregates are used in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower layers",
            "b) Upper layers",
            "c) Everywhere in the pavement",
            "d) Depends on the material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Soft aggregates cannot resist the weathering action and wheel load of the vehicle, so they are preferred in lower layers, as they are impacted directly."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a soft aggregate?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Brick",
            "b) Gravel",
            "c) Clay",
            "d) Silt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Bricks are not actually aggregates, but the crushed bricks or over burnt bricks are used as aggregates in pavement they are not so hard as the hard aggregate."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "Impact value is used to measure?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardness",
            "b) Toughness",
            "c) Wheel load",
            "d) Strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The impact value of an aggregate is used to measure its toughness; if it is tough then it has a low impact value, hardness is for resistance to abrasion, strength is resistance to crushing."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "The capability of aggregate to resist more weathering action and wheel load is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardness",
            "b) Toughness",
            "c) Durability",
            "d) Angularity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Durability is the period till which the aggregate can resist the weathering action and other loads, hardness is the resistance to abrasion and toughness is the resistance to impact."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "If the aggregates are exceptionally strong then they are having impact value which is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 10",
            "b) Less than 15",
            "c) Less than 30",
            "d) Greater than 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aggregates which have a less impact value are exceptionally tough, but normally the aggregate upto 30% impact value can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "The skid number for highways should not be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 55",
            "b) 45",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 25"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The skid number for highways should not be less than 55 for national highways to ensure smooth ride, if it is less than 55 then suitable precautions have to be taken."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "The specific gravity for aggregates should be within the range of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5-2.8",
            "b) 2.6-2.9",
            "c) 2.4-2.6",
            "d) 2.2-2.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific gravity for aggregates should be within the range of 2.6-2.9 for pavement construction purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "The crushing value of the aggregate determines its __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hardness",
            "b) Strength",
            "c) Toughness",
            "d) Durability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistance to crushing is referred as strength, whereas the resistance to abrasion is called hardness."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "The flakiness index for surface dressing should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15%",
            "b) 25%",
            "c) 35%",
            "d) 45%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flakiness index for aggregates that are used in the pavement surface dressing should not exceed 25%, but in any case combined flakiness and elongation index should never exceed 30%."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "The sum of flakiness index and elongation index should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IRC recommends the combined flakiness and elongation index not to exceed 30%. for the aggregate that should be used in a highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "Aggregates obtained from which type of rocks are strong?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Igneous",
            "b) Sedimentary",
            "c) Metamorphic",
            "d) Rocks formed by weathering"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Aggregates that are obtained from igneous rocks are strongest they include granite, basalt. Sedimentary are obtained from igneous rocks and metamorphic from igneous and sedimentary so they are not so strong."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "What is the maximum size that can be used in plain concrete?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 mm",
            "b) 20 mm",
            "c) 100 mm",
            "d) 80 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum size of aggregate that can be used in plain concrete is 80mm with ease of workability, however they exceed in some special cases up to 100 mm, mostly 20 mm aggregate is used in RCC and 40 mm in pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "What is the maximum size of aggregate that can be used in R.C.C?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10mm",
            "b) 15mm",
            "c) 20mm",
            "d) 25mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum size of aggregates used in RCC is limited to 20mm, for ease of compaction and workability, however 10 mm, 15 mm are also used, in some exceptions 25 mm also is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "The flaky aggregates should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2 of mean dimension",
            "b) 3/4th of mean dimension",
            "c) 3/5th of mean dimension",
            "d) 1/8th of mean dimension"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The flaky aggregate is usually considered as 3/5th of its mean lateral dimension, the flaky aggregates should not be used in pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "The factors which effect the formation of metamorphic rocks are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat",
            "b) Pressure",
            "c) Heat and pressure",
            "d) Molten lava"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Metamorphic rocks are obtained both from sedimentary and igneous rocks, which are influenced by factors like heat and pressure."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The fine aggregates are having a size less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5mm",
            "b) 4.75mm",
            "c) 2.36 mm",
            "d) 75 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the sieve size of aggregates less than 4.75mm, then it is called as fine aggregate. If it exceeds 4.75 mm it is gravel, if it is less than 75 microns it is a fine grain soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "Which type of aggregates gives good workability?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Round",
            "b) Flaky",
            "c) Angular",
            "d) Irregular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aggregates which gives more ease of working and workability is round aggregate, flaky and angular also used in some cases, irregular also are used in pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "If the bulk density of an aggregate is 2.6kg/lit and Gs is 2.8 then, the percentage of voids is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.1",
            "b) 71",
            "c) 710",
            "d) 0.71"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Percentage of voids=G-Ὑ/G\n=2.8-2.6/ (2.8)\n=7.14%."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The dividing and operating of aggregates into different sizes is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sieve analysis",
            "b) Gap grading",
            "c) Impact",
            "d) Hardness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The operating and division of the aggregates as per size is called as sieve analysis, in which the particles are divided as per size, gap grading is a part of the graph drawn in sieve analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The expansion of aggregate on reaction with water is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swelling",
            "b) Bulking",
            "c) Expelling",
            "d) Breaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the aggregate reacts with water and its volume increase then it is called as bulking, swelling is absorption of water, expelling is the removal of water, and breaking is a complete failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "The skid resistance is measured in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swedish pendulum number",
            "b) British pendulum number",
            "c) Indian pendulum number",
            "d) Friction coefficient"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The skid resistance of the pavement is measured in British pendulum number, which is obtained just by rubbing the material with equipment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "Which material can be replaced in concrete for a strong pervious concrete pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Course aggregate",
            "c) Fine aggregate",
            "d) Cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Apart from replacement, there are many materials that can be used for substitution, for a strong pervious concrete pavement better option is to replace coarse aggregate."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The minimum grade of concrete required for pavement design is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) M30",
            "b) M35",
            "c) M40",
            "d) M45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum grade of concrete required for pavement is M40 as it has to resist both wheel loads and weathering action, M30 for low volume roads, M45 may be more helpful."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "The aggregates which do not have sufficient strength like waste bricks can be used in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Base",
            "b) Shoulder",
            "c) Surface",
            "d) Footpath"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The aggregates which don’t have sufficient strength can be used in footpath as it is not so important component, surface and shoulder use gravel, base mostly requires high strength soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "Bitumen is obtained from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wood",
            "b) Petroleum",
            "c) Coal",
            "d) Kerosene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Bitumen is a product that can be obtained from petroleum, bitumen is the most preferred material for pavement now."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "Tar is obtained from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wood",
            "b) Petroleum",
            "c) Coal",
            "d) Kerosene"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Tar is a byproduct of wood, both tar and bitumen look similar and used for pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "Tar is not used now because of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Efficiency",
            "c) Harmful effects",
            "d) Not satisfactory"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Tar is not being used now because of its heating effects and poisonous gases released during heating."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "Bitumen is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pyrogenous",
            "b) Natural",
            "c) Either natural or pyrogenous",
            "d) Artificial"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bitumen may be natural or pyrogenous which is completely soluble in carbon disulfide and carbon tetrachloride."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "The bitumen is completely soluble in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Carbon monoxide",
            "b) Carbon dioxide",
            "c) Carbon sulfide",
            "d) Carbon disulfide"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Bitumen is completely soluble in carbon disulfide and carbon terachloride, these are the chemical substances in which bitumen dissolves completely."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "The resistance to flow is measured by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flash and fire",
            "b) Viscosity",
            "c) Penetration test",
            "d) Ductility test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The resistance to flow of the liquid is called as viscosity, the other tests are also conducted for bitumen, in viscosity the viscosity grade of bitumen is obtained."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "The temperature used in highway pavement in degrees centigrade is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 130",
            "b) 120",
            "c) 115",
            "d) 175"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperature varies between 130 and 175 degrees centigrade and it may also be above it, depending on the exposure of heat and time taken, usually it cools down very fast."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "The solvent used in cut back bitumen is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kerosene",
            "b) Oil",
            "c) Petrol",
            "d) Diesel"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The solvent mostly used in the cutback bitumen is kerosene, this bitumen is economical than others, oil petrol and diesel are inflammables so they should not be preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "The bitumen surface becomes stiff in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summer",
            "b) Winter",
            "c) Rainy",
            "d) Spring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bitumen becomes softer in summer due to heating and stiffer in winter due to cooling."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "Which bitumen does not need heating?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paving grade",
            "b) Cut back",
            "c) Modified",
            "d) Bitumen emulsion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cutback bitumen which is the most economical type may or may not require heating, whereas the remaining required to be heated."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "The distance between two samples in penetration test should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10mm",
            "b) 15mm",
            "c) 20mm",
            "d) 25mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum distance between samples must be 10mm in a penetration test, if it is less than 10 mm then there is no accurate value for penetration."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "Which of the following grade of bitumen is harder?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30/40",
            "b) 60/70",
            "c) 80/100",
            "d) All are equal"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  Lesser the value of bitumen stiffer will be the bitumen, 30/40 is the least value, whereas 80/100 is the highest value, so it is the most soft bitumen."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "The temperature in penetration test is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 27",
            "d) 35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The room temperature of the bitumen test is considered as 25 as per theory, practically it may not be possible, it may be 27 to 35 also in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The SI unit of viscosity is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stoke",
            "b) Pascal",
            "c) Pascal second",
            "d) Dynes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The SI unit of viscosity is Pascal second, Pascal is for pressure, Stoke is CGS unit, Dynes is also a CGS unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "The softening point of bitumen in the given options (in degree Celsius) will be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The softening point of bitumen may be between 35 and 70 in most of the cases, so here 35 is the most appropriate."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "Which layer of pavement should withstand stress?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface",
            "b) Sub grade",
            "c) Sub base",
            "d) Base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stresses and wheel load are to be transferred from pavement surface course to the soil sub grade, automatically the remaining three layers with stand the stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "The surface of bitumen should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth",
            "b) Rough",
            "c) Sufficient enough to resist friction",
            "d) Very smooth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The surface of bitumen should neither be smooth nor rough, it should have adequate frictional resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "The DBM is used in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Local streets",
            "b) Rural roads",
            "c) Highway",
            "d) Concrete bridges"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The DBM is a high quality bitumen mix used in highways and expressways, but they should fulfill some requirements to be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The filler material should pass from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.075mm",
            "b) 0.75mm",
            "c) 7.5mm",
            "d) 75mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The filler material should have 85 to 100 percent passing from 0.075mm sieve, then only it can be used in highway and express way."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "Rutting may be avoided by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Good compaction",
            "b) Good aggregate",
            "c) Good filler",
            "d) Good workmanship"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rutting is a problem caused in summer which can be avoided by using good aggregate, good filler and good compaction may not be enough, but good aggregate with good workmanship will be sufficient to avoid rutting."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "Bleeding may be avoided by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water voids",
            "b) Air voids",
            "c) Porosity",
            "d) Water content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The bleeding may be avoided by providing sufficient air voids in the mix, as it is due to leakage of the water from the mix, if air voids are provided then first air escapes and then the water."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "Which aggregate produce higher stability of mix?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel",
            "b) Sharp sand",
            "c) Rounded sand",
            "d) Fly ash"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Sharp sand and crushed aggregate produce higher stable mix than gravel and round sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregate in base course is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 mm",
            "b) 50 mm",
            "c) 40 mm",
            "d) 30 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum size of aggregate in base course is 50mm, but 20 mm, 30 mm and 40 mm are also used extensively."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "Maximum size of aggregate in surface course is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18.5mm",
            "b) 19.5mm",
            "c) 20.5mm",
            "d) 21.5mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum size in surface course of pavement is 18.5mm, as we move downward the size of the aggregate increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "The specific gravity of bitumen lies between __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.8 & 0.9",
            "b) 0.95 & 0.97",
            "c) 0.97 & 1.02",
            "d) 1.02 & 1.05"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The specific gravity of bitumen is between 0.97&1.02 which depends on the grade of bitumen."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "Volume of mineral aggregate is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) VV+VB",
            "b) Vv-Vb",
            "c) VV*Vb",
            "d) VV/VB"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The volume of aggregate is expressed as the sum of volume of voids and volume of bitumen."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "The specified method for bitumen mix in India is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hveem",
            "b) Marshalls method",
            "c) Hubbard method",
            "d) Super paver mix method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Marshall’s method has been specified by IRC and MORTH for bitumen mix design in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The temperature in Marshall’s method is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The temperature in Marshall’s design is taken as 60 for bitumen mix design purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "Marshall stability determines __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ductility",
            "b) Flexibility",
            "c) Utility",
            "d) Grade of bitumen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Marshall’s method is used to determine the flexibility of the given grade of bitumen."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "The number of blows in Marshalls test specimen is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 30",
            "c) 55",
            "d) 75"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of blows to be given in Marshalls test specimen is 75 with a height drop of 457mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "What is the minimum grade of concrete in CC pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) M20",
            "b) M30",
            "c) M40",
            "d) M50"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum grade of concrete required for pavement is M40, as it should withstand temperature and wheel stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "The cement used in water logged areas is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Portland cement",
            "b) Hydrophobic cement",
            "c) Quick setting cement",
            "d) Reediest cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cement mostly used in water logged areas is hydrophobic cement as it will resist the water from clogging."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "The waste material mostly used in pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fly ash",
            "b) GGBS",
            "c) Rice husk",
            "d) Soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The waste material mostly used in pavement is fly ash which is mostly obtained from thermal power plants."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "The cement on touching should give __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cool feeling",
            "b) Hot feeling",
            "c) neutral",
            "d) Very cool feeling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cement on touching with hand should give a cool feeling and not break; it should be free from lumps."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "Cement specific gravity is measured by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Kerosene",
            "c) Oil",
            "d) Petrol"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specific gravity of cement is measured by kerosene, because if it is measured with water then it forms heat of hydration."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "The specific gravity of cement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5",
            "b) 1.44",
            "c) 3.15",
            "d) 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The specific gravity of cement is 3.15, it is not like the density which is 1440 kg/m3 because here kerosene is used for density test and in 1 metre cube of volume 30 bags may be filled."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "One meter cube of cement consists of how many bags of cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: One meter cube of volume contains 30 bags of cement or 1500kg of cement, it is actually an assumption that one kg of bag consists of 50 kg cement, but density is 1440kg/m3, so approximately value is 30, but the actual value is more."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "The density of cement in Kg/m3 is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1440",
            "b) 1240",
            "c) 1340",
            "d) 1540"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The density of cement in Kg/m3 is 1440; it is not 3150 because its specific gravity is measured with kerosene."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "The initial setting time of cement is not less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 seconds",
            "b) 300 seconds",
            "c) 30 minutes",
            "d) 300 minutes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The initial setting time of cement is not less than 30 minutes for ordinary Portland cement and it may vary for various grades of cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "What is the first test to be done for determining any property of cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Consistency",
            "b) Setting time",
            "c) Soundness",
            "d) Fineness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first test to be done for determining any property of cement is a consistency test which lies between 27 and 29."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "The volume of water in setting time test is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.78p",
            "b) 0.75p",
            "c) 0.85p",
            "d) 0.95p"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The volume of water in the setting time test is 0.85p where p is the consistency of the cement sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "The volume of water in soundness test is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.6p",
            "b) 0.7p",
            "c) 0.78p",
            "d) 0.8p"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The volume of water in soundness test is 0.78p, where p is the consistency of the cement sample."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "The property of cement by which it doesn’t expand is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fineness",
            "b) Soundness",
            "c) Setting time",
            "d) Consistency"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The property of cement by which it doesn’t expand on contact with water is called as soundness."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "What is the most commonly used grade of cement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 33",
            "b) 43",
            "c) 53",
            "d) 63"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most commonly used grade of cement is OPC 53 grade cement for most of the purposes, fly ash is also mixed in some cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "What is the total grades of cement specified by IRC?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IS has classified the grades of cement depending upon the requirement into 9 categories of various classes and materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "The surface of the highway pavement should be designed to allow __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High rolling resistance",
            "b) Low rolling resistance",
            "c) No rolling resistance",
            "d) Very high rolling resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The surface of highway pavement should be designed to allow no rolling resistance for safety purposes."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "The soil becomes weak in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summer",
            "b) Winter",
            "c) Rainy season",
            "d) Spring season"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The soil becomes weak in rainy season due to the absorption of water in the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "The pavement layer is considered superior if it distributes load like a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point load",
            "b) Uniformly distributed load",
            "c) Uniformly varying load",
            "d) Triangular load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pavement layer is considered most superior if it distributes the load equally to all parts of pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "Which of the following pavement has greater life?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bituminous pavements",
            "b) Cement concrete pavements",
            "c) Gravel roads",
            "d) Earth roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cement concrete roads have a greater life than remaining all pavements which may last even up to 100 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "Which of the following requirement is given most importance in highway design?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural",
            "b) Functional",
            "c) Seasonal",
            "d) Maintenance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The structural design like highway speed, geometric design is given the most importance in design."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "The surface of the pavement should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth",
            "b) Rough",
            "c) Sufficient enough to resist skid",
            "d) Very rough"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation:  The surface of the pavement should be sufficient enough to resist the skid of vehicles by using friction."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "Rough and uneven roads increase __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vehicle cost",
            "b) Petrol cost",
            "c) Accident cost",
            "d) Vehicle operation cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Roughness and uneven roads will increase the cost of vehicle operation and maintenance of vehicle cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The drainage layer is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface course",
            "b) Sub base",
            "c) Base",
            "d) Sub grade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The drainage layer is the sub base layer that is used to collect the water from pavement surfaces to send to ground water."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "The maximum stress sustained by concrete pavements in kg/cm2 is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 45",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 55"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The concrete pavements are designed to sustain a stress of 45Kg/cm2 which is the maximum limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "The ICPB type of pavement uses __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concrete paver blocks",
            "b) Fly ash",
            "c) GGBS",
            "d) RMC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ICPB uses mostly interlocking concrete paver blocks for the construction of pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "The ICPB may be used in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water logged areas",
            "b) Parks",
            "c) Footpaths",
            "d) Highways"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The inter locking concrete paver blocks may be used in water logged areas to absorb the water and send it to the ground water."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "The design life of flexible pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation:  The design life of flexible pavement is considered as 15 years, it may last even further if properly maintained."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "The design period of cement concrete road is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 30",
            "d) 35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The design period of cement roads is usually taken as 30 years but they can even last longer if properly maintained and designed."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "In India the flexible pavement is designed as per __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSA",
            "b) KSA",
            "c) CSA",
            "d) FSA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flexible pavements are designed as per IRC 37 which uses MSA to specify the unit of the vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "The maximum length of vehicle that can be used on Indian roads is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11",
            "b) 12",
            "c) 13",
            "d) 14"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum length of a vehicle in India is restricted as per the rotary design of the highway which is maximum 12m."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "The most superior material is used in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) base",
            "b) sub base",
            "c) surface",
            "d) soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most superior material is used in the surface layer of pavement as it is the layer that is exposed to more number of stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "The soil sub grade suitable for pavement is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel",
            "b) Sand",
            "c) Black cotton soil",
            "d) Red soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The soil sub grade most suitable for pavement layer is gravel as it is very strong rock, black cotton is not suitable for pavement but suitable for crops, sand has a danger of liquefaction and red soil is not so advisable."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "The drainage layer is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub grade",
            "b) Sub base",
            "c) Base",
            "d) Surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The drainage layer of the pavement is granular sub base course which collects water from pavement surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "What is the minimum thickness of compacted sub grade?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 300 mm",
            "b) 500 mm",
            "c) 700 mm",
            "d) 900 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum thickness of sub grade required is 300mm and in highways it is 500 mm as they are provided with the maximum best facilities."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "What is the most common test used in evaluating soil strength?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CBR",
            "b) DCP",
            "c) Triaxial",
            "d) Plate bearing test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: All the tests are performed but the most commonly used one is CBR, which is called as California bearing test, performed in India."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "The CBR standard penetration is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.5 mm",
            "b) 5.0 mm",
            "c) 7.5 mm",
            "d) 25mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The standard penetration value of the CBR value is 2.5mm if 5 mm value is greater then the penetration test is repeated again."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "What is the minimum thickness of seal coat?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20mm",
            "b) 25mm",
            "c) 30.m",
            "d) 35mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum thickness of the seal coat required is 20mm for bitumen pavement, seal coat is a layer above the flexible pavement surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The impact value of aggregate used in the pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The aggregate impact value should not be more than 30% for aggregate used in bitumen if it is less than 30 the aggregate may be replaced."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "The abrasion value of the aggregate in pavement should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The abrasion value of aggregate should not be more than 40% for the aggregate tested by Los Angeles abrasion test, if it is more than 40, then it may be rejected."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The specifications for highway are prepared by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRC",
            "b) MORTH",
            "c) BIS",
            "d) NHAI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The specifications for the highway are prepared by MORTH, which is the Ministry of Road Transport and Highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "The number of factors considered for flexible pavement is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design factors that are considered are wheel load, soil, climate, pavement layer, drainage."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "The contact pressure is given by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pa",
            "b) a/P",
            "c) P/A",
            "d) PA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The contact pressure is given by P/A, where P is wheel load and A is area of contact."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "The distribution of circular load was obtained by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wester guard",
            "b) Boussinesq",
            "c) McAdam",
            "d) Taylor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stress distribution for the circular load was obtained by Boussinesq, in which he assumed homegenous and elastic material."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "What is the last step in the design of flexible pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Design of sub grade",
            "b) Design of base",
            "c) Design of mix",
            "d) Design of the pavement thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The last step in the design of the pavement is design of pavement thickness, after design of mix, design of sub grade, sub base and base."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "If one or more wheels act as a single load then it is called as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) EASEL",
            "b) EQWL",
            "c) EQML",
            "d) EQVL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If one or more wheels act as a single load then it is called as an equivalent single wheel load."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "The pressure in pneumatic tyres should not exceed _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10Kg/cm2",
            "b) 9.5Kg/cm2",
            "c) 9Kg/cm2",
            "d) 8Kg/cm2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum tyre pressure in pneumatic tyre is 9.5kg/cm2."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "The revised legal load of HCV in India in tonnes is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.17",
            "b) 9.17",
            "c) 10.2",
            "d) 11.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum legal load in India is considered after revision as 10.2 tonnes, before it was 8.17 tonnes only."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "The legal load considered in the benklemen beam method is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8.17",
            "b) 9.17",
            "c) 10.2",
            "d) 11.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum legal load in benklemen beam method is considered as 8.17 tonnes or 8170 kg."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "9.The load dispersion is assumed at an angle of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45°",
            "b) 60°",
            "c) 75°",
            "d) 90°"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The angle of the dispersion is assumed as 45° in the ESWL for the ease of construction and calculation."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "The equivalent wheel load factors are calculated by using _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) First power law",
            "b) Second power law",
            "c) Third power law",
            "d) Fourth power law"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The load factor follows the fourth power law for the calculation of VDF and load factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "What is the standard wheel load in Ewl factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4080 kg",
            "b) 9160 kg",
            "c) 8170 kg",
            "d) 5100 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The load is considered for only one wheel which is 4080kg, it is considered as the half of the legal load."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "The rate of growth in traffic in urban areas is assumed as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.5%",
            "b) 8.0%",
            "c) 8.5%",
            "d) 9.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rate of growth in traffic for urban areas is assumed as 7.5%, it may also vary depending on the requirement."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "The constant value used in the calculation of CSA is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 365",
            "b) VDF",
            "c) LDF",
            "d) N"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Except the value of 365, all the other constant vary depending on the lane, vehicle and traffic."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "The presence of moisture content causes _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swelling",
            "b) Shrinkage",
            "c) Alternate swelling and shrinkage",
            "d) Frost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The presence of moisture content in any water absorbed soil causes the swelling of soil and ultimately gives rise to cracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "Which frost heave is dangerous?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unlike frost heave",
            "b) Like frost heave",
            "c) Uneven frost heave",
            "d) Even frost heave"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The frost heave which is caused in cold temperatures raises the edges of the pavement, if they are uneven then it is very dangerous."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "Boussinesq assumed soil as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Homogeneous",
            "b) Heterogeneous",
            "c) Rigid",
            "d) Flexible"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The assumption by Boussinesq was the soil is homogeneous, elastic and isotropic under a circular load."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "Two elastic theory was developed by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Boussinesq",
            "b) Westergard",
            "c) Burnister",
            "d) McAdam"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The two elastic theory was developed by Burnister after Boussinesq developed the equation for evaluation of stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "Boussinesq assumed the load as a _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Point load",
            "b) UDL",
            "c) UVL",
            "d) Triangular load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Boussinesq assumed the load as a single point load acting at a depth z and radius r."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "The ratio of z/a=0 represent the stress at _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Top surface",
            "b) Bottom surface",
            "c) Middle",
            "d) Maximum stress point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The depth is zero, so the stress represented is at the surface of the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "The z is a function of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P, a",
            "b) P, z",
            "c) P, a, z",
            "d) P only"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The depth is a function of the stress, depth and radius of the load acting on the point."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "The ratio of the radius r/a=0 represents _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Center of chart",
            "b) Center of load",
            "c) Center of stress",
            "d) Center of the pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The radius is zero so it is possible only in a chart, which represents a point in the center of the chart."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "The Poisson’s ratio of soil is assumed as _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.6",
            "c) 0.7",
            "d) 0.8"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Poisson’s ratio for a homogeneous soil is assumed as 0.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "At surface the value of constant F is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.18",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the constant F in finding out the deflection is 1.5."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "The unit of deflection is measured in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) mm",
            "b) N mm",
            "c) joule",
            "d) watt"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deflection is measured in mm, cm or m depending on the requirement of the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "The constant in rigid pavement design is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 1.18",
            "c) 2",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The constant value of the pavement in rigid pavement design is assumed as 1.18."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "The diameter of the plate in plate load test is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 cm",
            "b) 30 mm",
            "c) 3 m",
            "d) 0.3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The diameter of the plate used in the plate bearing test is 30 cm, it is a rigid plate."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "What is the minimum deflection assumed in plate bearing test?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25 mm",
            "b) 0.25 cm",
            "c) 2.5 cm",
            "d) 2.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The deflection is usually fixed in plate bearing test and it varies between 0.25 cm and 0.5 cm."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "The layer which should have high modulus of elasticity is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil",
            "b) Sub grade",
            "c) Sub base",
            "d) Pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modulus of elasticity should increase as the pavement layer increase from bottom to top."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "What is the most superior material used in the pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) DBM",
            "b) WBM",
            "c) Tar",
            "d) Bitumen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The most superior material used in the pavement is bitumen which is mostly used for the surface layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "In which layer system the modulus of elasticity will be equal for all layers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single",
            "b) Double",
            "c) Triple",
            "d) Four layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In the single layer of system all the layers have same modulus of elasticity which means it is covered with only one material."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "How many types of methods are there to design a flexible pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: There are three types of methods to design a flexible pavement they are empirical, semi empirical and theoretical method."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "Empirical method is dependent on the strength of _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil",
            "b) Sub base",
            "c) Base",
            "d) Surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The strength of the soil sub grade is used to design the flexible pavement, because the sub base and base are more stronger than the sub grade, so design depends on sub grade only."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "The stress strain approach is used in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Empirical method",
            "b) Semi empirical method",
            "c) Theoretical",
            "d) CBR method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design of pavement using stress strain approach is used in semi empirical method, which depends both on theory and graph."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "CBR is a _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Measure of soil strength",
            "b) Flexible pavement design method",
            "c) Rigid pavement design method",
            "d) Measure of soil characteristics"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CBR is a method of designing flexible pavement by using the soil characteristics."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "The design charts are prepared based on _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climate",
            "b) Past experience",
            "c) Location",
            "d) Traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design charts are prepared based on the past experience hence they are not reliable, as it changes according to location."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "For which material the semi empirical method is useful?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic",
            "b) Plastic",
            "c) Rigid",
            "d) Semi rigid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the material is elastic, then it will obey hookes law, so after that limit it is not so useful."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "The CBR method was developed by _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) California division of highway",
            "b) IRC",
            "c) MORTH",
            "d) NHAI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In 1925, the California division of the highway designed the CBR method for the design of flexible pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "The soaking period in CBR sample is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 days",
            "b) 3 days",
            "c) 4 days",
            "d) 5 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The soaking period usually specified is four days which may not be sufficient for some highways."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "What is the total thickness of the pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant",
            "b) Changes with sub grade",
            "c) Changes with sub base",
            "d) Changes with base"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total thickness of the pavement remains constant as it does not depend on the number of layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "As per MORTH the specified compaction of density is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 95%",
            "b) 96%",
            "c) 100%",
            "d) 99%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: MORTH recommends a field density of 97% for heavy compaction, in some cases it recommended even 99 or 100% of lab density."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "The top 500mm of soil sub grade should be compacted at _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) OMC",
            "b) MDD",
            "c) Dry density",
            "d) Saturated density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The top 500mm layer in the soil sub grade should be compacted at OMC, to obtain M.D.D, only at M.D.D the soil gets its maximum strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "For how much amount of rainfall soaking of specimen is not required?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100 mm",
            "b) 200 mm",
            "c) 300 mm",
            "d) 500 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a rainy area which is having an amount of rainfall more than 500 mm, then soaking of specimen is not required."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "What is the maximum aggregate size in CBR method?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm",
            "b) 30 mm",
            "c) 40 mm",
            "d) 50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum size of aggregate should be 20 mm in the design of flexible pavement if it is more than 20 mm then above layers are not valid."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "The critical stress is considered in _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface",
            "b) Sub base layer",
            "c) Sub grade",
            "d) Both sub grade and surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Both horizontal stress and vertical stress are considered for flexible pavement and measured at these two layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "The design factor not considered in CBR is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weather",
            "b) Traffic",
            "c) VDF",
            "d) Growth rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The weather factor is not considered in CBR method as it keeps changing frequently, growth rate keeps increasing, VDF is a constant so climate doesn’t actually affect the CBR."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "The heavy commercial vehicles are considered if their weight exceeds __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.0 t",
            "b) 4.0 t",
            "c) 5.0 t",
            "d) 6.0 t"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The HCV are used to study the pavement design if their weight exceeds 3 tonnes."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "Axle load studies are carried out on a minimum sample of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 15%",
            "c) 20%",
            "d) 25%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum sample size of axle load considered in India is 20%."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "The overlay design is laid for a maximum life span of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 years",
            "b) 7 years",
            "c) 9 years",
            "d) 10 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maximum life span of an overlay design is 10 years, it may be also 5 years for small roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "What is the most commonly used overlay?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible over rigid",
            "b) Rigid over flexible",
            "c) Flexible over flexible",
            "d) Rigid over rigid"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most commonly used overlay is flexible over flexible, rigid over flexible and rigid over rigid are also used but flexible is the most preferred and used pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "The average vehicles considered for pavement studies are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150",
            "b) 1500",
            "c) 150 to 1500",
            "d) 15000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The commercial vehicles per day are considered as 150 to 1500 for pavement design studies."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "The VDF of a lane if the CVPD is greater than 1500 in plain terrain is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.5",
            "b) 2.5",
            "c) 3.0",
            "d) 4.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The VDF in plain terrain is 4.5 if the CVPD is greater than 1500, it mainly depends on the commercial vehicle and terrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "The VDF in hilly terrain for CVPD less than 1500 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 2.0",
            "d) 2.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The VDF in hilly terrain is less than that in plain and rolling terrain so it is 1.5, because hill roads don’t have traffic as plain terrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "The depth of rutting criterion is obtained by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro strain",
            "b) Macro strain",
            "c) Traffic",
            "d) Elasticity modulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Based on research the rutting criterion depends on the vertical strain on sub grade, which is responsible for developing cracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "The lane distribution factor on undivided roads with single lane carriage way is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The lane distribution factor is assumed as 1 on an undivided road with single carriage way."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "The least lane distribution factor value is least for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single lane",
            "b) Double lane",
            "c) Three lanes",
            "d) Four lanes"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The least lane distribution factor is least for four lane highway which is 0.45, because any vehicle can move in it’s own lane and is independent so it is less."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "The joint filling sand should have fines are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75 microns",
            "b) 85 microns",
            "c) 95 microns",
            "d) 100 microns"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The joint filling sand should have passed 2.36 mm and fines should pass 75 microns to be used in highway construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "The PQC denotes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paved quality cement",
            "b) Paved quality concrete",
            "c) Pavement quality concrete",
            "d) Paved quantity cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The PQC denotes the pavement quality concrete which is used in rigid pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "The layer not required in cement road is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub grade",
            "b) Sub base",
            "c) Base",
            "d) Surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The base course may be required but in cement road it is not mandatory, it is better if it is provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "The cement slab is provided with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Long joints",
            "b) Longitudinal joints",
            "c) Transverse joints",
            "d) Both Longitudinal and transverse joints."
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: A cement slab is provided with both the longitudinal and transverse joints in both the direction as a slab is not laid at a stretch, it may be useful for identification."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "The soil sub grade design is done by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plate bearing test",
            "b) CBR",
            "c) Plate load test",
            "d) Shear test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most commonly used test is plate bearing test which was developed by Westergard."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "Failure in rigid pavement occurs due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More compaction",
            "b) Less compaction",
            "c) More load",
            "d) Less load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The greater compaction effort does not lead to any loss but if the compaction is less then there may be a failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "What is the size of particles preferred in GSB layer of pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.075 mm",
            "b) 0.150 mm",
            "c) 0.300 mm",
            "d) 0.600 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The size of aggregate used in pavement GSB layer should be 0.075mm and have 5% fines."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "What is the failure in GSB layer of rigid pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pumping",
            "b) Blowing",
            "c) Pumping and blowing",
            "d) Fatigue"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most commonly found failure in the GSB layer is pumping and blowing, these failure mainly take place due to the water."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "The drainage layer of pavement can __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase the pavement life",
            "b) Decrease the pavement life",
            "c) Increase the pavement thickness",
            "d) Decrease the pavement thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The pavement thickness is constant and does not depend on granular sub base layer and if maintained properly it can increase the life span."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "The base course uses __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RCC",
            "b) Wet lean concrete",
            "c) Dry lean concrete",
            "d) Heavy weight concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most commonly used concrete for base is high quality concrete of lean concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "The spacing between construction joints in rigid pavement is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4.5 m",
            "b) 5.0 m",
            "c) 5.5 m",
            "d) 6.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The spacing between construction joints in rigid pavement is formed for expansion and contraction of pavement which is 5.0 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "What is the gap provided in slabs?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm",
            "b) 30 mm",
            "c) 35 mm",
            "d) 40 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slabs are provided with a gap of usually 20 mm for expansion in summer season."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "The stress in pavement changes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Daily",
            "b) Seasonally",
            "c) Annually",
            "d) Depends on pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stress in pavement changes daily according to the temperature on surface, actually it changes every minute but we can’t calculate it for every minute so assumption is taken it changes daily."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "The spacing of joint depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of joint",
            "b) Type of construction",
            "c) Type of material",
            "d) Same for all joints"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The spacing between the two joints depends on the type of joint, it may be 4.5 m for longitudinal and 3.5 m for transverse joint."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "How many factors contributing to the flexural stress of a pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most influence factors are wheel load and temperature stress in rigid pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "The life span of a rigid pavement depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic action",
            "b) Frictional action",
            "c) Location of loading",
            "d) Seasonal change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The life span of most of the pavement is dependent on the location of loading of the wheel."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "The term ‘a’ denotes?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius of wheel",
            "b) Radius of the area of contact",
            "c) Radius of the equivalent area of contact",
            "d) Radius of axle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The term ‘a’ denotes the radius of equivalent area of contact, which indicates the value of the radius of wheel in which that is in contact."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "The stresses are found in how many places of rigid pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stresses are found in three parts of pavement they are interior, edge and corner."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "What is the maximum fatigue ratio of rigid pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.45",
            "b) 0.65",
            "c) 0.8",
            "d) 0.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For a rigid pavement the fatigue ratio of the pavement is 0.45 to 0.9, in any case the value should not exceed 0.9."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "The ratio of flexibility strength applied due to a load and the flexural stress is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stress ratio",
            "b) Strain ratio",
            "c) Stress and strain ratio",
            "d) Bulk modulus"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The ratio of flexibility strength due to a load and it’s original flexural strength is called stress ratio."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "There will be no fatigue if stress ratio is kept below __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.44",
            "b) 0.50",
            "c) 0.70",
            "d) 0.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If the stress ratio is kept below 0.44, then there is no chance of fatigue, so the pavement is designed at a stress ratio of less than 44%."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "The design load is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15th percentile load",
            "b) 85th percentile load",
            "c) 98th percentile load",
            "d) 99th percentile load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The load considered is 98th percentile load which is exceeded only by 2.0% of vehicles."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "The load safety factor assumed is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.2",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 1.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The load safety factor is assumed as 1.2 for HCV, it may be even higher if it is an undivided pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "No warping stress is developed if the temperature __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Constant",
            "b) Less than normal",
            "c) More than normal",
            "d) Changes frequently"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The temperature must remain the same at both top and bottom of the slab to prevent warping stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "Proximity to sea contributes to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Warping stress",
            "b) Seasonal stress",
            "c) Climatic factor",
            "d) Weathering factor"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The proximity to sea contributes to the corrosion which is considered as a factor in the climate changes."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "The maximum stress in summer by pavement is experienced at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Morning",
            "b) Mid noon",
            "c) Evening",
            "d) Night"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most worst stress is experienced in the pavement at mid noon usually in summer it is very high."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "What are the major stresses in CC pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Wheel load stress",
            "b) Warping stress",
            "c) Wheel load and warping stress",
            "d) Frictional stress"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The major stress is caused due to wheel load and temperature, remaining all are the minor stresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "What is the unit of ‘K’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Kg",
            "b) Kg/cm",
            "c) Kg/cm2",
            "d) Kg/cm3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The modulus of sub grade reaction is the pressure per deflection unit, it was obtained by Westrergaard for deflection analysis."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "The deflection in Westergaard analysis is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.125",
            "b) 0.250",
            "c) 0.375",
            "d) 0.500"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deflection is assumed as 0.125 in Westergaard analysis, it is constant value for the deflection for modulus of sub grade reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "The Poisson’s ratio of concrete is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.15",
            "b) 0.3",
            "c) 0.6",
            "d) 1.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The Poisson’s ratio of concrete is mostly assumed as 0.15 however it may lie between 0.13 and 0.15."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "The deflection of slab is dependent on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexural strength",
            "b) Compressive strength",
            "c) Tensile strength",
            "d) Roughness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deflection is dependent on the flexural strength of the material on how it breaks."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "The stiffness of slab mainly depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Radius of wheel",
            "b) Radius of rotary",
            "c) Radius of relative pavement",
            "d) Radius of relative pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The radius of relative stiffness mainly depends on the soil sub grade reaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "If any load is placed at interior away from all edges then it is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Edge loading",
            "b) Far edge loading",
            "c) Interior loading",
            "d) Exterior loading"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The loading that takes place inside of the pavement away from all edges is called as interior loading."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "The loading which does not exist is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Edge",
            "b) Interior",
            "c) Exterior",
            "d) Corner"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The loading that doesn’t exist is exterior loading because a load cannot be outside of pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "The distance at which the crack is developed is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2.58 al",
            "b) 2.58(al)",
            "c) 1.58al",
            "d) 0.58al"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The distance is given by the equation 2.58al, where a is the radius of wheel distribution and l is radius of relative stiffness."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "Warping stress coefficient charts were prepared by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burnister",
            "b) Telford",
            "c) Bradbury",
            "d) IRC"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The charts were prepared by Bradbury, assuming it depends on seasonal coefficient and radius of relative stiffness."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "Based on topography and climate of the location which factor is estimated?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Temperature",
            "b) Pavement quality",
            "c) Pavement thickness",
            "d) Pavement design method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The thickness is the most important factor that is designed as per requirement, pavement quality and pavement method are indirectly dependent on pavement design."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "The warping stress is dependent on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Length of slab",
            "b) length and width of slab",
            "c) Thickness of slab",
            "d) Water content in slab"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The warping stress is due to the variation in the temperature of the pavement depends on length and width."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "The first thickness assumed in pavement is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRC thickness",
            "b) MORTH thickness",
            "c) Trial thickness",
            "d) Estimated thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first thickness is assumed as a trail thickness, it may be later revised after design."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "The factor of safety is the stress caused at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mid day",
            "b) Summer",
            "c) Winter",
            "d) Rainy"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The stress caused is measured at the mid day due to wheel load and temperature stress."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "What is the minimum factor of safety for rigid pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.1",
            "c) 1.5",
            "d) 1.7"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum factor of safety is 1.1 and if it doesn’t satisfy then the pavement thickness is revised."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The Westergaard equation was modified by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bradbury",
            "b) Burnister",
            "c) Teller and Sutherland",
            "d) Telford"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Westergaard analysis gave low stress results so it was modified by Teller and Sutherland at edge."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "If the flexural strength of a pavement is 45 and it’s stress is 40 then factor of safety is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.1",
            "c) 1.15",
            "d) 1.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio of the flexural strength to total flexural stress is called as factor of safety."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The pavement thickness is usually assumed in rigid pavement as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 cm",
            "b) 25 cm",
            "c) 30 cm",
            "d) 35 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trail thickness usually assumed in rigid pavement is 25 cm, if it doesn’t satisfy then the pavement thickness is revised."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "The temperature differential in coastal regions in India for a thickness of 25 cm is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 16.2",
            "c) 17",
            "d) 18"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The temperature differential in coastal regions in India is assumed as 16.2 degrees centigrade as recommended by IRC."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "What is the minimum quality of thickness in the low volume roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 35"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum grade required is M 40 but for low volume roads M 30 roads can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "The cement concrete roads are designed with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plain concrete",
            "b) RCC",
            "c) ICPB",
            "d) Bitumen"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cement slab is provided with dowel bars but it’s not considered as reinforced concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "The dowel bars are provided __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longitudinally",
            "b) Laterally",
            "c) Any directoion required",
            "d) In base of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The dowel bars are provided mostly in longitudinal direction to prevent movement of pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "The minimum diameter of dowel bar used is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 mm",
            "b) 35 mm",
            "c) 40 mm",
            "d) 50 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum diameter of dowel bar used in pavement for load transfer is 25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "The dowel should transfer __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40% of safe load",
            "b) 40% of design load",
            "c) 45% of safe load",
            "d) 45% of design load"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The dowels are designed in such a way that it should be able to transfer 40% of the design axle load."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "What is the first step in highway construction after paper work?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surveying",
            "b) Estimation",
            "c) Bill of quantities",
            "d) Evaluation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step after the office work in the highway design is surveying, after surveying the design is approved."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "The design of the highway should satisfy __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural requirement",
            "b) Drainage system",
            "c) Economical",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design of highway should satisfy economy, drainage and structural requirement."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "The economical highway can be achieved by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cheap aggregate",
            "b) Good quality aggregate",
            "c) Good aggregate and less transport cost",
            "d) More transport cost and less quality aggregate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum cost of aggregate doesn’t affect the highway cost, it is the transport cost which has a greater effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "The embankment is constructed by using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil",
            "b) Fly ash",
            "c) GGBS",
            "d) Bricks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  The soil embankment is constructed by using the locally available soil, if not satisfied we can replace it by stronger soils."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "The embankment construction should always be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Above MSL",
            "b) At MSL",
            "c) Above HFL",
            "d) below MSL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The embankment should always be constructed above HFL, as it may effect the pavement when floods occur if laid above MSL."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The part of pavement left over for drainage is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub base",
            "b) Footpath",
            "c) Ken",
            "d) Shoulder"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The part which is left over for the water to drain off is called as shoulder, it may be paved or unpaved."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The raise of ground water reduces the capacity by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 66.66%",
            "b) 51.33%",
            "c) 50%",
            "d) 75%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the ground water raises to ground level, then the bearing capacity of the soil sub grade reduces to 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "Embankment are laid __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Above ground level",
            "b) Below ground level",
            "c) 3.0 m above ground level",
            "d) 5.0m above foundation level"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Most of the embankments are laid below the ground level by cutting and then filling."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "What is the last step in design of embankment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height",
            "b) stability of slope",
            "c) Stability of foundation",
            "d) Settlement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: After the highway embankment construction, the stability of slope should be checked, settlement takes place after a few days and height is checked in design itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "If the height of embankment increases __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slope stability increases",
            "b) Slope stability remains constant",
            "c) Slope has to reduced",
            "d) Slopes need to be flattered"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The slopes need to be flattered if the embankment height is increased, if the embankment height is small then slope may be kept constant."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "The fill material used in embankment is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peat",
            "b) Silt",
            "c) Clay",
            "d) Granular soils"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The granular soil with less plasticity are more preferable in filling material."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "The settlement is due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More compaction",
            "b) Inadequate compaction",
            "c) Temperature",
            "d) Air pressure"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The settlement is due to the inadequate compaction effort which leads to excess settlement."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The stability of foundation is checked to ensure __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lateral strength",
            "b) Compressive strength",
            "c) Shear strength",
            "d) Tensile strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stability of the foundation is checked to ensure the soil satisfies the shear strength requirement."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "Stability of slopes change with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Climate",
            "b) Increase in load",
            "c) Increase in soil",
            "d) Increase in width of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The stability of slope mostly depends on the type of load if it changes the stability requirement will also change."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "An embankment is classified as high if height exceeds __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.0 m",
            "b) 4.0 m",
            "c) 5.0 m",
            "d) 6.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The embankment is classified as a high embankment if height exceeds 5.0m, if it is less than 5.0 m they may be medium height or small height embankments."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "What is the most common natural problem found in embankment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Settlement",
            "b) Stability of foundation",
            "c) Stability of slope",
            "d) Soil erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: All the problems are encountered by a highway engineer but soil erosion is a natural problem which cannot be avoided."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "The investigation of embankment should be carried out for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Twice the height of embankment",
            "b) Thrice the height of embankment",
            "c) Exact height of embankment",
            "d) Half height of embankment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The investigation of the embankment should be carried out at twice height of embankment below the ground level."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "The consolidation can be achieved faster by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clay",
            "b) Peat",
            "c) Sand drains",
            "d) Sand filter"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The Sand drains are a type of drainage system which is used to accelerate the consolidation."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "What is the minimum spacing between the two sand beds?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0 m",
            "b) 1.5 m",
            "c) 2.0 m",
            "d) 2.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum spacing between the two sand beds may be 2.5 m and the maximum is 6.0 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "The liquid limit of soil for embankment construction is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 70%",
            "b) Less than 90%",
            "c) Less than 60%",
            "d) Less than 45%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum liquid limit should be less than 70% for embankment construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The free swelling index of soil should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50",
            "b) 60",
            "c) 70",
            "d) 80"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The free swelling index of the soil should be less than 50% for the soil for good embankment."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The plasticity index for a sub grade should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 15"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The plasticity index for a sub grade should be less than 25 for embankment construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The rollers that uses both tamping and kneading is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Plain roller",
            "b) Vibratory roller",
            "c) Sheep foot roller",
            "d) Pneumatic roller"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The sheep foot roller can use both the procedure of tamping and kneading that is done by using a roller that resemble the paw of a sheep."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "The removal of earth for highway formation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Embankment",
            "b) Sub grade",
            "c) Excavation",
            "d) Filling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Ans : c\nExplanation: The process of removal of earth for construction is called excavation, it may be done by manual or machine."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "The best time to remove soil is during __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summer",
            "b) Winter",
            "c) Rainy season",
            "d) During storm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best time to remove soil is during summer, if it is removed in winter there may be chances of rain so it’s better to remove in summer."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "What is the equipment used for short haul distance of 100 m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bulldozer",
            "b) Scrapper",
            "c) Power shovel",
            "d) Hoe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Ans: a\nExplanation: The bulldozer is versatile earth equipment used for a short distance of 100m if it exceeds 100 m other equipment can also be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "The blade angle of bulldozer is usually __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60",
            "b) 90",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The blade angle of a bulldozer is usually kept perpendicular, which is always 90 degrees to the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "The precise control of excavation is possible by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scrapper",
            "b) Hoe",
            "c) Shovel",
            "d) Bulldozer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The precise control of the excavation is possible by scrapper, but they can’t be used for greater depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "The boom is supported by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cab",
            "b) Dipper stick",
            "c) Hoist line",
            "d) Crawler"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The hoist line gives the support to boom which is attached to the cab, cab is the place where controls are placed and boom is the support."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "Dragline cannot excavate __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soft rocks",
            "b) Black cotton soil",
            "c) Clay",
            "d) Stiff material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The dragline can’t exert high pressure and remove stiff materials, it can remove only soft rocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "The stiff materials can be excavated by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dragline",
            "b) Hoe",
            "c) Power shovel",
            "d) Scrapper"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:b\nExplanation: How is one equipment which can exert high tooth pressure and excavate stiff materials from the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "The equipment having a bucket is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shovel",
            "b) Clam shell",
            "c) Dragline",
            "d) Hoe"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: A clam shell consists of a bucket that is used to carry soil or any other material from a greater depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "The compaction of sand is done by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rollers",
            "b) Animals",
            "c) Vibrator",
            "d) Jetting"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The jetting of the sand cannot be done by using roller or vibrator, it requires effective techniques like jetting and pounding with water."
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The loss with sodium sulphate cycles for aggregate used for bitumen is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less than 12%",
            "b) Less than 15%",
            "c) Less than 16%",
            "d) Less than 20%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The loss of sodium sulphate with cycles should be less than 12% for aggregates used in bitumen binder."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "How many kg of binder is applied for 10m2 area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 68 kg",
            "b) 71 kg",
            "c) 82 kg",
            "d) 93 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum amount of binder to be applied depends on the thickness of the bitumen layer and it is 68 kg for 10 m2 area."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "Built up spray grout consists of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One layer",
            "b) Two layers",
            "c) Three layers",
            "d) Indefinite layers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Built up spray grout consists of two layers with crushed aggregate and bituminous binders."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "The stripping of aggregate should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 45"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IRC recommends a value of 25% for aggregates to be used in highway construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "The camber is checked at every interval of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 m",
            "b) 20 m",
            "c) 30 m",
            "d) 40 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The highway cambers should be checked at every interval of 10 m for every 10 metre square area."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "What is the minimum thickness used in bituminous macadam?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 mm",
            "b) 50 mm",
            "c) 75 mm",
            "d) 100 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pavement used in bituminous Macadam is usually of a thickness of 50mm and maximum is 100 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "The interface bond between the existing pavement and new pavement is provided by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tack coat",
            "b) Prime coat",
            "c) Bitumen",
            "d) Oil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The interface between the existing pavement and new pavement can be provided by using tack coat."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "The spreading test performed on bitumen can be checked on metal plates of dimensions is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200*200mm",
            "b) 300*300mm",
            "c) 400*400mm",
            "d) 500*500mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The test can be performed by metal plates of 200*200mm placed at 10m intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "The water sensitivity of aggregates should retain __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 75% of tensile strength",
            "b) 80% of tensile strength",
            "c) 95% of tensile strength",
            "d) 100% of tensile strength"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water sensitivity for aggregates used should retain 80% of tensile strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "The polished stone value for aggregate of surface course should be more than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15",
            "b) 25",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 55"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The polished stone value required for the surface of aggregate is more than 55, it depends on the type of stone used."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "What is the most commonly used type of concrete pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Unreinforced",
            "b) RCC",
            "c) Fibre reinforced",
            "d) Continous"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The most commonly used type is unreinforced, dowels and ties are not considered as reinforcements in slab."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "The pavement is checked for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tension",
            "b) Shear",
            "c) Flexure",
            "d) Compression"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pavement is checked for flexure because it is the factor which leads to cracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "What is the maintenance cost of rigid pavement when compared to the flexible pavement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) More",
            "b) Less",
            "c) Equal",
            "d) Depends on grade of concrete"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cost of maintenance for rigid pavement is always less than that for flexible pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "The critical stresses affecting the reinforced pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heavy loading",
            "b) Poor soil",
            "c) Poor drainage",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The extreme conditions are due to all the factors, but when they are combined the worst may occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "The steel reinforcement is placed at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1/2 of depth",
            "b) 1/3 of depth",
            "c) 1/4 of depth",
            "d) 1/6 of depth"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The steel reinforcement is usually provided at half or a little more than half of the depth."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "The excessive flexural stress can lead to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cracks",
            "b) Bending",
            "c) Torsion",
            "d) Settlement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The bending can resist a maximum flexural stress and if it exceeds it leads to cracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "The CC slab can be constructed in how many methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: CC pavement can be constructed by using slip form paver and fixed aide forms, which are the two most commonly used methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "The standard normal varaite in India is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.65",
            "c) 1.7",
            "d) 1.9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The standard normal variate is taken as 1.65, for concrete in India, it varies from county to country."
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "The positive tolerance level of sub grade in surface for concrete pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm",
            "b) 25 mm",
            "c) 30 mm",
            "d) 35 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum positive tolerance level for concrete pavement is taken as + 20 mm and negative is – 25 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "The expansion joints do not consist of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dowel bars",
            "b) Joint filler",
            "c) Joint sealer",
            "d) Tack coat"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: An expansion joint consists of dowel, joint filler and joint sealer, tack coat is used in bitumen surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "The design life for low volume roads is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 years",
            "b) 15 years",
            "c) 20 years",
            "d) 30 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The low volume roads consist of low volume traffic and its life span is taken as 10 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "The million standard axles in low volume roads is considered as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 million",
            "b) 1.5 million",
            "c) Less than 1 million",
            "d) 2 million"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The volume on low volume roads is taken less than 1 million for design purpose, it may actually be more but for ease it is taken as 1 million."
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "The low volume roads are designed as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) All weather roads",
            "b) Fair weather roads",
            "c) Flexible pavement",
            "d) Rigid pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Though the low volume road may have a lesser life span and capacity it should be accessible in all weathers."
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The type of road used for ESAL value less than 10000 is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earth road",
            "b) Gravel road",
            "c) Flexible pavement",
            "d) Rigid pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The earth road is the most suitable for less volume of road, it is a value that is obtained based on the traffic load."
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "What is the maximum limit of sub grade thickness?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 mm",
            "b) 200 mm",
            "c) 300 mm",
            "d) 400 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The prepared sub grade is limited to a maximum of 300 mm, in any case it must not exceed 300 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "The base course is generally laid in earth road for a thickness of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 mm",
            "b) 60 mm",
            "c) 80 mm",
            "d) 100 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The base course is laid for a thickness of 100 mm, it may exceed in some cases, in some cases it may be 80 mm and even 40 mm in unimportant roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "The camber depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Road",
            "b) Heat",
            "c) Wind",
            "d) Rainfall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The camber is provided to eliminate the rain that may be stored near the surfaces."
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "The plasticity index in soil used for low volume roads should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 9",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The plastic limit for the soil should not exceed 6 in any case for the soil that is used in the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "The gravel content in the surface layer can be a maximum of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60%",
            "b) 70%",
            "c) 80%",
            "d) 90%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum gravel content in surface layer should be maximum of 80% and the minimum depends on the type of the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "The minimum slope provided in a surface of cement concrete pavement is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 1.5%",
            "c) 2%",
            "d) 2.5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum slope provided is 2%, the maximum may be 2.5%. for a surface of the cement concrete pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "How many objectives of soil stabilised roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: There are two objectives of soil stabilised roads, they are to achieve roads with low cost and upgrading of existing roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "What is the biggest drawback in India for laying roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Limited roads",
            "b) Limited resources",
            "c) Limited finance",
            "d) Limited labour"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The biggest problem in developing countries like India is limited finance, so it takes a lot of time."
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "The stabilisation of roads is not done in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub grade",
            "b) Base",
            "c) Sub base",
            "d) Surface Layer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stabilisation of roads is not done in the surface layer of the pavement, because it is made of bitumen or concrete, so stabilization cannot be done."
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "The subgrade thickness is compacted to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 200 mm",
            "b) 300 mm",
            "c) 400 mm",
            "d) 500 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: For national highway and important roads the thickness is compacted to 500 mm and for village road it may be lesser."
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "The soil stability is not so good in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Black cotton soil",
            "b) Gravel",
            "c) Sand",
            "d) Boulders"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The black cotton soil is useful for agriculture, but not so good for pavement as it swell on absorption of the water and retain them as they are suitable for agriculture, plants grow very well in black cotton soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "The more thickness of the excavation will lead to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) More stability",
            "b) Less stability",
            "c) Increase of cost",
            "d) Decrease of cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The more thickness of the excavation will lead to more labour charge, which lead to more cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "The PMGSY aims to connect __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway",
            "b) Cities",
            "c) Towns",
            "d) Villages"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The PMGSY was launched to connect the villages all across the country from north to south and east to west by linking them with a nearby city."
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "The construction of soil stabilised roads is possible in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High volume roads",
            "b) Highway",
            "c) Village road",
            "d) Low volume roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The soil stabilised roads can be used in places where the volume of traffic is very low."
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "The black cotton soil is replaced in which roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway",
            "b) Low volume road",
            "c) Street road",
            "d) Village road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The priority is maximum given to the highway for laying roads, and if soil is not suitable then it is replaced."
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "What is the most commonly used material for stabilisation of soils?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cement",
            "b) Lime",
            "c) Heating",
            "d) Chemicals"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If there is no chance for soil replacement or its very costly then cement stabilised soil is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "What is the first principle of mechanical soil stabilisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Proportioning",
            "b) Compaction",
            "c) Consolidation",
            "d) Shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first principle of mechanical stabilised soil is proportioning and then compaction."
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "The non desirable property of soil is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shear",
            "b) Swelling",
            "c) Incompressibility",
            "d) Stability"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Swelling is not such a desirable property in soil because change in volume may cause great loss to soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "The maximum dry density of the soil can be achievement by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction",
            "b) Consolidation",
            "c) Removal of voids",
            "d) Removal of rocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The best method to achieve maximum dry density is by compaction of soil, as it is the easy, best and fast method."
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "The compaction of granular material is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very easy",
            "b) Easy",
            "c) Difficult",
            "d) Very difficult"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The compaction of granular material is a very difficult task as it needs a lot of effort."
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "If the grains in the aggregate lose contact, they __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Melt",
            "b) Float",
            "c) Freeze",
            "d) Sieze"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: When granular material is separated, then the grains in the soil mostly float and in cold region they freeze."
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "The n in the gradation formula is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradation value",
            "b) Gradation index",
            "c) Gradation factor",
            "d) Gradation distribution"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The n in gradation formula is called as the gradation index of the soil, which is used to denote the property of a particular soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "The value of the maximum gradation index lies between?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5",
            "b) 0.3",
            "c) 0.2",
            "d) 0.1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum gradation index is 0.5 it depends on the coarseness of aggregate, for less coarse aggregate it may be 0.1 to 0.2."
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "The mechanical stabilised soil does not depend on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gradation",
            "b) Salts",
            "c) Compaction",
            "d) Consolidation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The mechanical stabilisation of soil doesn’t depend on consolidation as it is a long process."
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "The proportioning method not in use is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rothfutch",
            "b) Triangular",
            "c) Lab tests",
            "d) CBR method"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The CBR method is a method of designing of flexible pavement, the remaining are proportioning methods."
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The percentage of chemical added in soil by weight is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 1.5",
            "c) 0.5",
            "d) 0.2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The usual volume of chemical added in the soil is 0.5% of the weight of soil if it is added more then the soil may lose it’s strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "In soil cement stabilisation the bond is imparted between cement and __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water",
            "b) Fine aggregate",
            "c) Coarse aggregate",
            "d) Soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: In the soil cement stabilisation, the bond is imparted between hydrated cement and compacted soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "Making of solid into fine powder is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Powdering",
            "b) Crushing",
            "c) Pulverising",
            "d) Refining"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The crushing of the solid into the fine powder is called as pulverising, mostly pulverised materials are used."
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The chemical that can harm the hydrated cement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Calcium sulphate",
            "b) Calcium di sulphate",
            "c) Calcium tri sulphate",
            "d) Magnesium sulphate"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The magnesium sulphate is a very strong chemical and it may even effect the hydrated cement reducing its strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "The increase of cement causes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in weight",
            "b) Increase in void ratio",
            "c) Increase in strength",
            "d) Increase in porosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The increase in cement causes the increase in strength and durability, and of water is added then it’s strength decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "Presence of unpulverised  dry lumps reduce the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Durability",
            "c) Strength and durability",
            "d) Water content"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The strength and durability of the soil are badly affected by the unpulverised powder."
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "If compaction efforts increase, then __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry density increase",
            "b) Dry density decrease",
            "c) Wet density increase",
            "d) Wet density decrease"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If compaction efforts increase, then dry density increases and wet density doesn’t change."
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": "The high temperature in soil cement stabilisation accelerates __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Dry density",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Compaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The higher temperature leads to rapid drying of the sample, which leads to the gain in strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "The additive not used in soil cement stabilisation is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sodium hydroxide",
            "b) Sodium carbonate",
            "c) Calcium chloride",
            "d) Sugar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Sugar is a retarder and it should not be used in soil cement stabilisation, whereas other chemicals like calcium chloride and sodium carbonate can be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "The BIS for soil cement stabilisation is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) British",
            "b) ASTM",
            "c) PCA",
            "d) British and ASTM"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The BIS method is based on both British and ASTM for the soil cement stabilisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "What is the soil samples are prepared in a mould of diameter?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 cm",
            "b) 10 cm",
            "c) 15 cm",
            "d) 20 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The samples are tested in a sample of diameter 5 cm and height 10 cm, by compacting them into the mould."
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "The graph between cement content and compressive strength is plotted for how many days of curing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 days",
            "b) 5 days",
            "c) 7 days",
            "d) 9 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The graph is plotted for cement content and compressive strength for a curing period of 7 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "What is the maximum brushing loss for A6 A7 soil type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The PCA recommends a loss of not more than 7% for soil type of A6 and A7, after 12 cycles of freeze and thaw."
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The plasticity index of soil cement base course should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 28",
            "b) 18",
            "c) 38",
            "d) 48"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: From practical considerations, the results obtained tell that the plasticity index should be less than 18."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "How many methods are available for the construction of a soil cement base course?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The two available methods are mix in place method, plant mix method."
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "The degree of pulverisation is checked by sieve of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 6.25 mm",
            "c) 4.75 mm",
            "d) 2.36 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The degree of pulverisation is checked by the sieve passing through 4.75 mm and it should exceed 50%."
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The non desirable property of soil after addition of lime is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High affinity with water",
            "b) Friability",
            "c) Pulverisation",
            "d) Reduction in plasticity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The soil should show less affinity towards the water, and all other changes are desirable."
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "The maximum dry density of soil lime mix is decreased by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 to 1.5%",
            "b) 2 to 2.5%",
            "c) 2 to 3%",
            "d) 4 to 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum dry density decrease by 2 to 3%, but it doesn’t effect its strength in any manner."
    },
    {
        "id": 677,
        "Question": "The structure of clay is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flocculated",
            "b) Dispersed",
            "c) Elongated",
            "d) Flaky"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The structure of clay is formed in flocks and when they react, a flocculated structure is formed."
    },
    {
        "id": 678,
        "Question": "The flocculated substances are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stable",
            "b) Unstable",
            "c) Neutral",
            "d) Depends on soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The flocculated substances are very stable, and they even remain stable under subsequent soaking."
    },
    {
        "id": 679,
        "Question": "The factor on which the property of soil lime doesn’t depend is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil",
            "b) Lime",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Curing"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The soil lime doesn’t depend on the shear, as it is a property of soil it can’t change the stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 680,
        "Question": "The increase in soil strength depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Clay fraction",
            "b) Thixotropy",
            "c) Activity",
            "d) Shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The clay fraction content in soil affect the physical and other properties such as base exchange and pozzolanic action."
    },
    {
        "id": 681,
        "Question": "The point at which plastic limit increase and then decrease is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lime point",
            "b) Fixing point",
            "c) Lime fixation point",
            "d) Lime reducing point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The plastic limit in lime stabilized soils, increase up to a certain point and then decrease, it is termed as lime fixation point."
    },
    {
        "id": 682,
        "Question": "The chemical which causes burns while working with is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Quick lime",
            "b) Hydrated lime",
            "c) Quick cement",
            "d) Sulphate resistant cement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The quick lime is very effective in stabilisation, but it causes burns, so hydrated lime is preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 683,
        "Question": "The compaction is carried out at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6% Water content",
            "b) OMC",
            "c) MDD",
            "d) Saturated density"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The strength is a very important factor considered in the soil lime stabilisation, so it is compacted at OMC to achieve MDD."
    },
    {
        "id": 684,
        "Question": "The strength of soil lime for several years after curing __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increases",
            "b) Decreases",
            "c) Remains constant",
            "d) Can’t say"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The lime soil strength increases with an increase in curing period unless and until effected by external sources its strength increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 685,
        "Question": "The substance added with lime for extra strength are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fertiliser",
            "b) Additive",
            "c) Plasticiser",
            "d) Super plasticiser"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The strength of lime alone is not enough for the stabilisation, so special substances called additives are added."
    },
    {
        "id": 686,
        "Question": "The design of soil lime mix is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) BIS",
            "b) PAC",
            "c) ASTM",
            "d) Lime fixation point"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The design of lime soil mix is based on lime fixation point, as it has no specific method for design."
    },
    {
        "id": 687,
        "Question": "What is the first step in the construction step of soil lime base course is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preparation of sub grade",
            "b) Preparation of pulverised soil",
            "c) Field tests",
            "d) Pre conditioning"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The first step after design of the mix is preparation of the sub grade followed by pulverising."
    },
    {
        "id": 688,
        "Question": "The lime soil can’t be used in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub base",
            "b) Base",
            "c) Surface",
            "d) Sub grade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The lime soil is very weak and cannot be used in the surface course, it can only be used in light traffic areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 689,
        "Question": "Increase in lime content results in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decrease in plastic limit",
            "b) Decrease in plasticity index",
            "c) Increase in plasticity index",
            "d) Change in volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The increase in lime content will cause a slight change in the plastic limit, increasing the plastic limit and decrease of plasticity index."
    },
    {
        "id": 690,
        "Question": "What is the basic principle of bituminous stabilisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water proofing",
            "b) Cohesion",
            "c) Water proofing with cohesion",
            "d) Adhesion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The principle of the bituminous stabilisation mix is to impart strength by cohesion and water proofing."
    },
    {
        "id": 691,
        "Question": "Which is the most commonly used bitumen?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tar",
            "b) VG 70",
            "c) Cutbacks",
            "d) VG 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most commonly used bitumen is cutback and emulsion, depending on the requirements."
    },
    {
        "id": 692,
        "Question": "The bituminous layer can be used in which layer of the pavement in low rainfall areas?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub grade",
            "b) Sub base",
            "c) Base",
            "d) Surface"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The bituminous stabilisation road can be used in the sub base, base and even surface course if there is low rainfall."
    },
    {
        "id": 693,
        "Question": "The soil not preferred in bituminous mix is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand",
            "b) Clay",
            "c) Gravel",
            "d) Granite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the soils other than clay are having high permeability, high clay content is not desirable as it expands."
    },
    {
        "id": 694,
        "Question": "The increase in strength in soil may be seen at an age of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3 days",
            "b) 7 days",
            "c) 28 days",
            "d) 56 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The strength of the soil increases up to a certain limit and then decreases, but for clay it will increase if soaked for long period like 28 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 695,
        "Question": "The OMC of bitumen binder is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 5%",
            "d) 8%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The OMC is usually considered based on experience, but it may be taken anywhere between 4 and 6%."
    },
    {
        "id": 696,
        "Question": "The stability of the bituminous mix is always __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater than water content",
            "b) Lesser than water content",
            "c) Equal to water content",
            "d) Can’t determine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: If a graph is drawn between the bitumen content and maximum dry density its stability is always greater than water content."
    },
    {
        "id": 697,
        "Question": "The higher compaction will result in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Less stability",
            "b) Less strength",
            "c) Less absorption of water",
            "d) High absorption of water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The higher resistance to the absorption of water can be achieved by the higher compaction effort."
    },
    {
        "id": 698,
        "Question": "The liquid limit of soil bitumen mix should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60%",
            "b) 50%",
            "c) 45%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The liquid limit of the soil based on practical considerations should be less than 40%, it is even good if it is lesser."
    },
    {
        "id": 699,
        "Question": "The bitumen giving more better results is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cutback",
            "b) Emulsion",
            "c) VG 30",
            "d) VG 40"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The emulsion gives an inferior result when compared with the cutback, so the cutback is the most preferred bitumen."
    },
    {
        "id": 700,
        "Question": "How many types of challenges are encountered in bitumen stabilisation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The major problems are choice of stabilisation, design mix and thickness of layer."
    },
    {
        "id": 701,
        "Question": "The final choice of stabilisation technique is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Labour",
            "b) Material",
            "c) Equipment",
            "d) Cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Though all the equipment, labour and materials are equally important, the final factor is cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 702,
        "Question": "The flexural strength is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRC",
            "b) Plate test",
            "c) CBR",
            "d) Shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most commonly used method for testing the strength of the flexible pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 703,
        "Question": "The mix design should take into consideration is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stability",
            "b) Durability",
            "c) Stability and durability",
            "d) Age"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The mix should take into consideration, the stability and durability requirements, strength is also equally important."
    },
    {
        "id": 704,
        "Question": "The modification factor used in base course thickness is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Granite equivalence",
            "b) Gravel equivalence",
            "c) Sand equivalence",
            "d) Soil equivalence"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In the thickness of the pavement layer the mix can’t be designed directly, so it needs some factor which is called equivalence factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 705,
        "Question": "The colloidal content in BC soils can be up to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20%",
            "b) 30%",
            "c) 40%",
            "d) 50%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The colloidal content in the soil may be up 50%, which is an undesirable property for pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 706,
        "Question": "What is the shrinkage limit value in BC soil?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0%",
            "b) 9%",
            "c) 15%",
            "d) 16%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The BC soils have a less shrinkage limit value from 10% to 15 %, which is a very high value, whereas in sand and silt they don’t exist."
    },
    {
        "id": 707,
        "Question": "The cement content required for BC soil is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High",
            "b) Very high",
            "c) Low",
            "d) Very low"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The cement content required for the cement is 15 to 25%, so it is not advisable to directly stabilize with cement."
    },
    {
        "id": 708,
        "Question": "The desert sand is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strong",
            "b) Weak",
            "c) Normal",
            "d) Unfit for pavements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sand in the desert is very huge and non availability of water is a major problem in the desert, and desert sand is very less stable, hence suitable stabilisation should be done."
    },
    {
        "id": 709,
        "Question": "The water content in the emulsion is about __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10%",
            "b) 20%",
            "c) 30%",
            "d) 40%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The emulsion in the mix consists of 40% of water, hence it is used for stabilisation of desert sand."
    },
    {
        "id": 710,
        "Question": "The earth slopes and cuts get damaged due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rain cuts",
            "b) Erosion",
            "c) Weathering",
            "d) Unevenness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The embankment and earth slopes particularly during rainfall get heavily damaged due to the formation of cuts."
    },
    {
        "id": 711,
        "Question": "The erosion between shoulder and pavement leads to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drop",
            "b) Break down",
            "c) Edge drop",
            "d) Flat drop"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The erosion between the pavement and shoulder leads to the formation of the edge drop."
    },
    {
        "id": 712,
        "Question": "The deterioration rate is more in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible pavements",
            "b) Rigid pavements",
            "c) Composite",
            "d) Same in all"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Usually the deterioration rate of the pavement is more in flexible than rigid because it’s having a less design life."
    },
    {
        "id": 713,
        "Question": "How many types of deterioration can be found in pavements?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The deterioration of the pavement is of 2 types, structural and functional, structural is related to design and functional is related to the maintenance aspects."
    },
    {
        "id": 714,
        "Question": "Which factor doesn’t affect physical deterioration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Traffic",
            "b) Climate",
            "c) Environment",
            "d) Population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The population may surround near the pavement, but it is not going to affect the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 715,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a physical factor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Formation of pot holes",
            "b) Formation of unevenness",
            "c) Freezing and thawing",
            "d) Formation of ruts"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The freezing and thawing is a physical factor, whereas the remaining all are structural."
    },
    {
        "id": 716,
        "Question": "The road roughness is measured by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bump integrator",
            "b) Laser profile",
            "c) Both bump integrator and laser",
            "d) Overlay vehicle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The road roughness can be measured by both bump integrator and laser, bump integrator is widely used whereas laser is used in advanced countries."
    },
    {
        "id": 717,
        "Question": "The uniform speed of bump integrator is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 Kmph",
            "b) 15 Kmph",
            "c) 25 Kmph",
            "d) 30 Kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The uniform speed of the bump integrator is 30 Kmph, considered to measure the unevenness."
    },
    {
        "id": 718,
        "Question": "The pavement rating of 3 is regarded as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poor",
            "b) Good",
            "c) Very good",
            "d) Excellent"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The rating of the pavement is considered from 0 to 5, as very poor, poor, good, very good and excellent."
    },
    {
        "id": 719,
        "Question": "The pavement surface value needing immediate attention is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.5",
            "b) 2.0",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 3.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The pavement surface index value needing immediate attention is 2.5, if not taken any immediate action then pavement may fail."
    },
    {
        "id": 720,
        "Question": "The damage can be caused to a well designed pavement in a hot region is by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rain",
            "b) Heat",
            "c) Snow",
            "d) Traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The surface may be not exposed to heat always, and there is no snowfall, only rain is a factor that will effect the strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 721,
        "Question": "The blockade of the longitudinal and cross drains leads to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase of water",
            "b) Decrease of ground water",
            "c) Stagnation",
            "d) Floods"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The blocking of cross drainage and longitudinal drainage will lead to the stagnation of water."
    },
    {
        "id": 722,
        "Question": "The deterioration left unnoticed will lead to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase of cost",
            "b) Increase of life span",
            "c) Increase of initial cost",
            "d) Decrease of material"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cracks or any defects may lead to heavy damage if not noticed and cause more repair cost than initial cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 723,
        "Question": "The inadequate compaction of sub grade may lead to distress in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flexible pavements",
            "b) Rigid pavements",
            "c) Both flexible and rigid",
            "d) WBM roads"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The flexible and rigid pavement are laid on the soil subgrade so they are affected by distress."
    },
    {
        "id": 724,
        "Question": "Which of the following is a cause of distress in rigid pavement only?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inadequate compaction",
            "b) Inadequate drainage",
            "c) Dowel bars",
            "d) Defect in materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The dowel bars are the only materials used in the concrete roads and the remaining defects are found in the flexible pavement also."
    },
    {
        "id": 725,
        "Question": "The maintenance operations do not involve __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Survey work",
            "b) Assessment of road condition",
            "c) Diagnosis",
            "d) Adopting the most appropriate steps"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The survey work is a factor, which is considered before the construction, the remaining steps are done before the construction."
    },
    {
        "id": 726,
        "Question": "The rate of growth of the deterioration is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear",
            "b) Parabolic",
            "c) Exponential",
            "d) Cubical"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rate of deterioration in the flexible pavement particularly is exponential curve, it doesn’t go linearly or parabolically."
    },
    {
        "id": 727,
        "Question": "The failure of the pavement which is not dependent on the design is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inferior materials",
            "b) Delay of compaction",
            "c) Settlement",
            "d) Overloaded vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The loading of the vehicles can’t be estimated and it doesn’t depend on the design."
    },
    {
        "id": 728,
        "Question": "The distress in bituminous pavement due to ineffective drainage system develops during __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summer",
            "b) Winter",
            "c) Rainy",
            "d) Spring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The deterioration rate is more than normal in the rainy season, and it may effect the drainage system."
    },
    {
        "id": 729,
        "Question": "The failure in settlement takes place due to the settlement of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fill",
            "b) Sub grade",
            "c) Fill and Sub grade",
            "d) Embankment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The deterioration in the settlement may take place due to the settlement of fill or sub grade or even both."
    },
    {
        "id": 730,
        "Question": "The maintenance works are not possible for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Shoulder",
            "b) Pavement",
            "c) Embankment",
            "d) Sub grade"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The sub grade or soil cannot be maintained as it is covered with other layers of surface."
    },
    {
        "id": 731,
        "Question": "The maintenance of rigid pavement is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Easy",
            "b) Difficult",
            "c) Very difficult",
            "d) Neutral"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maintenance of the rigid pavement is easy when compared to the flexible pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 732,
        "Question": "The desired cross slope in embankment is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The desired cross slope is 4 to 5%, as it is required to maintain the embankment dry."
    },
    {
        "id": 733,
        "Question": "On roads where the soil has been deposited should be stripped by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trowel",
            "b) Vicat apparatus",
            "c) Blade grader",
            "d) Bulldozer"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The deposited soil should either be removed by using a blade grader or suitable machinery."
    },
    {
        "id": 734,
        "Question": "The soil erosion may take place on roadside drains where the longitudinal slope is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very steep",
            "b) Steep",
            "c) Normal",
            "d) Not steep"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The erosion of the soil takes place where the longitudinal slope of the drainage is steep."
    },
    {
        "id": 735,
        "Question": "The longitudinal slope erosion can be corrected by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compaction",
            "b) Consolidated soil",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) Void ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The longitudinal slope of the erosion of soil may be corrected by using the compacted soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 736,
        "Question": "The culvert is a structure whose span is less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15m",
            "b) 60m",
            "c) 7m",
            "d) 6m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The span of a bridge which is less than 6m is called as a culvert and if up to 15 m as minor bridge and up to 60 m as a major bridge."
    },
    {
        "id": 737,
        "Question": "The slopes and edges of road embankment get eroded leading to the formation of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ruts",
            "b) Cuts",
            "c) Pot holes",
            "d) Cracks"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The slopes and edges of the embankment get eroded usually leading to the formation of ruts."
    },
    {
        "id": 738,
        "Question": "The measure not adopted to take care of the embankment failure is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benching",
            "b) Grass turf",
            "c) Stone pitching",
            "d) Rise of embankment above HFL"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Rise of embankment is not an adopted measure it is considered in the design, before the construction as it is a requirement not modification."
    },
    {
        "id": 739,
        "Question": "The miscellaneous road factor for maintenance is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface of pavement",
            "b) Shoulder",
            "c) Kerbs and median",
            "d) Geometric design"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The kerb, median and other facilities like traffic signals etc.., are considered as miscellaneous factor for maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 740,
        "Question": "The modern day pavement don’t consider loads of ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) HCV",
            "b) LMV",
            "c) Motor cycle",
            "d) Animal drawn vehicles"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The olden days pavement consisted of most predominantly animal drawn vehicles but they are not used so much now."
    },
    {
        "id": 741,
        "Question": "The CBR method in India is followed since __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1950",
            "b) 1960",
            "c) 1970",
            "d) 1990"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India since 1970s the CBR method is followed and in 1990 an additional layer called drainage layer was added."
    },
    {
        "id": 742,
        "Question": "The failure in olden roads were classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum failure of the pavement is classified into three types namely failure from sub grade, failure in pavement layers and total pavement failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 743,
        "Question": "The recoverable type of deformation is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic deformation",
            "b) Semi elastic deformation",
            "c) Rigid deformation",
            "d) Semi rigid deformation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The deformation occurred on pavement in which it can recover itself is elastic deformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 744,
        "Question": "The plastic deformation occurs in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel",
            "b) Sand",
            "c) Silt",
            "d) Clay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The plastic deformation mostly occurs in the clayey soil and it is not even partly recoverable."
    },
    {
        "id": 745,
        "Question": "The consolidation deformation is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non recoverable",
            "b) Semi recoverable",
            "c) Completely recoverable",
            "d) Partly recoverable and partly non recoverable"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The plastic deformation in pavements occurs only in a part and that part may be recoverable or non recoverable depnding on the extent of failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 746,
        "Question": "The shear failure occurs in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Elastic deformation",
            "b) Consolidated deformation",
            "c) Plastic deformation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The shear failure occurs due to the plastic flow which mostly occurs in the plastic deformation."
    },
    {
        "id": 747,
        "Question": "The deformation doesn’t increase with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in stress",
            "b) Increase in load",
            "c) Increase in thickness of pavement",
            "d) Increase in compacted soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The compacted soil, is a very important factor for the pavement, if it is compacted properly then the pavement will have less settlement."
    },
    {
        "id": 748,
        "Question": "The shear failure of soil sub grade may be attributed to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inadequate stability",
            "b) Excessive stress",
            "c) Inadequate stability & Excessive stress",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The failure of sub grade in shear may be attributed to inadequate stability and excessive stress application."
    },
    {
        "id": 749,
        "Question": "The main cause of inadequate stability of bitumen mix doesn’t include __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improper gradation of aggregate",
            "b) Use of wrong viscosity grade of bitumen",
            "c) Poor quality check",
            "d) More stopping sight distance provided"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stopping sight distance is not a property of the bitumen mix, it is a geometric design property."
    },
    {
        "id": 750,
        "Question": "The measure not adopted in reconstruction of new highway is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Providing effective drainage system",
            "b) Designing as per traffic",
            "c) Use of inferior quality material",
            "d) Use of modern machinery"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The measure not adopted is the use of inferior material, superior quality materials should be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 751,
        "Question": "Common types of unsurfaced roads adopted in India are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gravel roads",
            "b) WBM roads",
            "c) Both gravel and WBM",
            "d) Flexible pavements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gravel roads and WBM roads are most commonly used unsurfaced roads and they get damaged very easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 752,
        "Question": "The cross slope required for the correction of shoulder is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 4%",
            "d) 5%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cross slope of the shoulder required may be 5%, as they need frequent attention from damage due to rain."
    },
    {
        "id": 753,
        "Question": "The defects like pot holes, corrugation, rutting can be rectified by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trenching",
            "b) Grading",
            "c) Dragging",
            "d) Chemical treatment"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The grading is an operation that is used to rectify the defects in the initial stage, it is carried out in two stages."
    },
    {
        "id": 754,
        "Question": "The re gravelled course is checked at a distance of every ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 m",
            "b) 20 m",
            "c) 50 m",
            "d) 100 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The gravel course is checked for every 100 m interval by using a camber board."
    },
    {
        "id": 755,
        "Question": "The dust palliative not used for reducing dust is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnesium chloride",
            "b) Calcium chloride",
            "c) Molasses",
            "d) Fly ash"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The fly ash is a waste product obtained from the thermal power plant and it is a mineral admixture."
    },
    {
        "id": 756,
        "Question": "The WBM mostly get damaged in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Summer",
            "b) Winter",
            "c) Rainy season",
            "d) Spring"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The WBM mostly get damaged in the rainy season particularly due to steel vehicle drawn by animals."
    },
    {
        "id": 757,
        "Question": "The distress not caused in localised form is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pot hole",
            "b) Isolated crack stress",
            "c) Localised depression",
            "d) Liquefaction"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The Liquefaction is a phenomenon that occurs in the sand, particularly during monsoon and heavy floods."
    },
    {
        "id": 758,
        "Question": "An existing flexible pavement that develops extensive cracks is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ravelling",
            "b) Alligator cracks",
            "c) Shear",
            "d) Pot hole"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The flexible pavement which gets extensive cracks by inter connection of blocks is called alligator cracking."
    },
    {
        "id": 759,
        "Question": "Shear failure are classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Shear failure classified into two types, first one takes place in heavy traffic areas and in second type it is limited to bitumen surface only."
    },
    {
        "id": 760,
        "Question": "The rate of structural deterioration of flexible pavement doesn’t depend on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stability of pavement",
            "b) Magnitude of traffic",
            "c) Growth rate",
            "d) Climatic change"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The structural deterioration doesn’t depend on the climate, it is a functional change."
    },
    {
        "id": 761,
        "Question": "The objective of conducting structural evaluation studies doesn’t consist of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To measure the present structural condition",
            "b) Determine the drainage system",
            "c) Estimate the residual life",
            "d) Design of overlay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The objective of conducting structural evaluation doesn’t consist of estimate for the drainage system."
    },
    {
        "id": 762,
        "Question": "The existing strength of pavement can be made stronger by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Construction from sub grade",
            "b) Construction from sub base",
            "c) Construction from base",
            "d) Overlay"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The economic solution is to provide overlay for making the pavement stronger, the remaining methods may be used if the pavement is extremely damaged."
    },
    {
        "id": 763,
        "Question": "The repair cost is approximately how many times the maintenance cost?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three times",
            "b) Four times",
            "c) Five times",
            "d) Six times"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The maintenance cost if neglected for 3 years rises up to 6 times and even uptown 18 times if neglected for 5 years."
    },
    {
        "id": 764,
        "Question": "The structural evaluation studies are usually conducted for every?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 year",
            "b) 2 years",
            "c) 3 years",
            "d) 4 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The structural evaluation studies are conducted for every 1 year to evaluate the pavement strength."
    },
    {
        "id": 765,
        "Question": "The difference between existing pavement and new pavement is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Strength",
            "b) Deficiency",
            "c) Permeability",
            "d) Shear"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The difference between the thickness of the pavement between the existing pavement and overlaid pavement is the deficiency."
    },
    {
        "id": 766,
        "Question": "The Stability of flexible pavement structure depend on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sub grade",
            "b) Degree of compaction",
            "c) Drainage system",
            "d) Water cement ratio"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stability doesn’t depend directly on the water cement ratio but it depends on the design mix and quality of pavement layers."
    },
    {
        "id": 767,
        "Question": "The elastic recovery of deflection is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rebound deflection",
            "b) Elastic deflection",
            "c) Rigid deflection",
            "d) Semi rigid deflection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The elastic recovery of the pavement is considered as a rebound deflection if it doesn’t recover it is a failure."
    },
    {
        "id": 768,
        "Question": "The benkleman beam method was developed by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRC",
            "b) ASTM",
            "c) CGRA",
            "d) NHAI"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The benkleman beam method was designed by CGRA and followed in India. NHAI still follow this method for overlay."
    },
    {
        "id": 769,
        "Question": "The structural evaluation can’t be evaluated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynaflect",
            "b) Road rater",
            "c) FWD",
            "d) Bump integrator"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Bump integrator is not a pavement evaluation method, it is an instrument used for the measurement of roughness."
    },
    {
        "id": 770,
        "Question": "The slender beam used in benkleman beam method is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.5 m",
            "b) 3.66 m",
            "c) 3.8 m",
            "d) 3.7 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The slender beam dimension in length is 3.66 m, which is hinged to a datum frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 771,
        "Question": "The least count of the small needle in benkleman beam test is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 mm",
            "b) 1.0 mm",
            "c) 1.5 mm",
            "d) 2.0 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The least count for the large needle of dial gauge is 0.01 mm and small gauge is 2.0 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 772,
        "Question": "The tyre pressure in benkleman beam method should be inflated to (in kg/cm2).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5.0",
            "b) 5.2",
            "c) 5.4",
            "d) 5.6"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The plates should be inflated to a pressure of 5.6 kg/cm2, use of tyres with tubes and rib tread is recommended."
    },
    {
        "id": 773,
        "Question": "Wheel load distribution in one side of benkleman beam test is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1080 kg",
            "b) 2880 kg",
            "c) 4085 kg",
            "d) 8170 kg"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The total load is 8170 kg, and it is taken as 4085 kg on one side because it is considered as a single axle."
    },
    {
        "id": 774,
        "Question": "The clear space between the two tyres of the dual wheels should be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 mm",
            "b) 25 mm",
            "c) 27.5 mm",
            "d) 30 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The spacing is ideally considered between 30 and 40 mm, it is an ideal requirement for two tyres of the dual wheels, it may even be less or more."
    },
    {
        "id": 775,
        "Question": "The pavement whose rut depth is less than 10 mm is classified as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poor",
            "b) Very poor",
            "c) Fair",
            "d) Good"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The classification for no cracking or rut depth less than 10 mm is good, if it exceeds 10 mm they are fair, poor and very poor depending on the degree of ruts."
    },
    {
        "id": 776,
        "Question": "The test pits are maximum dug at a distance of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 m",
            "b) 250 m",
            "c) 300 m",
            "d) 500 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The test pits are dug from a distance of 250 to a maximum distance of 500 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 777,
        "Question": "The minimum length of a sub stretch is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 km",
            "b) 1.0 km",
            "c) 1.5 km",
            "d) 2.0 km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum length of a sub stretch is taken as 1.0 km, for longer pavement distances."
    },
    {
        "id": 778,
        "Question": "The depth of the hole dug for measuring of temperature is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 mm",
            "b) 55 mm",
            "c) 65 mm",
            "d) 75 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum depth of hole is 45 mm and diameter is 10 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 779,
        "Question": "The quantity of soil collected in benkleman beam method is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 g",
            "b) 100 g",
            "c) 1000 g",
            "d) 2000 g"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum quantity of soil collected is 100 g for checking the plasticity index of soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 780,
        "Question": "The deflection value D is obtained from multiplying the difference of initial and final gauge difference of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The deflection value D is given by D=2(Do-Df)."
    },
    {
        "id": 781,
        "Question": "The difference between initial and final deflection should not exceed ____ mm, for no leg correction value.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.02",
            "b) 0.025",
            "c) 0.050",
            "d) 0.075"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The difference between the initial and final deflection should not exceed 0.025m or 2.5 division."
    },
    {
        "id": 782,
        "Question": "The statistical analysis of data doesn’t require ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mean deflection",
            "b) Standard deviation",
            "c) Characteristics deflection",
            "d) Settlement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The statistical analysis of data requires mean deflection, characteristics deflection and standard deviation."
    },
    {
        "id": 783,
        "Question": "The characteristics deflection value is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dm+s",
            "b) Dm-s",
            "c) Dm-s",
            "d) Dm/s"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The characteristics deflection is given by Dm+s, where Dm is the mean deflection and s is the standard deviation."
    },
    {
        "id": 784,
        "Question": "The sum of 15 deflections is 100, find the mean deflection.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.33",
            "b) 4.44",
            "c) 6.66",
            "d) 1.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The deflection is given by 100/15=6.66, where 100 is the mean deflection and 15 is the number of observations."
    },
    {
        "id": 785,
        "Question": "The deflection correction will be negative if the temperature exceeds ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 32",
            "c) 35",
            "d) 39"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In India the temperature is considered as 35°c for evaluation of pavement because India is a sub tropical and hot country."
    },
    {
        "id": 786,
        "Question": "The Overlay thickness depends on how many factors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The overlay thickness depends on two major factors namely stability and CASA."
    },
    {
        "id": 787,
        "Question": "The VDF is assumed as 4.5 for commercial vehicle count of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1000",
            "b) 1200",
            "c) 1500",
            "d) 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The vehicle damage factor is assumed as 4.5, for commercial vehicle count of more than 1500."
    },
    {
        "id": 788,
        "Question": "The thickness of the flexible overlay is given by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) hd-he",
            "b) hd+he",
            "c) hd.he",
            "d) hd/he"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The thickness of flexible overlay is given by hd-he, where hd is the thickness of the new design pavement and he is the existing pavement height."
    },
    {
        "id": 789,
        "Question": "The spacing between longitudinal joints may be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.0 m",
            "b) 3.2 m",
            "c) 3.5 m",
            "d) 4.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: IRC recommends a value of 3.5 m for pavement, So the spacing is equal to the width of pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 790,
        "Question": "The pavement design in olden days was based on ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mix design",
            "b) Proportion of weight",
            "c) Strength",
            "d) Proportion of weight or volume"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The olden days pavement was designed based on the proportion of weight or volume."
    },
    {
        "id": 791,
        "Question": "The thickness of the pavement in olden days was ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 mm",
            "b) 75 mm",
            "c) 100 mm",
            "d) 200 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The usual thickness of the pavement in olden days were around 100 to 150 mm, due to lack of technology they used such big sizes."
    },
    {
        "id": 792,
        "Question": "The cement production in India increased by the year.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1970",
            "b) 1980",
            "c) 1990",
            "d) 2000"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: During the 1990’s the cement gained a rapid growth in production, before the 1990 period cement was imported."
    },
    {
        "id": 793,
        "Question": "The common types of failure in the cement slabs don’t include ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mud pumping",
            "b) Development of structural cracks",
            "c) Spalling of joints",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Erosion of the soil takes place only if there is heavy rain and of the soil is not strong enough."
    },
    {
        "id": 794,
        "Question": "The design thickness of the CC slab of important highway with heavy traffic is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 250 mm",
            "b) 125 mm",
            "c) 275 mm",
            "d) 300 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The range of the pavement thickness for the heavy traffic is 280 to 320 mm, of such heavy thickness is not provided then pavement will fail."
    },
    {
        "id": 795,
        "Question": "The process of mud or soil being ejected out through the joints and edges of the CC pavements is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mud pumping",
            "b) Ravelling",
            "c) Scaling",
            "d) Ejection"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The mud pumping is a process in which the soil is pumped out of the pavement edges."
    },
    {
        "id": 796,
        "Question": "The factor which doesn’t initiate mud is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Weak CC pavement",
            "b) Strong CC pavement",
            "c) Ineffective drainage",
            "d) CC pavement directly over soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The mud pumping is initiated mainly due to high deflection, ineffective drainage and cc pavement laid on soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 797,
        "Question": "The diameter of the holes in the mud jacking process is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 15 mm",
            "c) 20 mm",
            "d) 30 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The diameter of holes used for cement jacking is around 30 mm to 50 mm, it may be a minimum of 30 mm and maximum of 50 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 798,
        "Question": "If a part of cement mortar gets detached from the surface, exposing the coarse aggregate which results in a rough surface, then it is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ravelling",
            "b) Mud pumping",
            "c) Mud jacking",
            "d) Scaling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The scaling of cement concrete occurs if a part of the cement mortar gets peeled off and exposes the coarse aggregate."
    },
    {
        "id": 799,
        "Question": "The factor not related to scaling of the concrete is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mix deficiency",
            "b) Higher water cement ratio",
            "c) Good quality of aggregate",
            "d) Chemical impurities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the aggregate quality is good, then mix design will not have any defects, so good quality of aggregate can help reduce scaling."
    },
    {
        "id": 800,
        "Question": "The ravelling occurs due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Impact",
            "b) Shear",
            "c) Abrasion",
            "d) Reaction with water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ravelling occurs mainly due to the abrasion of the aggregate, particularly when fine shrinkage cracks occur."
    },
    {
        "id": 801,
        "Question": "The CC pavement is considered good quality of the unevenness index in mm/km is less than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4500",
            "b) 3500",
            "c) 3300",
            "d) 2200"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: If the unevenness index calculated by the bump integrator is less than 2200, then the pavement quality is good."
    },
    {
        "id": 802,
        "Question": "The CC pavement should be construed again if ravelling depth is more than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 mm",
            "b) 15 mm",
            "c) 20 mm",
            "d) 25 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The CC pavement ravelling depth should not exceed 25 m, if exceeded 25 m then it should be constructed again."
    },
    {
        "id": 803,
        "Question": "The poly sulphide sealant perform well uptown?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 years",
            "b) 7 years",
            "c) 10 years",
            "d) 15 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The poly sulphide sealant can perform well up to 10 years and it may even last more if maintained well."
    },
    {
        "id": 804,
        "Question": "The shrinkage cracks have a length of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 m",
            "b) 0.2 m",
            "c) 0.4 m",
            "d) 1.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The shrinkage cracks usually have a length of 0.3 m to 0.6 m and extend to a depth of 20 to 30 mm."
    },
    {
        "id": 805,
        "Question": "The probable causes for loss of surface texture don’t include ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Poor texturing",
            "b) Abrasion",
            "c) Movement of Traffic",
            "d) Use of durable materials"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The loss of surface is not caused due to the durable materials, it is caused due to non durable materials."
    },
    {
        "id": 806,
        "Question": "The surface texture may be calculated by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Abrasion test",
            "b) Impact test",
            "c) British pendulum number",
            "d) Viscosity test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: British pendulum number is a test which is conducted for the testing of the pavement frictional resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 807,
        "Question": "The depth of groove in skid resistance test is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 mm",
            "b) 1.0 mm",
            "c) 1.5 mm",
            "d) 2.0 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The depth of the groove in the skid resistance test is 1.5 mm, in which it can handle the apparatus."
    },
    {
        "id": 808,
        "Question": "The structural distress in the CC pavement is not due to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Excessive loading",
            "b) Inadequate thickness",
            "c) Long spacing",
            "d) Erosion"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The erosion is not structural distress, it is a type of functional distress, structural distress are related to design."
    },
    {
        "id": 809,
        "Question": "The method not used in structural evaluation of CC pavement is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Visual inspection",
            "b) Deflection test",
            "c) Non destructive testing",
            "d) Benkleman test"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Benkleman test is a method used to verify the deflection of flexible pavement and not used in rigid pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 810,
        "Question": "The methods of crack repairs are classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The methods of crack repairs are crack stitching, partial depth and full depth repairs."
    },
    {
        "id": 811,
        "Question": "The diameter of bars used for insertion in crack stitching method is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8 mm",
            "b) 10 mm",
            "c) 12 mm",
            "d) 16 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The diameter of the bars used are 16 mm HYSD bars which are bent into U shape and inserted in holes at 600 mm intervals."
    },
    {
        "id": 812,
        "Question": "The partial depth repairs are limited to a slab height of less than ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 150 mm",
            "b) 100 mm",
            "c) 90 mm",
            "d) 75 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The partial depth repairs are limited to a height of less than 75 mm, or 1/3rd of the height of slab."
    },
    {
        "id": 813,
        "Question": "In full depth repairs the diameter of the hole is greater than the diameter of dowel bar by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 mm",
            "b) 1.5 mm",
            "c) 2.0 mm",
            "d) 2.5 mm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The diameter of the hole dug is 2 mm more than the diameter of the dowel bar, which is useful for inserting tie bars."
    },
    {
        "id": 814,
        "Question": "The pavement condition factor for good condition is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.25",
            "b) 0.35",
            "c) 0.45",
            "d) 1.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factor for the good, sound and slightly cracked pavement is 1.0, if it gives more cracks it decreases from 0.45 to 0.25."
    },
    {
        "id": 815,
        "Question": "The process of removing and controlling excess surface and sub soil water within roadway is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway Engineering",
            "b) Highway maintenance",
            "c) Highway drainage",
            "d) Highway finance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The removal of excess surface and sub surface soil within the roadway or right of way is considered highway drainage."
    },
    {
        "id": 816,
        "Question": "The number of important factors for highway engineer are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The important factors that are considered for the highway engineer are design, construction and maintenance."
    },
    {
        "id": 817,
        "Question": "The highway drainage system consists of how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The drainage system is classified as surface drainage system and sub surface drainage system."
    },
    {
        "id": 818,
        "Question": "The surface water is obtained from ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground water",
            "b) Rainfall",
            "c) Leakage of water from water treatment plants",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Both surface and sub surface water are obtained from the rainfall, in case of leakage the water is percolated into the ground, the run off is obtained from the remaining water flowing on the ground."
    },
    {
        "id": 819,
        "Question": "The removal and diversion of surface water from the roadway is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface drainage",
            "b) Sub surface drainage",
            "c) Camber",
            "d) Cross slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The removal of land from surface and adjoining land is called as surface drainage."
    },
    {
        "id": 820,
        "Question": "The surface drainage doesn’t consist of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Camber",
            "b) Road side drains",
            "c) Culverts",
            "d) Curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As far as possible the surface drainage should be kept as straight as possible, usually curves are not the part of surface drainage if unavoidable then bends may be provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 821,
        "Question": "The seepage flow is present in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface drainage",
            "b) Sub surface drainage",
            "c) Camber",
            "d) Cross slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The seepage flow is present in the sub surface drainage which is excavated from the soil."
    },
    {
        "id": 822,
        "Question": "The water that cannot be drained of by gravity is called ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pore water",
            "b) Held water",
            "c) Gravitational water",
            "d) Capillary water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The gravitational force can’t send off the water which is present in pores, such water is called as held water."
    },
    {
        "id": 823,
        "Question": "The structure provided on the pavement to remove the storm water is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Drainage",
            "b) Camber",
            "c) Crown",
            "d) Curves"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The camber is a structure provided on the pavement to drain off the storm water, resulting from rain crown is provided above the camber."
    },
    {
        "id": 824,
        "Question": "The highest point provided on the pavement is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Crown",
            "b) Camber",
            "c) Cross slope",
            "d) Drainage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The highest point provided on the pavement is called crown, which is provided above the camber and it is not used for the same function as camber."
    },
    {
        "id": 825,
        "Question": "The highway drainage requirement don’t include ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective drainage",
            "b) Water entering the roadway",
            "c) Sufficient longitudinal slope",
            "d) Erosion free"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The water should not enter the roadway as it will cause severe damage to the pavements."
    },
    {
        "id": 826,
        "Question": "The preferable height of the water table should be __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.75 m",
            "b) 1.0 m",
            "c) 1.2 m",
            "d) 0.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The preferred height for the ground water should be 1.2 m below the sub grade. If it is less than 1.2 m it may raise upward."
    },
    {
        "id": 827,
        "Question": "The precautions should be mostly taken for drainage in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dry areas",
            "b) Semi dry areas",
            "c) Water logged areas",
            "d) Desert areas"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Special precautions need to be taken especially in the areas where there is water logging."
    },
    {
        "id": 828,
        "Question": "The increase in moisture causes the strength to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase",
            "b) Decrease",
            "c) Remains same",
            "d) Can’t determine"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: An increase in the moisture content will reduce the strength of the soil, so it should be very carefully calculated."
    },
    {
        "id": 829,
        "Question": "The excess water on shoulder in a dry region with a good drainage system causes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Water stagnation",
            "b) Floods",
            "c) Damage to pavement",
            "d) Increase of initial cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The damage of pavement is caused due to the excessive amount of water on the pavement shoulders."
    },
    {
        "id": 830,
        "Question": "The sustained contact with water cause failure due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Swelling",
            "b) Stripping",
            "c) Ravelling",
            "d) Sloping"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The sustained contact with water in flexible pavement causes stripping of bitumen from aggregate."
    },
    {
        "id": 831,
        "Question": "The damage in cold region is caused due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heat",
            "b) Rain",
            "c) Frost action",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: In cold regions when freezing temperatures are prevalent then there is considerable damage due to frost action."
    },
    {
        "id": 832,
        "Question": "The path of wheels cause damage in the form of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Undulations",
            "b) Shear",
            "c) Deflection",
            "d) Ruts and corrugation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ruts and corrugation are formed due to the heavy vehicles, and they give impressions on the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 833,
        "Question": "The swelling and shrinkage is mostly seen in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sand",
            "b) Gravel",
            "c) Black cotton soil",
            "d) Kankar"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The black cotton soil is a soil in which mostly alternative shrinkage and drying occurs, in construction of pavement the black cotton soil is not preferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 834,
        "Question": "In India for storm sewage and domestic sewage we use?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Individual sewers",
            "b) Combined sewers",
            "c) Iron pipes",
            "d) Closed sewers"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: In India we mostly use combined sewers and they are mostly open and made with concrete."
    },
    {
        "id": 835,
        "Question": "How many components are present in the surface drainage system?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The surface drainage system consists of three components they are camber, side drains and cross drains."
    },
    {
        "id": 836,
        "Question": "If the canal and drain at same level then the cross drainage structure is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aqueduct",
            "b) Siphon aqueduct",
            "c) Level crossing",
            "d) Aquiclude"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: If the canal and the drainage both are at the same level then the drainage structure is called level crossing."
    },
    {
        "id": 837,
        "Question": "What is the value of camber on earth roads?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 2%",
            "d) 1.7%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the camber is recommended as 1.7% for the earth roads, for paved it may be up to 4%."
    },
    {
        "id": 838,
        "Question": "Which is the most preferred shape of drainage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rectangular",
            "b) Trapezoidal",
            "c) Triangular",
            "d) Circular"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The trapezoidal shape is the most preferred shape of the drainage because of it’s simplicity and ease."
    },
    {
        "id": 839,
        "Question": "The longitudinal drain may be provided if the cross slope is more than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0%",
            "b) 2.0%",
            "c) 3.0%",
            "d) 4.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The longitudinal drain should be provided only if the cross slope exceeds 4.0%, if it doesn’t exceed then it may not be necessary."
    },
    {
        "id": 840,
        "Question": "The rural roads are provided with __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RCC drains",
            "b) Trapezoidal drains",
            "c) Kutcha drains",
            "d) No drainage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The rural roads are mostly provided with the Kutcha drains, because of less population they are given the least importance."
    },
    {
        "id": 841,
        "Question": "Which type of drainage most advisable in cutting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Longitudinal drainage",
            "b) Side drains",
            "c) Deep drainage",
            "d) No drainage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The most advisable type of the drainage in the cutting is open deep drainage because it is the most convenient type in cutting, remaining types can also be used if there is no alternative."
    },
    {
        "id": 842,
        "Question": "The water may be collected in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Catch pits",
            "b) Longitudinal drains",
            "c) Kerb",
            "d) Filter sand"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The water from the rainfall is collected in a typical type of catch pit, and then it is forwarded to the drains."
    },
    {
        "id": 843,
        "Question": "If the span exceeds 6m then the bridge is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Culvert",
            "b) Minor bridge",
            "c) Major bridge",
            "d) Truss"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: If the span is less than 6m it is called as a culvert, and if it is between 6 to 15m it’s a minor bridge, and if total span is 60m it’s a major bridge."
    },
    {
        "id": 844,
        "Question": "The relationship between specific yield specific retention and porosity is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specific yield+specific retention= porosity",
            "b) Specific yield-specific retention= porosity",
            "c) Specific yield/specific retention=porosity",
            "d) Specific yield*specific retention=porosity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Porosity is the sum of specific yield and specific retention, specific yield is the ratio of volume of draw down to volume of water stored, and specific retention is the amount of water retained."
    },
    {
        "id": 845,
        "Question": "The design aspects of the surface drainage system are classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The design aspects are classified into hydrological and hydraulic analysis, these two are the important aspects of drainage system."
    },
    {
        "id": 846,
        "Question": "What is the objective of hydrological analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Estimate maximum quantity of water",
            "b) Design",
            "c) Maintenance",
            "d) Repair of CD structural defects"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The main aim of hydrological analysis is to estimate the maximum quantity of the water reaching the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 847,
        "Question": "The portion of water which flows on surface is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Run off",
            "b) Catchment",
            "c) Percolated water",
            "d) Storm water"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The portion of the water flowing on the surface after percolation into the ground and remaining on surface is called run off."
    },
    {
        "id": 848,
        "Question": "The factors not affecting run off is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intensity of soil",
            "b) Type of soil",
            "c) Topography of soil",
            "d) Type of road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The run off is not afford by type of road, in national highway and state highway there may not be having more run off but they don’t affect the runoff."
    },
    {
        "id": 849,
        "Question": "The number of steps followed for surface drainage system is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:d\nExplanation: The four steps include collection, finding the drainage, determine the run off and to estimate peak quantity."
    },
    {
        "id": 850,
        "Question": "The rational formula is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q=CiA",
            "b) Q=ki",
            "c) Q=AV",
            "d) Q= CA"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The rational formula is given by Q=CiA where, Q is the run off, C is the run off coefficient and A is the area of the drainage."
    },
    {
        "id": 851,
        "Question": "The value of C is taken as ____ for bitumen pavements.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 0.9",
            "d) 0.95"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The run off coefficient may be taken as 0.9 for bitumen and CC pavements, as in these pavements water is drained off very easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 852,
        "Question": "What is the minimum velocity required in drainage to maintain flow?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Self cleaning velocity",
            "b) Sewage velocity",
            "c) Gradient velocity",
            "d) Maximum velocity"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum velocity in which the water can flow with out any pressure is called as self cleaning velocity."
    },
    {
        "id": 853,
        "Question": "The area of the drainage is expressed in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 sq.km",
            "b) 100 sq.km",
            "c) 1000 sq.km",
            "d) 10000 sq.km"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The drainage area is calculated for every 1000 sq.km for the drainage area present in the locality."
    },
    {
        "id": 854,
        "Question": "For a bitumen pavement calculate the discharge in m3/sec if intensity of the rainfall is 40 mm/sec and area of drainage is 100 m2.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 360",
            "b) 36",
            "c) 3.6",
            "d) 0.36"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Q=CiA\nQ=0.9*40*100\nQ=3.6m3/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 855,
        "Question": "The side drains and partially filled culverts are designed on the basis of ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open channel flow",
            "b) Hydrological analysis",
            "c) Pavement geometry",
            "d) Run off"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The partially filled culverts and side drains are designed on the basis of the open channel flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 856,
        "Question": "The continuity equation is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Q=KiA",
            "b) Q=AV",
            "c) Q=A/V",
            "d) Q=AV2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The continuity equation is given by Q=AV, where A is the area and v is the allowable velocity."
    },
    {
        "id": 857,
        "Question": "The desirable velocity for sand and silt are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.2m/second",
            "b) 0.5 m/second",
            "c) 0.7 m/second",
            "d) 0.9 m/second"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The desirable velocity for the silt and sand is 0.3 to 0.5 m/second."
    },
    {
        "id": 858,
        "Question": "The discharge in m3/sec  for a surface drainage of 100 m2  and a velocity of 5 m/second is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 500",
            "d) 0.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Q=AV\nQ=100*5\nQ=500 m3/sec."
    },
    {
        "id": 859,
        "Question": "The roughness coefficient is assumed in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chezys formula",
            "b) Manning’s formula",
            "c) Heigen poiuselles equation",
            "d) Continuity equation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The roughness coefficient is a constant for different types of materials, and it is assumed in Manning’s formula."
    },
    {
        "id": 860,
        "Question": "The hydraulic radius is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) A/P",
            "b) P/A",
            "c) PA",
            "d) A+P"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The hydraulic radius is the ratio of wetted area and wetted perimeter."
    },
    {
        "id": 861,
        "Question": "What is the maximum value of Manning’s coefficient for soil with heavy vegetation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1",
            "b) 0.2",
            "c) 0.3",
            "d) 0.4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum value of the Manning’s coefficient for the soil with heavy vegetation is 0.1."
    },
    {
        "id": 862,
        "Question": "The total time for inlet flow and flow along the drain is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) T1+T2",
            "b) T1T2",
            "c) T1/T2",
            "d) T1-T2"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total time duration of the inlet flow and flow of the drainage is  the sum of both the times."
    },
    {
        "id": 863,
        "Question": "If the depth of a trapezoidal section is 0.50 m and free board is 0.15 m, then the total depth is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.35 m",
            "b) 0.65 m",
            "c) 0.50 m",
            "d) 0.15 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total depth is the sum of both the depth and free board provided\nd=0.50+0.15\nd=0.65m."
    },
    {
        "id": 864,
        "Question": "The time of flow in minutes for a longitudinal drain of 400 m and with a velocity of 0.8 m/sec is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.33",
            "b) 7.33",
            "c) 8.33",
            "d) 9.33"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The time of flow=L/V\nT=400/(0.8*60)\nT=8.33 mins."
    },
    {
        "id": 865,
        "Question": "In slab culverts RCC slab is placed over abudment of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Masonry",
            "b) Pre stressed",
            "c) Steel",
            "d) Composite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: Generally the RCC slab is placed over abudment made of masonry only because other materials are costly."
    },
    {
        "id": 866,
        "Question": "The span of RCC slab is limited to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 m",
            "b) 1.5 m",
            "c) 2.0 m",
            "d) 3.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The span of the RCC slab is usually limited to 3 m as it may have maintenance problems."
    },
    {
        "id": 867,
        "Question": "What is the minimum diameter used in pipe culverts?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25 cm",
            "b) 35 cm",
            "c) 45 cm",
            "d) 75 cm"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum diameter of the pipe culverts used is 75 cm made of steel or RCC, usually RCC is only used as steel corrodes."
    },
    {
        "id": 868,
        "Question": "The GWT should be at a distance of _______ from ground level.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.5 m",
            "b) 0.6 m",
            "c) 1.2 m",
            "d) 5.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The preferred distance from the ground level is 1.2m, however it is not a problem where ground water table is very low."
    },
    {
        "id": 869,
        "Question": "The total interruption to traffic in a year should not exceed __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 45 days",
            "b) 40 days",
            "c) 30 days",
            "d) 15 days"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The interruption should be kept as low as possible if unavoidable then we must provide it for 15 days."
    },
    {
        "id": 870,
        "Question": "The clay seal may be provided if the seepage zone is at a depth of less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.2 m",
            "b) 1.0 m",
            "c) 0.9 m",
            "d) 0.6m to 0.9 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The clay seal may be construed if the seepage zone is at a depth of less than 0.6 m to 0.9 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 871,
        "Question": "The capillary control can be controlled by how many methods?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The capillary control can be controlled by two methods called granular capillary cut off and impermeable capillary cut off."
    },
    {
        "id": 872,
        "Question": "To fulfill the adequate permeability the D15 of filter/D15 of foundation ratio should be greater than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  For adequate permeability, the ratio of the D15 of filter/D15 of foundation should be greater than 5."
    },
    {
        "id": 873,
        "Question": "The D85 point size is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dp",
            "b) 2Dp",
            "c) 3Dp",
            "d) 4Dp"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The D85 point size of the filter is given by the value 2Dp."
    },
    {
        "id": 874,
        "Question": "The loss of water from leaves present on embankment is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Evaporation",
            "b) Transpiration",
            "c) Sublimation",
            "d) Boiling"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The vegetation is provided on the embankment as they can absorb the water during heavy rain, and the loss is termed as transpiration."
    },
    {
        "id": 875,
        "Question": "The roads passing through hilly terrain and leading to the villages and towns near hills are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) State highway",
            "c) Hill road",
            "d) Village road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The roads which pass through hilly terrain and leading to the villages on hills are called as hill roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 876,
        "Question": "The problem not faced in hilly regions is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extreme climate",
            "b) Landslide",
            "c) Snow",
            "d) Summer cracks in pavements"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The cracks are not formed in summer here as there is no hot temperature, but cracks may be due to frost."
    },
    {
        "id": 877,
        "Question": "The hill roads in India are not mostly found in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) North India",
            "b) North east India",
            "c) Western that’s",
            "d) South India"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The hill roads in India are found mostly in North and north east India, south India also has a few hill roads but not as many as north Indian and border roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 878,
        "Question": "The cross slope for a pavement to be plain should be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum cross slope should be less than 10, it is better if it is 0."
    },
    {
        "id": 879,
        "Question": "For a terrain to be termed as steep, the cross slope should be greater than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 25",
            "b) 35",
            "c) 45",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The terrain may be termed as steep if the cross slope exceeds 60."
    },
    {
        "id": 880,
        "Question": "The hill road should be aligned __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stable side",
            "b) Unstable side",
            "c) Based on economy",
            "d) Based on population"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation:  A hill road should always be aligned on the stable side of the mountain if we consider only economy it may be dangerous."
    },
    {
        "id": 881,
        "Question": "Which is the most common feature in hill road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) U turn",
            "b) Hair pin bend",
            "c) Speed limit",
            "d) SSD"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The most common feature in the hill road is hair pin bend, it is provided due to zigzag roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 882,
        "Question": "The hill roads are classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Five"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The hill roads also are classified as a national highway, state highway, village roads, major district roads and other district roads."
    },
    {
        "id": 883,
        "Question": "The road development in borders is taken care by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) BRO",
            "b) IRC",
            "c) NHAI",
            "d) DRDO"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: BRO is Border Roads Organisation which was set up by Indian government in 1960."
    },
    {
        "id": 884,
        "Question": "The class division for 3 tonne vehicle is named as ________ by Border Roads Organisation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) Class 9",
            "c) Class 5",
            "d) Class 3"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The class division for a 3 tonne vehicle is named as class 6, whereas for 1 tonne vehicle and jeep it is class 5 and class 3 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 885,
        "Question": "In a hill road,  the best alignment when the sum of ascent and descent between extreme points is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Maximum",
            "b) Minimum",
            "c) Maximum+minimum",
            "d) Maximum-minimum"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The total sum of the time of ascent and descent is the minimum in a well designed hill road."
    },
    {
        "id": 886,
        "Question": "The length may be provided ________ times from height.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30",
            "b) 40",
            "c) 50",
            "d) 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The permissible length may be increased by 50 times by the height for a hill road, it may vary between 30 to 60 depending on the situation."
    },
    {
        "id": 887,
        "Question": "The application that is not useful for the hill survey is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Aerial survey",
            "b) Photogrammetry",
            "c) GPS",
            "d) StaadPro"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: StaadPro is a software that is used for the calculation of structural design and other structural functions, whereas the remaining three are useful before the construction and StaadPro is useful for pavement design."
    },
    {
        "id": 888,
        "Question": "What is the total resistance length of a road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Effective length",
            "b) Effective length after friction",
            "c) Effective length after skid",
            "d) Effective length after all resistance"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Resisting length of a road is given by effective length after taking into account all the resistances including skid, friction and overturning."
    },
    {
        "id": 889,
        "Question": "The total resisting length increases due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in friction",
            "b) Decrease in friction",
            "c) Increase in pavement thickness",
            "d) Decrease in pavement thickness"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The total resisting length increases with the increase in friction, as it is mostly dependent on the friction, pavement thickness is for smooth travel."
    },
    {
        "id": 890,
        "Question": "The ruling gradient in trace cut is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 10",
            "b) 1 in 25",
            "c) 1 in 20",
            "d) 1 in 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The trace cut is done at a ruling gradient of 1 in 25, and when it’s complete we have a ruling gradient of 1 in 20, 1 in 30 may provide a gradient of 1 in 25."
    },
    {
        "id": 891,
        "Question": "What is the minimum width of the trace cut provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0 m",
            "b) 1.5 m",
            "c) 2.0 m",
            "d) 2.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The trace cut is a narrow track of width 1.0 m to 1.2 m made along the alignment of hill road to enable inspection, if more width is provided then it may cause obstruction."
    },
    {
        "id": 892,
        "Question": "Degree of stability of hill side slope don’t depend on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Type of rock",
            "b) Dip",
            "c) Ground water",
            "d) Type of pavement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The stability of the rock depends on the dip, type of rock and ground water table, any type of pavement is effected irrespective of quality."
    },
    {
        "id": 893,
        "Question": "Stratified sedimentary rocks often occur as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fault",
            "b) Fold",
            "c) Sediments",
            "d) Dip"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mostly the stratified sedimentary rocks occur as folds and not as faults, sediment is formed after the igneous rocks are converted into sedimentary rocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 894,
        "Question": "The problem which doesn’t cause landslide in the hill road is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ground water flow",
            "b) Unstable rock",
            "c) Stable rock",
            "d) Overlay of relatively weak soil"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The landslides are not caused due to a stable rock, rather they are helpful in preventing them, ground water flow and weak soil effect the landslide very easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 895,
        "Question": "The alignment of hill roads is divided into how many stages?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The alignment of hill road is divided into three stages namely reconnaissance, trace cut and detailed survey."
    },
    {
        "id": 896,
        "Question": "The general route for alignment is selected during __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reconnaissance",
            "b) Trace cut",
            "c) Detailed survey",
            "d) Detailed project report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The general route for the alignment is selected during the reconnaissance survey and after any problem is found it is modified later."
    },
    {
        "id": 897,
        "Question": "The bench marks are fixed during the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Preliminary survey",
            "b) Reconnaissance",
            "c) Detailed survey",
            "d) After detailed project report"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The bench marks are fixed and longitudinal and cross section are obtained during the detailed survey."
    },
    {
        "id": 898,
        "Question": "What is the strip length to be surveyed on the straight alignment?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 m",
            "b) 10 m",
            "c) 15 m",
            "d) 30 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The strip length required to be surveyed on the straight paths is 15 m and on curves it is 30 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 899,
        "Question": "What is the speed limit on the national highway on hill road in Kmph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60",
            "b) 50",
            "c) 40",
            "d) 30"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The speed limit on the national highway for hill road is 50 Kmph and on curves it is 30 Kmph, in plain rotary it is 40 Kmph and on plain it is 60 Kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 900,
        "Question": "What is the minimum right of way distance in exceptional cases?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7 m",
            "b) 5 m",
            "c) 3 m",
            "d) 4 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum right of way required is 5 m but in exceptional cases it should be 3 m, it is good if it is 7m."
    },
    {
        "id": 901,
        "Question": "The pavement width for a single lane road on a hill is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.5 m",
            "b) 3.75 m",
            "c) 7.0 m",
            "d) 7.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The pavement width required for a single lane pavement is 3.75 m and 7 m for two lanes, on the national highway it is 7.5m."
    },
    {
        "id": 902,
        "Question": "The flatter camber may be provided if the road has a longitudinal gradient greater than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 40",
            "b) 1 in 35",
            "c) 1 in 30",
            "d) 1 in 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The flatter camber may be provided if the longitudinal gradient is greater than 1 in 20, if it is 1 in 30 or 1 in 45, then a cross slope may be provided."
    },
    {
        "id": 903,
        "Question": "The camber for the earth roads should be never less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4%",
            "b) 3.75%",
            "c) 3.5%",
            "d) 3.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The camber value recommend for the earth roads in hill alignment is 3.0 to 4.0%, so it should be never less than 3.0%.it may vary depending on the type of road like for bitumen it is 4.0%."
    },
    {
        "id": 904,
        "Question": "What is the stopping sight distance for a speed limit of 50 Kmph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 m",
            "b) 40 m",
            "c) 60 m",
            "d) 120 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The stopping sight distance as recommended by IRC is 60 m for a speed of 50 Kmph, for the value of 40,30 the SSD is 40m and 30 m, 120 m is the ISD."
    },
    {
        "id": 905,
        "Question": "What is the intermediate sight distance for a speed limit of 50 Kmph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 120 m",
            "b) 60 m",
            "c) 40 m",
            "d) 30 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The intermediate sight distance is equal to twice the stopping sight distance."
    },
    {
        "id": 906,
        "Question": "What is the maximum super elevation on snow bound area?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.0%",
            "b) 5.0%",
            "c) 7.0%",
            "d) 10.0%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum permissible slope is 10% in hill roads, but in snow area it is 7.0% only."
    },
    {
        "id": 907,
        "Question": "The minimum sufficient straight distance between the transitional ends for reverse curves is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3.0 m",
            "b) 5.0 m",
            "c) 9.0 m",
            "d) 12.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum distance between the two transitional ends for reverse curves is 9.0 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 908,
        "Question": "The absolute minimum radius of the curve in snow bound area is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 60 m",
            "b) 70 m",
            "c) 80 m",
            "d) 90 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum absolute radius of the snow bound area as recommended by IRC is 60 m, it may be up to 90 m depending on the area."
    },
    {
        "id": 909,
        "Question": "What is the extra width on a hill road with 300 m radius?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0",
            "b) 0.6 m",
            "c) 0.9 m",
            "d) 1.2 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: There is no requirement of the extra width on a curve of radius 300 m, whereas for radius of 100 to 300 m extra widening may be 0.6 m, 0.9 m and 1.2 m depending on the requirement and terrain."
    },
    {
        "id": 910,
        "Question": "For a speed of 30 Kmph, and radius of 30 m, the length of the transition curve is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 15 m",
            "b) 30 m",
            "c) 45 m",
            "d) 60 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: IRC recommends that, for a speed of 30 Kmph and radius of 30 m, the length of the transition curve is 30 m, the values change depending on the speed and length of the transition curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 911,
        "Question": "What is the minimum speed limit design for hair pin bend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 Kmph",
            "b) 30 Kmph",
            "c) 40 Kmph",
            "d) 50 Kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum speed limit in the hair pin bend is 20 Kmph and if it exceeds it there may be a chance of overturning."
    },
    {
        "id": 912,
        "Question": "What is the super elevation in the circular portion of the curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 5",
            "b) 1 in 7",
            "c) 1 in 10",
            "d) 1 in 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The super elevation on the circular portion of the curve is 1 in 10 as suggested by IRC, it may be maximum up to 10%, but 7% is safe."
    },
    {
        "id": 913,
        "Question": "What is the maximum gradient in the curve?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 30",
            "b) 1 in 40",
            "c) 1 in 50",
            "d) 1 in 60"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum permissible gradient in the circular curve portion is 1 in 40, in plain region it varies from 1 in 30 to 1 in 60."
    },
    {
        "id": 914,
        "Question": "The approach gradient should not be steeper than _______% for 40 m.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The approach gradient should not be steeper than 5% for 40 m as recommended by IRC, it is permissible by a slight change but if they exceed then there is a change required for the geometric design."
    },
    {
        "id": 915,
        "Question": "What is the minimum carriage way width for MDR?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6.0 m",
            "b) 6.5 m",
            "c) 7.5 m",
            "d) 8.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum carriage way width for MDR is 7.5 m and for village road it is 6.5 m, and 7.0 m for 2 lane national highway."
    },
    {
        "id": 916,
        "Question": "The minimum straight length between any two successive hair pin bend should not be less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 m",
            "b) 40 m",
            "c) 60 m",
            "d) 70 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum straight length between any two successive hair pin bend is 60 m excluding the circular curve and transition curve."
    },
    {
        "id": 917,
        "Question": "The ruling gradient in steep terrain upto 3 km height in % is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 8",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 7",
            "d) 7.5"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The ruling, limiting and exceptional gradient above 3000 m are 6, 7 and 8 respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 918,
        "Question": "The compensated gradient should not be flatter than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4%",
            "b) 3%",
            "c) 2%",
            "d) 1%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The maximum permissible gradient is 75/R, but they should not be flatter than 4.0%."
    },
    {
        "id": 919,
        "Question": "The value recommended by IRC for a deviation angle of 0.16 and the design speed of 30 Kmph, the length of the summit curve is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 40 m",
            "b) 75 m",
            "c) 100 m",
            "d) 200 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The value of the length of the summit curve is 100 m for a deviation angle of 0.16 and design speed of 30 Kmph, it varies depending on the deviation angle and speed limit."
    },
    {
        "id": 920,
        "Question": "What is the value of the valley curve when compared with the summit curve for the same design speed may be best justified by?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Valley curve value is greater",
            "b) Summit curve value is greater",
            "c) Both are equal",
            "d) Depends on the deviation angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The value of the valley curve or summit curve may be greater depends upon the deviation angle."
    },
    {
        "id": 921,
        "Question": "What is the minimum radius of inner curve in hair pin bend?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10 m",
            "b) 12 m",
            "c) 14 m",
            "d) 16 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The minimum radius of the innermost curve for a hair pin bend is 14 m as recommended by IRC, if there is enough space they may be up to 16 m also."
    },
    {
        "id": 922,
        "Question": "What is the maximum gradient compensation for a pavement of the radius 150 m?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1%",
            "b) 2%",
            "c) 3%",
            "d) 4%"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The maximum gradient compensation is 75/R, which is 75/150=2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 923,
        "Question": "The right of way width in normal area for a two lane national highway is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 18 m",
            "b) 24 m",
            "c) 36 m",
            "d) 45 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum right of way width for a 2 lane national highway is 24 m in normal cases and 18 m in exceptional cases, if illegally occupied then they may be up to 45 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 924,
        "Question": "What is the minimum design speed on the major district road of hill?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 30 Kmph",
            "b) 40 Kmph",
            "c) 50 Kmph",
            "d) 20 Kmph"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The minimum design speed is 30 Kmph, maximum is 40 and for steep terrain it is 20 and maximum on highway is 50 Kmph."
    },
    {
        "id": 925,
        "Question": "What is the width of a pavement of 2 lane national highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7.0 m",
            "b) 3.75 m",
            "c) 8.80 m",
            "d) 3.00 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The width of a pavement of a two lane national highway is 7.0 m, for single lane it is 3.75 m and including parapet it is 8.8 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 926,
        "Question": "What is the minimum setback?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4 m",
            "b) 0.2 m",
            "c) 3.0 m",
            "d) 5.0 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Desirable setback is 5.0m, whereas minimum is 3.0m, near rocks it may be reduced by 0.4m and 0.2 m in other cases."
    },
    {
        "id": 927,
        "Question": "What is the camber for high bitumen road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.7",
            "b) 2.0",
            "c) 2.5",
            "d) 3.0"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The camber for high type bitumen is 1.7 to 2.5 and for thin it is 2.0 to 2.5, for gravel it is 2.5 to 3.0%."
    },
    {
        "id": 928,
        "Question": "What is the SSD value for speed of 20 Kmph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 20 m",
            "b) 40 m",
            "c) 25 m",
            "d) 50 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The SSD value of the vehicle is same as the speed of the vehicle upto 40 Kmph and thereafter it increases slightly."
    },
    {
        "id": 929,
        "Question": "What is the ISD value of the hill road with a speed of 50 Kmph?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 50m",
            "b) 100m",
            "c) 60m",
            "d) 120m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The ISD value is twice the value of the SSD, but after 40kmph it increases slightly, so it is considered as 120m."
    },
    {
        "id": 930,
        "Question": "What is the minimum super elevation?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7%",
            "b) 10%",
            "c) Camber",
            "d) Longitudinal slope"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The maximum super elevation is 7%, on hills it is 10%, and for drainage it is considered as camber or cross slope."
    },
    {
        "id": 931,
        "Question": "On which road the maximum radius is provided?",
        "Options": [
            "a) National highway",
            "b) MDR",
            "c) ODR",
            "d) VR"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: National highway and state highway have the same value of 80m, whereas 50,30 and 20 are provided on the MDR, ODR and VR respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 932,
        "Question": "The maximum gradient compensation for a radius of 150 m is _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Maximum gradient compensation=75/R\n=75/150\n=2%."
    },
    {
        "id": 933,
        "Question": "The length of valley curve depends on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed limit",
            "b) deviation angle",
            "c) Centrifugal acceleration",
            "d) Speed limit and deviation angle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The length of the valley curve is dependent both on speed limit and deviation angle, for a speed limit of 50 Kmph and deviation angle of 1.0 the length of the curve is 100m, for the speed of 30 Kmph and deviation of 0.08, length is 30m."
    },
    {
        "id": 934,
        "Question": "The number of steps involved in the construction of hill roads are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The construction of hill road includes trace cut, jungle clearance, earth work excavation and rock cutting."
    },
    {
        "id": 935,
        "Question": "The hard rock is permitted to over hang the road forming a __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Half tunnel",
            "b) Full tunnel",
            "c) 3/4 tunnel",
            "d) 1/4 tunnel"
        ],
        "Answer": ": a\nExplanation: If the rock strata slopes down into the hill side, then the hard rock is permitted to over hang the road forming half a tunnel."
    },
    {
        "id": 936,
        "Question": "Where there is insufficient time for blasting the alternative method is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cliff gallery",
            "b) Cradles",
            "c) Excavation",
            "d) Both cliff gallery and cradle"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The blasting may not be useful every time, and if there is no sufficient time, then cradles and cliff galleries are alternatives."
    },
    {
        "id": 937,
        "Question": "What is the most important structure in a hill road?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Retaining wall",
            "b) Pavement",
            "c) Drainage",
            "d) Security force"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer:a\nExplanation: The retaining wall is the most important structure in a hill road as it provides adequate stability."
    },
    {
        "id": 938,
        "Question": "The best type of material for retaining wall is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Concrete",
            "b) Brick masonry",
            "c) Stone masonry",
            "d) Composite"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The best type of material for the retaining wall is stone masonry as it permits the drainage to drain off easily."
    },
    {
        "id": 939,
        "Question": "The general minimum width adopted for the retaining wall is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.3 m",
            "b) 0.45 m",
            "c) 0.6 m",
            "d) 0.9 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The minimum width of the retaining wall adopted is 0.45 m, and as a thumb rule we use 0.5h to obtain the width of the retaining wall, but never less than 0.45 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 940,
        "Question": "The typical retaining wall is less than __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6 m",
            "b) 5 m",
            "c) 4 m",
            "d) 3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The height of a typical retaining wall may be greater than 6 m, but only for special purpose, the height of the retaining wall usually never exceeds 6 m."
    },
    {
        "id": 941,
        "Question": "The width of the retaining wall foundation is taken as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.4h+0.3 m",
            "b) 0.3h+0.3 m",
            "c) 0.2h+0.3 m",
            "d) 0.1h+ 0.3 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The width of the retaining wall foundation is given by 0.4h+0.3, where h is the height of the retaining wall and 0.3 is the width at top."
    },
    {
        "id": 942,
        "Question": "The foundation bed is provided with a downward slope of __________ towards the hill side.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1 in 6",
            "b) 1 in 5",
            "c) 1 in 3",
            "d) 1 in 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The foundation bed is provided with a slope of 1 in 6 or 1 in 4 towards the hill side."
    },
    {
        "id": 943,
        "Question": "The thickness of the pitching done by stone masonry to avoid erosion due to water is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.1 m",
            "b) 0.3 m",
            "c) 1.0 m",
            "d) 1.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The embankment slopes are normally protected with a rough stone pitching of about 0.3 m, to avoid erosion due to water flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 944,
        "Question": "Catch water drains, sloping drain, road side drains, catch pit and culverts are periodically cleared to prevent __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Landslide",
            "b) Over flow of water",
            "c) Earthquake",
            "d) Snowfall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All are drainage structures and they are maintained periodically to prevent overflow of water, landslide may cause earthquake and in hilly regions there will be a snowfall but primary purpose is to prevent overflow of water."
    },
    {
        "id": 945,
        "Question": "The preventive measure adopted in hill road don’t include __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stabilization of soil",
            "b) Grass turf",
            "c) Stone masonry",
            "d) Brick masonry"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: Stone masonry is advisable in hill road as, brick masonry is difficult and as brick joints consists of mortar, seepage may be a problem."
    },
    {
        "id": 946,
        "Question": "The problems in snowfall region, of snow is not cleared is overcome by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hill markers",
            "b) Snow markers",
            "c) Traffic signal",
            "d) Closing the road"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Mostly in peak snowfall region, the road is closed, but if it is extremely necessary then snow markers may be used."
    },
    {
        "id": 947,
        "Question": "The important structure constructed above the road with out impacting the load is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Gallery",
            "b) Drainage",
            "c) Camber",
            "d) Crown"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The gallery is a special type of structure which is used for the snow to slide without impacting the load, crown is the highest point, camber is used to prevent the drainage."
    },
    {
        "id": 948,
        "Question": "The frequent problem on the hill road is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Earthquake",
            "b) Landslide",
            "c) Soil erosion",
            "d) Seepage"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All the problems are frequent, but landslide occur very frequently and special care should be taken for landslide."
    },
    {
        "id": 949,
        "Question": "The landslide denotes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Downward and upward movement of hill slope material",
            "b) Disintegration of rocks",
            "c) Earthquake on hill",
            "d) Breaking of rock"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The landslides are a problem which is caused due to earthquake and landslide ultimately leading to the disintegration of rocks and they cause upward and downward movement."
    },
    {
        "id": 950,
        "Question": "The landslide doesn’t take place due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sliding",
            "b) Falling",
            "c) Flowing",
            "d) Breaking"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The landslides take place only due to sliding, flowing and falling."
    },
    {
        "id": 951,
        "Question": "The failure of landslide is classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The landslides are classified as slides, falls, flows and complex slides."
    },
    {
        "id": 952,
        "Question": "The failure due to shear occurs in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slides",
            "b) Falls",
            "c) Flows",
            "d) Complex slides"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In slides the movement is caused due to shear failure along one or several surfaces, in complex slides the failure occurs from a combination of slides and falls or slides and flow."
    },
    {
        "id": 953,
        "Question": "The measure not advisable to prevent landslide is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soil nailing",
            "b) Geo synthetic fibre",
            "c) Soil stabilization by any method",
            "d) Retaining wall"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The soil stabilization should not be done by any method, it depends on many factors like soil, slope stability and other factors."
    },
    {
        "id": 954,
        "Question": "The studies prepared for environmental studies are called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) EIA",
            "b) Environmental study",
            "c) Environment assessment",
            "d) Environment conservation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The EIA denotes the environmental impact assessment, in which the road side development is assessed based on the impact by using environment studies and environmental assessment."
    },
    {
        "id": 955,
        "Question": "The pressing problems on the existing highway are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Encroachment",
            "b) Ribbon development",
            "c) Both encroachment and ribbon development",
            "d) Traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Illegal encroachment and ribbon development are most common particularly in the rural areas, it’s very difficult in encroached areas for the development."
    },
    {
        "id": 956,
        "Question": "The number of factors to be considered during the road side development studies are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Three",
            "b) Four",
            "c) Five",
            "d) Six"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The factors include highway factors, highway traffic operation factors, maintenance aspects, road user amenities, road side plantation and general amenities."
    },
    {
        "id": 957,
        "Question": "The cross drainage structure of a highway is considered in which aspect?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Highway factors",
            "b) Highway traffic factors",
            "c) Maintenance aspects",
            "d) Road user amenities"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The cross drainage structure is considered in the highway factors which includes the geometry and drainage works, highway traffic and road users are also benefitted by the drainage system."
    },
    {
        "id": 958,
        "Question": "The compensation for loss of land in agricultural areas should be paid __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) During the planning stage",
            "b) Before construction of highway",
            "c) After completion of the highway",
            "d) Not required"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: As farmers have only agricultural land for their living, the compensation should be paid well before the construction of the highway project."
    },
    {
        "id": 959,
        "Question": "The point that should not be considered for a better highway is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Smooth alignment",
            "b) Small right of way",
            "c) Flat slopes",
            "d) Suitable plantation"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The right of way for a national highway should be wide enough and it should be available for further expansion, flat slopes with camber and smooth alignment and trees for plantation are the best alignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 960,
        "Question": "The planting of trees along road side is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arboriculture",
            "b) Geometry design",
            "c) Green belt",
            "d) Garden"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The planting of the trees along the road side is called as arboriculture, in few cities like Visakhapatnam, Andhra Pradesh a green belt is maintained and garden is also provided but the planting of trees is called arboriculture."
    },
    {
        "id": 961,
        "Question": "The trees in urban areas are provided for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beauty and landscape",
            "b) For fruits",
            "c) To provide shade",
            "d) To provide a cool weather"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: In urban areas most of the trees can’t provide shade due to the place restriction, but most of them provide beauty, shade can’t be expected till 20 years and fruits are not edible in a polluted zone."
    },
    {
        "id": 962,
        "Question": "What is the desirable distance for a tree from the carriage way?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.0 m",
            "b) 1.5 m",
            "c) 2.0 m",
            "d) 2.5 m"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum desirable distance from the edge of the pavement is 2.5m and 12m from the centre of the pavement."
    },
    {
        "id": 963,
        "Question": "The number of trees required for 1 km of length in nursery are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 100",
            "b) 150",
            "c) 180",
            "d) 270"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The minimum number of the trees required in the new avenue of a nursery for one kilometre length are 270 in new avenue and 150 in old, 100 and 150 in new and old sites respectively."
    },
    {
        "id": 964,
        "Question": "The improvement in highway leads to the following.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Increase in vehicle operation cost",
            "b) Decreased comfort to passenger",
            "c) Reduction in accident rate",
            "d) Difficulty in driving"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The improvement in highway leads to reduction in the vehicle operation cost, saving time, reduction in accident rate and increased comfort of passengers."
    },
    {
        "id": 965,
        "Question": "Several highway are implemented by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Government",
            "b) Private",
            "c) Public private partnership",
            "d) Depends on the requirement"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: Most of the highway are constructed by private companies and maintained by government, some may be government, some may be private but most are public private partnership."
    },
    {
        "id": 966,
        "Question": "The improvement benefits of roads don’t include which type?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improvement in city",
            "b) Improvement in a district",
            "c) Improvement in a state",
            "d) Improvement in between two countries"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The improvement may never take place between two countries as it is a concern regarding security, the Improvement takes place in city, district state and country."
    },
    {
        "id": 967,
        "Question": "The benefits due to the road improvement are classified into how many types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) One",
            "b) Two",
            "c) Three",
            "d) Four"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The benefits are classified into two types namely tangible and intangible benefits, tangible are which can be measured and intangible are related to social aspects."
    },
    {
        "id": 968,
        "Question": "The social facilities like medical services, educational and recreation facilities are classified as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tangible benefits",
            "b) Intangible benefits",
            "c) Tangible & Intangible benefits",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: All these are related to social aspects as they are not tangible."
    },
    {
        "id": 969,
        "Question": "The cost of the vehicle operation and time for unit distance may be represented by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) T=a+b+c",
            "b) T=a+ (b+c)/speed",
            "c) T=a+b",
            "d) T=a"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: ‘a’ is the running cost per unit distance, ‘b’ is a fixed hourly cost and ‘c’ is the portion of cost depending on speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 970,
        "Question": "The rate of fuel consumption for every motor cycle will be at __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low speed",
            "b) High speed",
            "c) Optimum speed",
            "d) Zero speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The optimum speed is a speed limit in which neither the bike is going fast nor slow, it usually is between 30-45 Kmph for bikes."
    },
    {
        "id": 971,
        "Question": "The unevenness index in terms of the international roughness index is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UI=IRI",
            "b) UI=IRI/2",
            "c) UI=IRI/3",
            "d) UI=(IRI)1.12"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The UI is the unevenness index and IRI is the international roughness index, UI is in mm/km and IRI is in m/km."
    },
    {
        "id": 972,
        "Question": "As the unevenness index increases there is no substantial increase in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fuel consumption",
            "b) Wear and rear of tyres",
            "c) Vehicle maintenance cost",
            "d) Increase of speed"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As there is an increase in the unevenness index, there is no substantial increase in speed, instead it decreases."
    },
    {
        "id": 973,
        "Question": "What is the maximum life span assumed for the highway?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 70 years",
            "b) 80 years",
            "c) 90 years",
            "d) 100 years"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The life span for the right of way is assumed between 75 to 100 years, and the maximum life span assumed is 100, it may also be 70,80 and 90 depending on the pavement design."
    },
    {
        "id": 974,
        "Question": "The average annual highway cost for a road system may be summed up by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ca=H+T+M+Cr",
            "b) Ca=H+T+M-Cr",
            "c) Ca=H+T",
            "d) Ca=H"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average cost of the annual road system is the sum of all costs like average cost of highway administration, operation and maintenance and also the recovery fund."
    },
    {
        "id": 975,
        "Question": "The CRF denotes __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Central Road Fund",
            "b) Capital Recovery Fund",
            "c) Capital Recovery Factor",
            "d) Central Research Fund"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The first cost of a capital improvement is converted into equivalent annual cost which is called capital recovery factor."
    },
    {
        "id": 976,
        "Question": "The Vs in average annual capital cost represents?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Savage value",
            "b) Salvage value",
            "c) Waste value",
            "d) Usable value"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: Salvage is the income available after the structure has almost completed the life span."
    },
    {
        "id": 977,
        "Question": "If the principal is P and rate of interest is i and it has to be paid in n years then, the sum S is given by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) P(1+i)",
            "b) P(1-i)",
            "c) P/I",
            "d) P(1+i)n"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The compound interest is calculated for every year and it’s leived on the preceding interest."
    },
    {
        "id": 978,
        "Question": "What is the first step in economic analysis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Determine the AADT",
            "b) Estimate growth rate",
            "c) Assessment of traffic route",
            "d) Estimate additional traffic"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: a\nExplanation: The average annual daily traffic is required for the completion of the remaining steps."
    },
    {
        "id": 979,
        "Question": "The method not used in economic analysis is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Annual cost",
            "b) Rate of return",
            "c) Benefit cost ratio",
            "d) Floating car"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: The floating car method is a method that is used for the estimation of the traffic, whereas the remaining are methods of analysis of the cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 980,
        "Question": "The savings in annual road user costs, annual savings in accident costs and capital cost of Improvement are parameters used in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Annual cost method",
            "b) Rate of return method",
            "c) Benefit cost ratio",
            "d) None"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The transport laboratory of London has developed this method in which a rate of return is obtained by these parameters, the remaining methods don’t require these parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 981,
        "Question": "The ratio of annual benefit from improvement to annual cost of the improvement is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Benefit",
            "b) Cost",
            "c) Benefit cost ratio",
            "d) Maintenance cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: c\nExplanation: The ratio of annual benefit from the improvement to annual cost of the improvement is called benefit cost ratio, benefit is the profit, cost is the investment and maintenance cost is after the investment."
    },
    {
        "id": 982,
        "Question": "The national highway act was ammended in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) April 1956",
            "b) June 1995",
            "c) July 1956",
            "d) August 1995"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: b\nExplanation: The national highway act 1956, was amended in June 1995, it was actually planned in April 1956."
    },
    {
        "id": 983,
        "Question": "As on April 2009, how many projects have been completed on BOT basis?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 42",
            "c) 25",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": "Answer: d\nExplanation: As on April 2009, twenty five projects have been sanctioned and nine projects were completed by April 2009 and in other proposals 42 projects were remaining in which 5 are completed."
    }
]